<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-15T02:00:17-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">btruhand - scattering of thoughts</title><subtitle>Btruhand's blogging outlet, ranging from technical writeups to social opions</subtitle><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Ohmmmm, that seems like the FED</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/10/16/ohmmm-that-is-FED" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ohmmmm, that seems like the FED" /><published>2021-10-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-10-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/10/16/ohmmm-that-is-FED</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/10/16/ohmmm-that-is-FED">&lt;p&gt;Recently I have been dabbling a bit more into cryptocurrencies finding interesting projects and communities. Of course, there is the investment portion of it, but there is also the educational and pure interest part of it. Since I’ve been more into economics and finance lately and being a part of what media likes to call the digital generation, cryptocurrency has become more attractive as an interest. One of the most economically interesting cryptocurrency project that I have gotten to know is the [Olympus] project. What makes it interesting is that it is a project that is trying to become a monetary reserve system of Ethereum, that is, it is tyring to become a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Reserve&quot;&gt;FED&lt;/a&gt;-like entity, with cryptocurrency and decentralization twist along with a different monetary policy outlook&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I would like to help readers (you) better understand Olympus’s economic models and their implications, to the best of my ability and understanding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I will be using several cryptocurrency terminologies which may seem foreign to those that have never delved into cryptocurrencies before. Such terminologies will be &lt;em&gt;italicized&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I am not affiliated with Olympus, nor do I own (at the time of this writing) any investments in Olympus’s products. I am not a financial advisor, and you should not take the content here as investment advise. The information and opinions in this post are solely mine, and are published for informational purposes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ohm-a-backed-currency&quot;&gt;Ohm: A backed currency&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; is the currency circulated by Olympus. It is a currency that is backed against assets held in the Olympus treasury of which currently primarily consits of &lt;em&gt;stablecoins&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;liquidity provider (LP) tokens&lt;/em&gt;, and several accepted cryptocurrencies. To be more precise, it is not the assets that Ohm is backed against, but a guaranteed amount of value that Ohm calls this the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.olympusdao.finance/main/references/glossary#rfv&quot;&gt;Risk-Free Value&lt;/a&gt; derived out of the market value of these assets. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.olympusdao.finance/main/references/equations#backing-per-ohm&quot;&gt;RFV formula&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does it mean to be backed? Is the value of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; supposed to equal the value or &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RFV&lt;/code&gt; of the assets? That’s not the case. In fact Olympus explicitly made it clear that &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://policonomics.com/lp-exchange-rate-regimes-free-float/#:~:text=A%20free%20floating%20exchange%20rate,government%20intervention%20is%20totally%20inexistent.&quot;&gt;free-floating currency&lt;/a&gt; with a market driven market rate. If &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;’s value is enforced to be 1-to-1 correspondent to the value of the backing assets, it’s value will be &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;. However, Olympus is giving a guarantee that every &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; out there will always be redeemable for &lt;strong&gt;AT LEAST&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;. This is the price floor of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;, or in other words its current intrinsic value to be &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;. Theoretically in general, it is possible for the price floor of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; to be above &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olympus makes this possible precisely because of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RFV&lt;/code&gt; in the treasury, that can be used to buy any circulating &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;, or theoretically in general any price floor e.g &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$100&lt;/code&gt;. Essentially, if &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;’s price ever goes down below &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;, a seller can go to Olympus and sell it for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt; which Olympus buys using the treasury assets it has accumulated. Additionally, by buying &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; Olympus can remove the purchased &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; out of circulation through a &lt;em&gt;burning&lt;/em&gt; process (algorithmic removal of a token supply). So in addition to the price increase pressure from Olympus being a so-called &lt;strong&gt;buyer of last resorts&lt;/strong&gt;, the price of the still circulating &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; will eventually get back to its intrinsic value&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ohm-an-inflationary-currency&quot;&gt;Ohm: An inflationary currency&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned previously how &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;’s market price is free-floating and possibly above &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;. The market price is the market price, it is a price that is determined by market outlook, sentiment and supply and demand. If &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; is seen as a useful and productive currency, it’s price has a chance to go up. In fact, it is natural for such a currency to increase in price over time all else being equal. The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;USD&lt;/code&gt; for example, is a valuable currency used to transact across many countries and regimes around the world for all kinds of assets and commodities and used as various countries cash reserves. At times when there are high demand for the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;USD&lt;/code&gt; you would expect its price, relative to some other currency to increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While price increase sounds nice for primarily an investment asset, price increase relative to goods, services and other assets are deflationary. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If with 10 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; you can buy 10 apples, but then the price of Ohm increases 10 times while the price of apples stays the same, then that same 10 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; can now buy 100 apples. The value of apples has deflated subjective to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with deflation is that it encourages indefinite hoarding. If you are acclimated to prolonged a deflationionary pricing environment you would likely eventually be led to believe that deflation is the state of nature. The result is that you would start to believe that the asset that you hold will be worth more tomorrow than it is today, and your neighbours and everyone else with their assets would think the same. The rational next step is for everyone to not consume or divest the value of that asset and just hoard! But clearly this is problematic for a currency, whose objective is in large part to be spent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to combat the deflationary aspect caused by a potential market price increase, Olympus has set out &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; to be an inflationary currency, which means that Olympus literally mints more &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; over time. In order to mint more &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;, Olympus provides a staking program (covered more later), that gradually mints more &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; at a variable rate. Essentially you can think of this as making a deposit into an account with a variable interest rate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may think that this is bad since the consequence of minting more of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; means that there is a price reduction pressure, and that is true! But this is a feature of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;, not a bug. The point of minting more of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; is to ensure an adequate supply of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; in the ecosystem. With an inflationary currency, or hence a deflationary currency in value, holders will be incentivized over time to spend &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; instead of hoarding it. As &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; is used more and more as a currency being used to transact and purchase goods and services, there will be more demand for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;. This demand will lead to some price increase support, but more importantly it requires &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; to be present to be used widely and as conveniently as possible. Inflationary supply helps make that possible&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now lastly, remember the previous section where I talked about the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RFV&lt;/code&gt;. While Olympus mints &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;, it is algorithmically made to mint only to the point that the amount of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; in circulation matches the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RFV&lt;/code&gt; in treasury. The reason is because 1 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; is backed by &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;. Not minting more &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; than the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RFV&lt;/code&gt; would help ensure that every &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt; can be sold back for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;staking-the-monetary-supply-tool&quot;&gt;Staking: The monetary supply tool&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;quick-comparisons-with-the-fed-and-modern-monetary-system&quot;&gt;Quick comparisons with the FED and modern monetary system&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The FED is also the issuer of currency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The banks create money, Olympus is both reserve and money creator&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Olympus says that it’s money is backed by real assets, USD is backed by nothing. This is not quite true since the USD can be seen as backed by &lt;strong&gt;future&lt;/strong&gt; spending, and the production of the economy. Likewise, Olympus reserves backed by the belief in cryptocurrency economy, and hence likewise for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Ohm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things to follow up on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What happens to the APY and staking when the price of Ohm increases?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What happens to the APY and staking when the price of Ohm decreases?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="finance" /><category term="economy" /><category term="cryptocurrency" /><category term="ethereum" /><summary type="html">Recently I have been dabbling a bit more into cryptocurrencies finding interesting projects and communities. Of course, there is the investment portion of it, but there is also the educational and pure interest part of it. Since I’ve been more into economics and finance lately and being a part of what media likes to call the digital generation, cryptocurrency has become more attractive as an interest. One of the most economically interesting cryptocurrency project that I have gotten to know is the [Olympus] project. What makes it interesting is that it is a project that is trying to become a monetary reserve system of Ethereum, that is, it is tyring to become a FED-like entity, with cryptocurrency and decentralization twist along with a different monetary policy outlook</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Oh! Interesting… Week 1</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/09/05/oh-interesting-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Oh! Interesting… Week 1" /><published>2021-09-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/09/05/oh-interesting-#1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/09/05/oh-interesting-1">&lt;h1 id=&quot;1996-cra-housing-study&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribd.com/document/521864486/CRA-ATIP-RESPONSE#download&quot;&gt;1996 CRA Housing Study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apparently in 1996 auditors of CRA (Canada Revenue Agency, the government body dealing with taxes and income) conducted a study on luxury residential properties being bought by new incoming immigrants in Burnaby, British Columbia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They found that a lot of luxury properties were bought by recent immigrants to Canada. In Burnaby for properties with that is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt; $800,000&lt;/code&gt; in purchasing value, 33 out of 48 buys in the sample were purchased by immigrants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interestingly, the average declared income among these immigrants were considerably much lower than other groups sampled in the study. Some even declared their income to be negative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This raised questions surrounding potential tax evasion through global income, business or perhaps some convoluted loan schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The study was never truly publicized and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scmp.com/news/china/diplomacy/article/3146957/canada-tax-agency-reveals-secret-study-linking-home-prices&quot;&gt;allegedly ignored&lt;/a&gt;. It surfaced only after 5 years of a process called “Access to Information and Privacy” (ATIP)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One of the reasons that Canadians consider to be a factor to the ever increasing prices of residential properties is foreign buyers with greater purchasing power buying properties. This report will likely make their concerns even larger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the same time the study was primarily focused on luxury properties, and at least based on the study itself there is no clear indication of how luxury property purchased with foreign money impact the overall property market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/canadahousing/comments/perryt/canada_revenue_agency_intentionally_buried_a_1996&quot;&gt;Original source that I read&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rent-control-inefficacy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://freakonomics.com/podcast/rent-control/&quot;&gt;Rent control inefficacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rent control is sometimes proposed as part of a solution to combat housing unaffordability. But it may not be as desirable as one would think&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imposing rent control can lead to decrease in overall housing supply throughout the years that rent control is enforced. The reasons assume assumptions on the rational behaviour of landlords and real estate developers. Essentially due to the capped potential profit, suppliers have less incentive to supply properties as rentals and when this situation is prolonged it can lead to severe undersupply&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the same time rent control does positive effects on reducing the displacement of residents. In other words, residents can keep staying at the same place&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However, rent control also disincentivizes people to move to other locations which may impede their economic mobility, but also further restricts the options of future incoming residents. Future residents are likely to have to find residence in a non-rent control place&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overall, rent control seems to benefit the immediate at the expense of future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And yet, removing rent control itself won’t be the best course of action given the likelihood of undersupply in areas with rent control. Removing rent control without other supporting actions would only serve to displace people and exacerbate the housing affordability problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To me the whole debacle of housing affordability, from the lens of rent control, is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tragedy_of_the_commons&quot;&gt;tragedy of the commons&lt;/a&gt;. All sides would like an outcome that suits their best interest but they often conflict with one another and decisions that tilt one favorably over another may be a short term net benefit but a long term problem. In this case the issuance of some versions of rent control may have ironically made things more unaffordable when moving forward into the future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rent control also seems to be a rough attempt in creating the positive effects of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Land_value_tax&quot;&gt;land value tax&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;curation-economy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gaby.mirror.xyz/LGrzJJbwV9ewhYAa7gcFYa2nxYlTWRH-SxmSuViEWA4&quot;&gt;Curation economy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The amount of content out there in the world to be consumed is ever expanding and inundates us with choice paralysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But we desire to consume content as part of our ever digitalized life and media loving generation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There seems to be an increasing amount of willingness to pay for high quality content. These companies or ventures that thrive on the collection of curated content are called curators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the author’s perspective, a curation must also be based on an underlying theme, that you can cultivate to a brand from&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some curators or forms of curation that come to my mind include: podcasts, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.morningbrew.com/daily&quot;&gt;Morning Brew&lt;/a&gt;, YouTube channels, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hiatus.net/&quot;&gt;Hiatus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This series in itself is a curation of things I found interesting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non media content curation may include ventures like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hellofresh.ca/&quot;&gt;HelloFresh&lt;/a&gt;, and you may try to stretch that dating apps are also a form of curation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wholly agree that curation is going to play a bigger role in our future of consumption as the number of content, and also poorly made ones, increase and get sieved through our perceptions, values, ideas and culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;negativity-bias&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://freakonomics.com/podcast/reasons-to-be-cheerful-rebroadcast/&quot;&gt;Negativity bias&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Negativity bias is the tendency to focus on the negatives, more so on the positives. The higher amount of focus and attention given to negative events and aspects leads us to be more attentive and attracted, perhaps worryingly so, to such events dulling the positive impacts of positive events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This trait of us to focus on negative events seems to be understood as a form of generally true statement in psychology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You probably also notice that much of the news media, traditional or more contemporary like in our social media feeds, has a tendency to gravitate towards negative events. They know how to cash in on our attention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A general rule of thumb is that it takes &lt;b&gt;4 good things&lt;/b&gt; to offset the psychological impact of &lt;b&gt;1 bad thing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Life has to win every day. Death only has to win once”&lt;/em&gt; - Roy Baumeister, psychologist. Our negativity bias may have come about from evolutionary needs to stay alive by avoiding the negative and even dangerous moments in life. Our ancestors had to live a life of struggle against the wilderness and spurious events that was literally life and death moments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If negativity bias was an evolutionary line of defense, it may not be as needed anymore in our modern days. Certainly the dangers of the wilderness is less faced by most of us. And we have systems and mechanisms in place, while imperfect, that are doing better at keeping us safe from what used to endanger our ancestors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The focus on what is negative may make us lose sight of what is truly important and what is possible. This may lead us to sub-optimal decisions, whether in the short or long run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;fairness-as-a-constraint-on-profit-seeking&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sci-hub.se/https://www.jstor.org/stable/1806070&quot;&gt;Fairness as a Constraint on Profit Seeking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Economics 101 would tell you that what dictates price is the law of supply and demand. But while it is certainly fundamental in pricing mechanisms, it is not the only factor that influences pricing. Daniel Kahnemann et al. finds that rules of fairness puts certain limitations on how prices can move&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The researches posited that when it comes to what is fair, consumers as market participants deem what is fair through an assessment that the researchers call the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dual-entitlement view&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dual-entitlement view is the view that:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It is not fair for suppliers of goods and services to charge a higher price if it means that transactors will incur at a loss. This applies &lt;strong&gt;EVEN IF&lt;/strong&gt; there legitimate cost increases. &lt;em&gt;Note that transactors in the study includes customers, tenants or employees&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It is fair for suppliers of goods and services to gain profit by taking advantage of cost reductions, even if such cost reductions are not necessarily caused or induced by the suppliers&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These are some hypotethical scenarios in the study that were deemed unfair, but would be possible through pure supply and demand mechanisms:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A hardware store has been selling snow shovels for $15. The morning after a large snowstorm, the store raises the price to $20&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A small photocopying shop has one employee who has worked in the shop for six months and earns $9 per hour. Business continues to be satisfactory, but a factory in  the area has closed and unemployment has increased. Other small shops have now hired reliable workers at $7 an hour to perform jobs similar to those done by the photocopy shop employee. The owner of the photocopying shop reduces the employee’s wage to $7&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The researchers claims that many people accounts loss and profit in what is called &lt;em&gt;naive accounting&lt;/em&gt;. Naive accounting takes into account the &lt;em&gt;reference pricing&lt;/em&gt; of the situation rather than the final end state of profit and loss. Rational pricing frameworks suggest what matters is the final end state, not the relative intermediate changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They also noticed that people are more adverse to perceptions of loss than gains.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perceptions of loss and gain along with naive accounting have significant impacts are significantly influenced by the framing of the situation. Even though the final accounting state may be the same, certain situations may be deemed unfair:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A small company employs several people. The workers’ incomes have 
been about average for the community. In recent months, business for the company has not increased as it had before. The owners reduce the workers’ wages by 10 percent for the next year.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;A small company employs several people. The workers have been receiving a 10 percent annual bonus  each year and their total incomes have  been about average for the community. In recent months, business for  the company has not increased as it had before. The owners eliminate the workers’ bonus for the year.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In both scenarios the firm ends up with 10% in extra profit kept. However, the first scenario was deemed predominantly as unfair while the second one being fair by research participants&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are some economic consequences to the perceptions of fairness by market participants. Many of the ramifications that the researchers posited involve the failure of markets in delivering goods, services and labor at prices that supply and demand curve would suggest is appropriate. Inability to raise prices, or lower wages, in certain situations may lead to inbalances in the demand and supply that causes excess in one way or another. Economically speaking this leads to negative externalities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some recent pricing events that come to my mind related to this study are:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shrinkflation, the practice of reducing amount of packaged goods but at the same price. Consumers are likely to be less perceptive in what seems to be neither gain nor loss, even though the end state, the price per unit may steadily increase&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Canada’s housing is widely accepted to be undersupplied, and during the pandemic has skyrocketed in demand along with increased prices. Yet, in some online forums there are clear grievances and even bouts of anger and exclamations of unfairness. Clearly, there are some goods and services that can be increased in price but at the same time have a perception of unfairness imposed on them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It is widely accepted that technological advancements have led to an increased boom in productivity and consequently corporate revenues/profits. And technological advancements are not restricted to high growth tech companies, though it is certainly a major recipient and producer of it. But wages have predominantly stayed flat (in Canada, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/t1/tbl1/en/tv.action?pid=1110023901&amp;amp;pickMembers%5B0%5D=1.1&amp;amp;pickMembers%5B1%5D=2.1&amp;amp;pickMembers%5B2%5D=3.1&amp;amp;pickMembers%5B3%5D=4.3&amp;amp;cubeTimeFrame.startYear=1976&amp;amp;cubeTimeFrame.endYear=2019&amp;amp;referencePeriods=19760101%2C20190101&quot;&gt;median and average employment income has barely moved&lt;/a&gt;). Is it because of perceived fairness? Or is it because of mostly unaware employees? I personally think the latter&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I found about this study initially from reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/08/22/prices.html&quot;&gt;Vitalik Buterin’s blog post on under pricing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">1996 CRA Housing Study</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I decided to fire myself</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/08/28/i-decided-to-fire-myself" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I decided to fire myself" /><published>2021-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/08/28/i-decided-to-fire-myself</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/08/28/i-decided-to-fire-myself">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay to start off, excuse my clickbaity title, but I feel that my title is appropriate (I’ll explain further down). So recently I changed my jobs after a long time of deliberation. Before deciding to change jobs, I actually had another opportunity to change jobs several months ago. At that time I finally decided to not change jobs at the time for several reasons. But the things I deliberated back then were either similar or related to the things I deliberated in my recent decision. In this blog post I would just like to share my experience and thoughts on this episode in my career&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-made-me-consider-changing-jobs&quot;&gt;What made me consider changing jobs?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision to fire myself is inextricable from the considerations to change my job. So let’s start from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I liked my previous job’s co-workers. I also liked the product concept that the company is making and trying to iterate on. I liked my team. But there was a lack of alignment between what I felt was valued, and what I think is valuable. This misalignment turned to be the main catalyst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made lots of code and I enjoyed that. And besides coding I also did the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Devops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best practices development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Processes improvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CI/CD enhancement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AWS Resources Management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Establishing and iterating on code architecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trying to connect technical initiatives with business goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lunch and learns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was doing what can be called as &lt;a href=&quot;https://noidea.dog/glue&quot;&gt;glue work&lt;/a&gt;, which in essence is all the things things that connect various aspects of the organization in order to make the software product and projects run well. I list these responsibilities not out of dislike, in fact I like to do most of them. But liking an activity is not the primary reason for taking responsibility on my shoulders. During a 1-on-1 session with my manager they asked me whether I liked to do more devops oriented work. My reply was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I certainly do not dislike doing it. But more than liking it or not, I do it mainly because I find it necessary for the company’s quality and longevity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Necessity breeds invention they say. But while there were some level of acknowledgement of the importance of the above, there was a lack of targeted effort, attention and resources allocated to them. And for those that were allocated some resources, I felt they were lacking. It felt that that things were &lt;strong&gt;just barely&lt;/strong&gt; holding on due to the efforts and attention given by a small number of people on glue work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that often resource allocation translates to capital allocation, which may or may not be feasible to distribute across so many necessities. But if that was the case, then I certainly expect management to step in and to work with the frontline engineers and business to align focus allowing for targeted resource allocation. I expect that gradually things would be given their due attention. If it was found that the business cannot shoulder the burden of working on so many priorities at the same time, then I expect management to make things feel and be manageable, even if that means de-prioritizing certain goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect all of these from an environment that aims to strive for lasting excellence and quality. And yet, I did not see the company move towards such an environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;firing-myself&quot;&gt;Firing myself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Firing” is often seen as having a negative connotation, but my own framing of “firing” is a bit different. I had the chance to talk to my ex-CTO where I asked what skills they think are required for the company. One of the abilities they said they’d like to see from employees is the ability to fire people. What they meant is that there are going to be, for fortunate and unfortunate reasons, people that no longer align with the business. Misalignment between people and the company may include values, skills, results etc. Whatever the misalignment may be, my ex-CTO thought it is important to be able to let go of such people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wondered why I was unsure of whether to change jobs or not. In the end I came to realize that I was no longer delivering outputs that aligns to what the business values. I felt that my focus on tackling the challenges and tasks I listed above, clashed with what the company needed at the time. The company needed and seeked for more immediate business results that translates to clients’ success. Of course, I strived to bring success for our clients. I see my role as an engineer not to just create technology for the sake of itself, but to create technology that aligns with a greater purpose. In order to deliver those values I identified that the iterative and continous improvements on glue work were needed. Meanwhile, with the numerous projects accompanied with statically defined delivery schedules, as time goes on it became clearer that how I deliver value does not align with how the company delivers value. I knew there was a misalignment because though I often bring the topic of the need for continued organizational effort on glue work, I did not see changes materialize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that I was an integral part of the team. And I also knew that I am not in alignment with the company any longer. So instead of waiting for things to feel worse for both me and the company, I took the step to fire myself rather than prolong the situation. By firing myself I let the myself depart from the idealistic vision of what I think work should be like within the company. At the same time I also gave the opportunity to the company to re-allocate the resources and energy they spent on me towards others (potentially a new hire) that would better suit their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I am happy with my decision. Some may, and I did myself, argue that I should have stayed and try harder. If I really emphasized quality and really think what I did were important, then I should have aimed harder at creating buy in. I should reach further and connect people across the company. Or maybe, I should just have been a better communicator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not disagree with such thoughts and I definitely see the merits of each. That’s why I hesitated to change jobs myself, questioning my own motives and decisions. But I realize that I may also be impeding not just my own growth, but perhaps the company’s growth too due to our misalignment. Additionally, by staying I may be delivering less impact than I can had I worked with an organization that aligns better with myself. Both sides have reasonable arguments depending on the situation and in the end I just chose what felt to be the best one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I do encourage everyone to seek to work for organizations (or even create ones) that aligns with themselves so that everyone can maximize their positive impact, I realize that the ability to fire oneself is a privilege. Not everyone will be able to nor afford to do it. I am certainly fortunate. Hence I hope employers continuously strive to onboard those that truly align with the organization but also be ready to adapt and shift to ensure that they themselves align with their workforce. It will require effort on all sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading thus far. I hope it has been valuable to you&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="professional life" /><category term="management" /><category term="career" /><category term="thoughts" /><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 1, Land Value Tax - Oh Canada, Why Is Your Land So Expensive?</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/08/11/oh-canada-why-is-your-land-so-expensive" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 1, Land Value Tax - Oh Canada, Why Is Your Land So Expensive?" /><published>2021-08-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/08/11/oh-canada-why-is-your-land-so-expensive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/08/11/oh-canada-why-is-your-land-so-expensive">&lt;h2 id=&quot;canadas-housing-price&quot;&gt;Canada’s Housing Price&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Canadian reader headlines of large price increases on real estate, particularly on housing real estate, is likely not foreign to you. In 2021. A quick search yields &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ctvnews.ca/business/canadian-home-sales-prices-surge-to-new-record-in-march-1.5388622&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; that says Canadian house prices rose by 31.6% from March 2020 (start of COVID-19 pandemic) to March 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On another &lt;a href=&quot;https://housepriceindex.ca/2021/07/june2021/&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;, most major cities in Canada have had their highest real estate during the COVID-19 pandemic. The surge on real estate prices is taken note by Bank of Canada as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://betterdwelling.com/boc-governor-says-canada-will-lean-on-real-estate-because-we-need-the-growth/&quot;&gt;significant economic driving force&lt;/a&gt; with residiential real estate investment accounting for over 9% of gross domestic product. Increase in residential real estate prices, along with accomodative monetary policies such as low interest rates have prompted investments into residential real estate to &lt;a href=&quot;https://betterdwelling.com/canadians-now-pump-more-into-residential-real-estate-than-business-development/&quot;&gt;slightly eclipse&lt;/a&gt; that of non-residential’s. &lt;a href=&quot;https://financialpost.com/investing/david-rosenberg-housing-is-keeping-canadas-economy-going-and-thats-bad-news-when-the-bubble-pops&quot;&gt;Some are opining that Canada’s economiy is over-reliant&lt;/a&gt; on the residential real estate market, with investments on productive assets being thwarted by the chase on real estate investments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, money goes where returns shine the brightest and certainly the Canadian housing market is shining bright hot in price. Considering residential, or housing’s, status of both as a consumption and asset it brings both pain and joy throughout the economy. For those that have entered into the real estate ownership, there is surely some joy having an asset that appreciates (though I personally contest this notion of housing as an asset). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newswire.ca/news-releases/housing-in-crisis-3-in-4-canadians-who-want-a-house-can-t-afford-one-829319771.html&quot;&gt;But for many&lt;/a&gt;, it can be painful thinking of ever growing house prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;price-reasoning&quot;&gt;Price Reasoning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has always perplexed me that house prices continue to rise especially if it does so in extraordinary numbers. Check out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JamesEagle17/status/1377353707478601729&quot;&gt;Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt; for an infographic of how much Canada’s house prices have risen. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/pub/46-28-0001/2019001/article/00002-eng.htm&quot;&gt;ever increasing housing price has continued to outpace income in growth&lt;/a&gt; making house affordability an increasing pain point throughout the country. You see it in headlines and probably have conversations with it online and offline. As someone that do not have their own house and who may (or may not) choose to buy one in the future in Canada, it is definitely a situation that is worrisome. Even if you are not planning to buy some housing property it is still an economical and social concern. For those in governing seats, it is likely a political concern too. What can we do about this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To hope to answer the question we would need to assess reasons for why house prices have continued to grow. Some of the common reasons that I have seen and heard are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low interest rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discrepancy on supply and demand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speculation money driving up prices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An accommodative government that will not tolerate house prices to drop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing foreign investments or buyers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hiding laundered money through buying properties&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pro-buying programs such as first time home owner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there is the classic - all of the above and more, which I agree is probably the case with each point having some degree of relevance. But on this series I would like to focus on the third reason, speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;land-and-speculation&quot;&gt;Land and Speculation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it that is being speculated on with housing and how does that speculation get reflected in price? I think we can all agree that in general, over time a house’s condition will deteriorate if maintenance is not properly given. Much like a car that is used over time, it will lose its price as its value is eked over time. A house’s design has a certain of sense and fashion to it which may gain in popularity much like fashion and may come and go in popularity. But such ebb and flow in consumer taste is hardly a reason for an endemic increase in price. So neither the interior nor exterior quality of a house by in itself may drive us to speculate on its price. Then it must be something else, and based on the title of this article, it is the land of the house that can be speculated to increase in value and hence price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, the available land to us is static and no one can truly produce more of it. Okay, maybe there are instances where land is “created” (or reclaimed) land like in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtco.com/polders-and-dikes-of-the-netherlands-1435535&quot;&gt;Netherlands&lt;/a&gt; or in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Land_reclamation_in_Singapore&quot;&gt;Singapore&lt;/a&gt;, but these instances are few in contrast to the vast land that we have. Or perhaps you say that land is being lost due to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/environment/article/sinking-land-rising-seas-dual-crises-facing-coastal-communities&quot;&gt;land sinking based on effects of climate change&lt;/a&gt;. Okay find, but land sinking isn’t what we humans consciously work for in the economy like how you or I work at our jobs. Land, for the most part, is simply not something we produce, it’s supply is fixed (pre-dominantly) by what mother nature gives to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then if land is fixed, supply and demand from economics 101 will tell us that price can only increase as a matter of demand. So when we speculate on the value of land we speculate that the price of land will increase as a function of higher demand. Why will a particular piece of land gain or lose demand? Because the land is surrounded by or removed of other valuable things (including other valuable land). The things of value built surrounding a particular land is a function of economic investments and market or community participation. Acknowledgement of the participation of a greater community is key to understand that the value of land is not beholden to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;land-value-is-not-owned-by-anyone&quot;&gt;Land Value is Not Owned by Anyone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let us recap:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Land’s supply is fixed and no person can increase or decrease its price through direct production&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Land gains value by what it is surrounded by and the community and market that participates on it and it’s surrounding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these two observation we can claim that &lt;em&gt;land’s value is not owned by anyone&lt;/em&gt;. Of course in a system of capitalism there is a notion of private ownership. Land itself can be privately owned for purposes such as building a business on top of it, or to live on it. But it’s value cannot be privately owned, because it’s value is not a function of one’s own work but that of mother nature’s and society as a whole. This is what Henry George argues for in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/your-book-review-progress-and-poverty&quot;&gt;Progress and Poverty&lt;/a&gt;. But our friend George here goes further than just defining land value, George wants to tax the land value we are standing and living on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;land-value-tax-and-speculation&quot;&gt;Land Value Tax and Speculation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George’s land value tax (LVT) is a simple proposal: put a tax on the value of the land. George goes further to say that LVT is the only tax that is needed to fund everything. He also contends that it is the most just tax to impose because no one owns the value of land (he allows land ownership, just not ownership over it’s value).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make it even more starking George wants to tax 100% of the value of land. Partly again becasue of the no ownership over land value. Another reason is because George thinks that this would help dampen speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would it be so? Well consider someone who is a house flipper that aims to buy some house property and sell it in a year or so. This person thinks that the price of the house will increase in the future without them needing to do &lt;em&gt;improvements&lt;/em&gt; on top of it. To make it concrete say they bought for 500k CAD, and in a year they manage to sell for 600k CAD making a 100k revenue. Minus transaction costs and fees they may take home 50k in profit. But remember that they did not make any improvement to the property, thus the government can say that the price increase was wholly due to some land value increase. So through a 100% LVT they will be taxed on the full 50k profit or 100k revenue, depending on how the tax policy is enacted. No economic agent looking to make a profit will bother with flipping a house anymore because there is no profitable incentive to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if the flipper did decide to make some improvements to the house and sell higher based on the improvements? Then based on George’s LVT, they are entitled to the profits of their improvements. And since George advocates as LVT as the only tax, the profit from improvements will not be taxed. So if they made a 20k CAD improvement on the property, and sold it for 50k CAD, they are entitled on the full 30k profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-lvt-feasible&quot;&gt;Is LVT Feasible?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are already some forms of LVT around the world, though not to the same degree that George laid it out. But there does seem to be government funding that is similar to essence with LVT. One such recent funding is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/innovation-science-economic-development/news/2021/07/3500-mhz-auction--process-and-results.html&quot;&gt;Canada’s 5G broadband auction&lt;/a&gt;. While not deemed as tax, you can easily think of it as a one time tax for Canadian telecom providers that wish to supply 5G connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like how in LVT the government mandates that no one has ownership over land, the spectrum’s value is also not owned by anyone since they are simply leased through a license by the government. The spectrum’s value is for all, stewarded by the government in this case. The perception of the auction bids as a form of tax on future profits is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloombergquint.com/onweb/quebec-cable-firm-surprises-with-5g-spending-spree-in-canada&quot;&gt;reflected in the stock market of the highest bidders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The encounter with LVT while thinking about what can be done about Canadian housing price has been a delight. I do think that LVT can be applied to try and curb the speculative sensation of the Canadian housing market. Dampening down speculation should help bring down, or at least keep house prices down at a reasonable price or growth rate. Meanwhile the proceeds from LVT can be used to fund public goods, and even perhaps a universal basic income as a way to disperse the riches of Canadian lands to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In part 2 I will be briefly look at the economic and policy implications of LVT.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="housing" /><category term="real estate" /><category term="taxation" /><category term="policy" /><category term="economics" /><summary type="html">Canada’s Housing Price</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Agile is Experimentation</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/07/12/agile-as-experimentation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agile is Experimentation" /><published>2021-07-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/07/12/agile-as-experimentation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/07/12/agile-as-experimentation">&lt;p&gt;Recently I had a conversation with two gents about software development and the word “Agile” propped up. As software engineers, or even business management these days, the word agile is everywhere. In job postings, in company slogans, in company talks, on our computer screens, and in our purported work values. But I know from personal feelings, observations and anecdotes there is some distaste to “Agile” and that it feels more as hype and even worse at times feels like a marketing tool to attract talent which sadly does not deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as per my usual inquiring-and-chatty-self I asked the two gents, “So, what does agile mean to you?”. And I purposefully directed the question to them through the vocabulary “you” because I want to understand their own personal mental model of Agile. I do not care about Scrum, Kanban or whatever new Agile framework out there is, I wanted to get to the fundamental of Agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first said that for him Agile is all about doing breaking up the work and taking them up. He stated that the importance is not in the pointing mechanism itself, but more in actually being able to take up and do the work. The other said that Agile for him is all about the small iterative steps that is aimed for continuous refinement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these kind of mental models of Agile is quite common. Generally they are surmised by these adjectives or nouns: ‘iterative’, ‘small’, ‘continuous improvement’. But I would like to further refine this understanding of iteration. So let’s do that in this post, let’s try to develop a better mental model of Agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my take:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The main abstraction provided by Agile is experimentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;experimentation-first-the-rest-is-by-product&quot;&gt;Experimentation first, the rest is by-product&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As software engineers we love to abstract things away, to turn details into common patterns that can be encoded as a set of computer interactions (algorithms basically) to solve a problem, or class of problems. As a software engineer I posit that the main abstraction that Agile brings is experimentation in order to solve the problem of business development and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I say experimentation, I really mean experimentation as in the scientific method sense:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/82/The_Scientific_Method.svg/1024px-The_Scientific_Method.svg.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A picture of the scientific method, which is an on-going process. Source - &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_method&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I posit that Agile is really all about experimentation brought to business practice, then there are four elements that businesses adopting Agile must absolutely meet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A hypothesis to test&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mechanisms to perform tests for or against the hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The gathering of, and capability to assess data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A commitment and understanding to learn and adapt continuously based on feedback of previous experiments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When viewing and applying Agile as experimentation through the scientific method towards business, iteration and continuous improvement is a given. It simply becomes a by-product. Small requires an additional perspective which I will touch later on, but I assure you that it remains a by-product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;on-hypotheses-and-testing&quot;&gt;On hypotheses and testing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I would like to touch on hypothesization and testing because as a software engineer this is where a lot of software engineer’s time is spent struggling on. It shouldn’t and definitely isn’t the only phase in the Agile cycle where software engineers are involved in, but I find a lot of software engineers along with their business counterparties stumble in these areas often. The stumbles that occur here impede the whole Agile flow, and impacts its adoption within a team and potentially organization at large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poorly-made-hypotheses&quot;&gt;Poorly made hypotheses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of the hypothesis is often estranged from the software engineers’ work and by that I mean something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Business asks for a feature &amp;gt; Business comes up with requirements &amp;gt; Business forks over requirements to engineers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two problems with this kind of “hypothesization”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It isn’t really framed as a hypothesis. A hypothesis is about creating an assumption that is meant to be further investigated. Hence a hypothesis must always be made with the presupposition and even expectation that it may be false or incorrect. So a rewording may say that “Business thinks that a feature would be useful to be developed” instead. &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/eozFlgu6ByY&quot;&gt;Dave Farley in his video&lt;/a&gt; covers this idea of expecting false assumptions further and better than I do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The software engineers are often the people who procure the experimentation “ingredients” (code and machineries) and make the testing of the hypothesis possible. When the those that are creating the test experiments are not involved in the development of the hypothesis, there is significant risk that what would be setup does not reflect what the hypothesis is claiming. In other words - what software engineers develop may stray away tremendously from what the business actually needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;failure-to-perform-tests-for-the-hypothesis&quot;&gt;Failure to perform tests for the hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming that the software engineers have managed to scrounged up some code for the hypothesis, Agile as experimentation would say the next step is to test that the hypothesis is correct. You can also say you can (and probably should) test that the implementation of the hypothesis is correct. But too many organizations forego this step, likely because they do not think of Agile as experimentation. The result of this in my experience usually leads to (in order of severity and face-palm worthiness, with some embellishment):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never testing it because the software never got released in fear of what can go wrong (and also not knowing what can go right)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Letting the majority of the users be the one and only tester of the hypothesis - it’s not a bug, it’s a feature (or it’s not a feature, it’s a bug)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business performs tests on their side only at the very end when every hypothesis are realized as code. Then they spectacularly notice that nothing works as hypothesized&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software engineers never testing out their code and solution before running experiments. Usually exacerbating the length of feedback loops and by the time they are aware of issues highlighted in experiment results they already forgot what they did&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Silo’d QA teams that have no idea what is happening and have poor awareness of the hypothesis that needs to be tested&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of testing, and the inability to perform testing whether because of technological unreadiness or organizational politics impedes the collection of data. Without this data, Agile breaks down because the next experiment cycle will be disconnected from the previous. And even if the next experiment cycle does not have anything to do with the previous one, without testing the experiment cycle is incomplete. Yet many teams and businesses readily jump in to the next experiment without really finishing the previous one at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be noted that the procurement of data and testing of the hypothesis in Agile may come from various tests and groups of testers. This idea of diverse testers should be intuitive in both its concept and also importance. In fact, the differing kinds of testers at times also help keep the experiment iteration small. For example, software engineers as testers is likely (or hopefully) testing a small piece of the hypothesis in a fairly quick manner, keeping the experiment and feedback fast and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;failures-in-adopting-agile&quot;&gt;Failures in adopting Agile&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve postulated Agile as primarily an experimentation it becomes we can look at the potential concrete reasons why Agile adoption fails. And here is where the pscyhology aspect of working with or within Agile becomes more prominent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mischaracterization-of-agile&quot;&gt;Mischaracterization of Agile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that is quite likely to have happened is that the organization has mischaracterized Agile as a set of procedures and formal methodologies. This is exactly not what Agile was meant to be based on the Agile manifesto. The focus is likely to have been aimed at adopting Scrum or Kanban methodologies while missing the essence of Agile; an abstraction for scientific experimentation for the business problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-off-from-being-wrong&quot;&gt;Closing off from being wrong&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you watched Dave Farley’s video that I linked above you should understand where I am coming from with this. Experimentation necessitates that there is an uncertainty that wants to be further investigated. By nature this must mean that incorrect hypothesis and even seemingly unfruitful effort will be made as business attempt to solve problems through products, services and processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of being wrong is psychologically difficult to reconciliate with. There is also a social dimension to it which hits some people harder than others, for legitimate and illegitimate reason. But even disregarding that, our brain and ego often limits our ability to accept mistakes, by others or ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inability-to-change&quot;&gt;Inability to change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific method is a continuous loop. Each loop may feed in new data points and observations for the next loop. Iteration is enabled by the successive feed of data from one step to another. But some experiments will inevitably challenge our assumptions and hence our cycle. More likely though, challenges will come from external sources Agile processes. It is unlikely that your Agile journey will be a sequence of smooth loops; they say the only constant is change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disregarding turbulent external change, Agile itself promotes change, and so it must be something that teams and organizations can work and be comfortable with. But inherently change is difficult to do. There is technical aspect of change which is difficult in itself which covers aspects of software design, architecture, CI/CD and many more. Then there is the fragility of our human cognition in accepting change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need for change may be brought by previously held incorrect hypothesis or experimentations. And we’ve said that accepting being wrong in itself is already hard. Even if it isn’t necessitated by previous missteps we may be prone to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Status_quo_bias&quot;&gt;status quo bias&lt;/a&gt;. Or perhaps we have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.behavioraleconomics.com/resources/mini-encyclopedia-of-be/sunk-cost-fallacy/&quot;&gt;sunk cost fallacy&lt;/a&gt; towards our previous assumptions. Erroneously, some organizations may situate themselves to be unable to respond to the need for change because of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End-of-history_illusion&quot;&gt;end-of-history illusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;uncontrolled-change&quot;&gt;Uncontrolled change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some organizations do change, to the point of being overwhelmed by change. Change is difficult, and more so when change happens frequently and in an unstructured fashion. The COVID-19 pandemic has thought us that we need to change our long-held practices. But the deluge, abrupt and perhaps unprecedented scale of change that needs to be adapted for the modern era made many of us grind to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of our difficulty when change is uncontrolled:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small businesses anguish at ever changing regulations and response turbulence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Health officials saying they are doing science by looking and listening to the evidence that is constantly changing based on new data points. To many it seems these officials are flip-flopping and changing their stance or suggestions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scrum, Kanban and other Agile methodologies particularly shine here by bringing in a framework that acts as a guidance. In particular the emphasis on the dissection of experiments into smaller pieces helps to make change feel and be manageable. But these methodologies work best when the change being brought are iterative towards some form of north star, a loose trajectory guidance. When the north star itself is what keeps changing, many will find it difficult to handle what often becomes uncontrolled change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;industrial-friction&quot;&gt;Industrial friction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming that individuals within the organization themselves can apply Agile as a way of experimentation, there are still industrial challenges to the adoption of Agile. Such challenges may come internally or externally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internally, the problems mentioned above can equally be replicated and exacerbated on the organizational level. So there are the pscyhological dimensions on the individual and corporate that needs to be addressed in the adoption of Agile. Many organizations are still not comfortable yet in performing experiments; in hypothesizing, testing, analyzing data and rinse and repeat. They view business problems as work that needs to be steamrolled in one go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Externally, some organizations are situated within an industry that makes experimentation difficult. These industries often have low tolerance for mistakes. Arguably all industries are intolerant for mistakes, but some just feel more daunting than others, whether that is true or not is another topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite internal or external friction, it is possible to adopt Agile methodologies in gradients. While indeed Agile can be adopted within the context of “move fast and break things”, it can also be adapted in more nuanced and smaller scale. I take inspiration from SpaceX that continuously runs launch experiments against their hypothetical products. The level of funding needed to run these experiments, which may end with million-dollars fireworks, is ludicrously high. Yet, SpaceX shows that it is possible that Agile is possible even in high-stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead of fully backing off from Agile, we can try to see at which parts of our organizations do Agile make sense and in what form. At the very least I think all software engineering teams can and should adopt Agile by adopting CI/CD pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Dave Farley has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/v8f6q4ruvds&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; more on SpaceX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-comments&quot;&gt;Final comments&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear Agile, I always think of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://agilemanifesto.org/&quot;&gt;Agile Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;. We know that at the heart of it Agile is not Scrum, and it is not Kanban. I posit it as the abstraction of the scientific experimentation to solve business problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing Agile as experimentation puts a lot of emphasis on &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Working software&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Responding to change&lt;/code&gt; of the Manifesto. In particular, the Agile experiments are there to serve as a way to create software that works (for customers, not just for computers) according to battle-tested hypotheses. The experimental loop fundamentally necessitates organizations to expect change from the Agile cycles, and also from external forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this helps you in truly bringing Agile changes to your organization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="software development" /><category term="management" /><category term="organizational techniques" /><summary type="html">Recently I had a conversation with two gents about software development and the word “Agile” propped up. As software engineers, or even business management these days, the word agile is everywhere. In job postings, in company slogans, in company talks, on our computer screens, and in our purported work values. But I know from personal feelings, observations and anecdotes there is some distaste to “Agile” and that it feels more as hype and even worse at times feels like a marketing tool to attract talent which sadly does not deliver.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EUPHORIA - An acronym for financial well-being</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/05/02/euphoria-acronym" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EUPHORIA - An acronym for financial well-being" /><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/05/02/euphoria-acronym</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/05/02/euphoria-acronym">&lt;p&gt;It has been a while since my latest blog post and this time I’m writing out of whimsical inspiration. I was browsing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/PersonalFinanceCanada/&quot;&gt;PersonalFinanceCanada sub-Reddit&lt;/a&gt; and saw a question about being mindful of lifestyle creep. If you don’t know what lifestyle creep is, it basically means ever increasingly extravagant lifestyle, usually marked with fancier material posessions, dinners or experiences. It usually coincides with increases in salary, relocation or a momentous life event (such as a financial windfall).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually (though not everyone necessarily sees this way), lifestyle creep has a negative connotation, particularly because it usually hampers someone’s ability to save for their future. Suffice to say that the poster of the thread was of that mindset. So I came up with the acronym &lt;strong&gt;EUPHORIA&lt;/strong&gt;, hoping that it can be of help to the poster. And I hope an expansion of the acronym in this blog post will also help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;e---envision-where-you-want-to-be&quot;&gt;E - Envision where you want to be&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.halhershfield.com/&quot;&gt;Hal Hershfield&lt;/a&gt;, a UCLA researcher in the domain of behavioural decision making has conducted studies into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.halhershfield.com/research-index&quot;&gt;effectiveness of envisioning yourself into the future&lt;/a&gt;. He contends that interestingly, often we treat ourselves in the future as completely different people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While at first it may be surprising, intuitively you can kind of see why that may be the case. It is unsurprising to us now that though the world is ever more connected through the Internet, the lack of physical proximity may still cause a toll in our connection and relationship with others. Similarly ourselves in the future are temporally distant to ourselves. But at the very least space is arguably a visible and felt concept while time is more nebulous and seemingly unfelt, and you certainly never feel like slamming against time as you do against a wall. Compound this with the idea of trying to project yourself into the future several years ahead and you would likely have a hard time accurately depicting what you will be like into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know about you, but I certainly have moments of surprises when I think back what I was like 5 years ago compared to how I am now. I find it surprising not because of how extraordinarily different I am now than what I hope to be, but simply because I didn’t even imagine a world where I am like I am now. In his research Hal and his colleagues identified that given effective cues to both visually and imaginatively one’s future self, those that were studied were able to make better savings decisions. They contend that the exercise helped create a connection between the present and future selves which helped participants to &lt;strong&gt;discount future rewards less&lt;/strong&gt;. In other words they were better able to appreciate the value of delayed gratification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;u---understand-yourself&quot;&gt;U - Understand yourself&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If self envisioning can help you to more seriously aim for desired future targets to achieve, then the next question would be to ask what kind of targets you would like to pursue. While you can try to envision what, how and where you want to be in the future, it is still notoriously difficult to understand the &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; of the goals you are making. In a &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/post/2021/01/05/what-matters-given-you&quot;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; I talked a bit on the topic of exploring what matters for yourself. In the post I advocate for the notion of focusing on your situation to find out what is important for you. The blog post was inspired by the larger notion of self-understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The hardest but most important financial skill is getting the goalpost to stop moving - Morgan Housel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it so hard? Morgan argues that in order to keep the goalpost from moving requires a sense of having enough. But our sense of needs and wants live in a continuum scale, and probability will tell you that identifying the chances of a single point in the scale to materialize is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probability_distribution#Continuous_probability_distribution&quot;&gt;a flat zero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a perfect understanding of what is enough for us need not be the case. We simply need to be able to narrow it down enough to a small band of area in the needs and wants spectrum such that we can confidently say that anywhere within this small band we are content and can continue to be so. To be able narrow the ban BUT also stay confident in our judgement of what brings us contentment, joy, happiness, fulfillment etc. the ability to understand ourself is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example: for myself I am keeping a “decision log” that tracks my investment decisions. It helps me record and assess my actions such that I don’t just understand myself by how I feel, but also by what I actually did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;p---prioritize-what-is-important-not-what-is-nice&quot;&gt;P - Prioritize what is important, not what is nice&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you are able to both envision yourself, and continuously improve your understanding of yourself, you will now come to the impasse of how to proceed with life such that you can reach that envisioned content self. Between now and the future we all notice that there is no magical time leap machine we can take such that we can jump through the hoops of process and life. So we must take things step by step, which requires us to &lt;em&gt;create prioritizations in life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally the act of prioritization is akin to the act of making decisions. For this I will direct you to this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZU2VOXH2PI4&amp;amp;t=2s&quot;&gt;Rational Reminder podcast episode #120 with Annie Duke&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I want to say though is that it is okay if you find your prioritizations to shift and change over time. Independently, envisioning and understanding yourself is already difficult, even more so when you start thinking of things and steps you would like to prioritize in order to achieve your goals and targets. The point is to be able to commit to the things that you have identified to be important, and if you realize eventually that they are not as important as you think they were, your vision for the future and the understanding you have for yourself will act as your lighthouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of us have heard of tales of regret from those whose lives have run out short. The least we want to be is be that someone that poured our resources for that extra dash of glittering junk in life, while missing the real beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;h---hold-off-from-making-hasty-decision&quot;&gt;H - Hold off from making hasty decision&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have heard of the tale of the GameStop mania in early 2021. Basically the story goes that GameStop’s stock experienced a massive increase in price, over a whopping 2000% growth from January 1st, 2021 of the year to its highest point on January 27th, 2021. Many people took a substantial amount of profit from this and those are the headlines you would like to see (or maybe not if you are feeling sour about it), but how many people &lt;em&gt;LOST&lt;/em&gt; money?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know the global number, but here I’ll take a sample (and for sure a biased one to make a point). Based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wealthsimple.com/en-ca/magazine/gme-data&quot;&gt;Wealthsimple’s report&lt;/a&gt; 67% of people that invested in the GameStop stock (GME) lost money. The holding period is an average of 4.5 days, not very long. So what does this say? Well, in general the average investor likely saw the craze, for whatever reason decided to jump in to the craze, and then seemingly as fast as they went in they got out of it. It’s good that many didn’t lose more than 1000, but financially it would’ve been better that they didn’t lose any. Ah but perhaps they were allured at the &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; prospect&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile one of the earliest believers in the GME stock, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith_Gill&quot;&gt;Keith Gill&lt;/a&gt;, made millions out of this episode (and have not fully cashed out at the time of this writing), but he was holding the stock for a much longer period than 4.5 days. He held the stock since September 2019, whilst during that time the GME stock kept going lower AND he was making YouTube content talking about his position, making his thoughts and opinions public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against all odds AND viewing eyes, Keith held on and continued to have conviction. Yes his conviction may have turned out to be a bad result, but you cannot deny his conviction. At least in contrast to some of his peers with a holding period of 4.5 days, his decision definitely seems less hasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it is not necessarily the time horizon that I want to focus on, but the reasoning and believe you have over your decisions that I want to highlight. Remember, your future self and your self-understanding continues to be your lighthouse. Here’s another way to get my message across:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgflip.com/580uty.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Courtesy of imgflip&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;o---organize-your-finances-and-be-on-top-of-it&quot;&gt;O - Organize your finances and be on top of it&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What you do not measure, you do not know&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably a pretty common saying you may have heard somewhere in your professional career or even the Internet. Leaving a side the origins of the statement and how accurate it is, it is undeniable that observability, data and understanding over that data is becoming more important in the digital age. Data is the new gold they say. So why not bring to your personal finance life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am an &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life&quot;&gt;advocator for budgeting&lt;/a&gt;. I am not a budgeting expert, but I try to budget and set myself expenditure targets. It helps me understand where my money is going, where I want it to go, and any discrepancy between reality and desire that may happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a more universal topic, mayhaps you have heard tales of people who get swamped in their purchasing debt and are having trouble keeping a rein on it or improving the situation. And if you are Canadian you probably have heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L0JI-rWPG3Y&quot;&gt;hearsay speak about how high personal debt is in Canada&lt;/a&gt;(and continue to grow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are possibly some structural issues that people may be facing, it can also be useful to bring in specialized financial organization tools. Coupled with a vision for your future self, an understanding of oneself, commitment to prioritization and identification of what is important and holding off from making hasty decisions, these organization tools can be immensely powerful in paving the way for financial wellness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some tools that you can try to look into:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wealthica.com/&quot;&gt;Wealthica&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mint.intuit.com/&quot;&gt;Mint.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zero-basedbudget.com/&quot;&gt;Zero based budgeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youneedabudget.com/&quot;&gt;YNAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good old Excel spreadsheets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;r---run-from-comparison&quot;&gt;R - Run from comparison&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another commonly heard phrase:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Comparison is the thief of joy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was small, from time to time I get compared by my parents to some other kid they knew. Luckily it wasn’t often for me, but when it did happen it always felt unnerving and discomforting. Even for the pettiest of things (at least in my head), such as who dresses nicer (definitely not me), it would still be a bit of a sting. A sting to my pride, confidence and yes, joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not dislike all kinds of comparisons. In fact, it is useful to be able to compare one thing over another, a lot of our decisions are a matter of extracting conclusions from comparisons. But there are certainly good AND bad comparisons. Remember how apples aren’t necessarily comparable to oranges? The same case applies often when we are compared against one another. A person’s situation may seem similar but contain vastly differing details. A comparison that does not really apply equal criteria and assumptions likewise is not a good comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when it comes to finances, it is also equally important to NOT make comparisons against others yourself. Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/global/2017/may/11/outclassed-neighbors-income-happiness&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; that mentions that social and wealth comparisons are detrimental for your psyche, and there are other research delving into the topic. It is the case irrespective of who is initiating the comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think in recent years we have started to learn the lesson from our exposure to social media, and we can apply the same wisdom there with our financial lives. Some people may be able to tolerate it, some may even revel in it. But it is probably best for most if not all of us, to run from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;i---involve-your-partner-in-the-discussion&quot;&gt;I - Involve your partner in the discussion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that marriage is costly? Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weddingwire.ca/wedding-ideas/how-much-does-the-average-wedding-cost-in-canada--c1677&quot;&gt;an article from WeddingWire&lt;/a&gt; that says the average Canadian wedding costs 29,450 CAD (maybe it has gone down during the pandemic though). But I contend that divorce is costlier. You get the mental and physical stress, arguments, fear, trauma, child care disputes, legal costs and also on top of it the financial costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not going to be a fair example for daily people like you and me but consider Jeff and Mackenzie Bezos’ divorce. Depending on how you see it, Mackenzie (Jeff) got (lost) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weddingwire.ca/wedding-ideas/how-much-does-the-average-wedding-cost-in-canada--c1677&quot;&gt;38 billion USD in Amazon stock&lt;/a&gt;. Financially a big win for Mackenzie, but at the very least a dent into Jeff’s financial situation. As I’ve noted this is not a fair nor representative example of the average person, but it strikes an example of how costly financially a divorce can be. As your marriage (or even just dating) there are some assets that have been grown together between the you and your partner, a big one would be housing usually, which would somehow need to be divided amongst the both of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insauga.com/many-canadian-couples-open-about-their-finances-survey&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; that may be closer to home for young Canadian couples. It seems that financial communication has improved for these couples, yet still there are a significant percentage feeling like they are struggling to meet their financial goals. Communication is on aspect, but when I say “involve your partner” I mean so much more. It is about bringing your partner along with your journey of self-envisioning, self-understanding, self prioritization etc. Transforming the self into a process and activity of togetherness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me try to inspire you with my own experience. Compared to me my partner isn’t at all interested in investments. I don’t try to force her into it but I explain to her about the things I do, and likewise she explains to me her thought process. While not much, but I managed to help her started with investing bit by bit, with what we think is suitable for her at this time. Everytime I think something good can be done for her investments I consult her, and I let her have the final say. Sometimes I want to do things faster, but she doesn’t. Sometimes I share investment material and discuss financial topics or scenarios with her, as much as she is willing to take. In doing all this I’ve made it clear to her that I want her to be financially ready and successful, regardless if I am there in her life or not. While we may be different in many ways, this is a common goal and journey that we are both working towards for each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a---automate-where-possible&quot;&gt;A - Automate where possible&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a software engineer, automation naturally plays a big role in my life. I love to be able to automate the rote work I need to do day to day. Not only is it faster, if done well it can help bring a much needed simplicity to my activities. And the same case applies to finances, if not even more so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money has been a very emotionally related and charged topic in our culture. It has led to one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/financial-consumer-agency/services/financial-wellness-work/stress-impacts.html&quot;&gt;greatest stressors in people’s lives&lt;/a&gt;. Let alone making investments, people sometimes don’t know what to do to keep things afloat! Automation can’t help to start to fill all the holes caused by financial stress, but I believe it can greatly help people achieve consistency in implementing their goals and targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scotiabank.com/ca/en/personal/programs-services/bank-the-rest-personal-savings-program.html&quot;&gt;Scotiabank’s Bank The Rest Program&lt;/a&gt;, automatic paycheck deposit to savings account, pre-authorized contributions for investments, robo-advisors, spending tracking apps and tax software management, are just some examples of ways you can automate your financial life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will automation bring you the most optimal financial result? Theoretically, not always, especially since some of these automation technologies have a cost. However it definitely does help alleviate the taxing mental energy you would have otherwise required to invest in. And as human beings we are neither fully rational or have infinite capacity and resources to always consistently reach the optimal result. Worse, we are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investmentnews.com/fundamentals-of-behavioral-finance-overconfidence-bias-197276&quot;&gt;prone to be overconfident in our own ability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why not let technology help you achieve speed, greater peace of mind and consistency? Those non-financial gains may very well outweigh whatever financial optimization you were trying to do, especially when you take into account what you should prioritize&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;Final words&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acronym &lt;strong&gt;EUPHORIA&lt;/strong&gt; was created in the mindset and context of financial well-being. But I think it has room to be amended for other contexts. Additionally it doesn’t go through the gritty details and leaves out other important considerations. Some points may need to be adapted for your specific case (most easily visible in “&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;” if you don’t have a partner). But in general I believe it is a good and applicable recipe for financial (or other) well-being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been reading this far in, thank you for your time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="finance" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">It has been a while since my latest blog post and this time I’m writing out of whimsical inspiration. I was browsing the PersonalFinanceCanada sub-Reddit and saw a question about being mindful of lifestyle creep. If you don’t know what lifestyle creep is, it basically means ever increasingly extravagant lifestyle, usually marked with fancier material posessions, dinners or experiences. It usually coincides with increases in salary, relocation or a momentous life event (such as a financial windfall).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Matters, Given You</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/01/05/what-matters-given-you" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Matters, Given You" /><published>2021-01-05T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/01/05/what-matters-given-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/01/05/what-matters-given-you">&lt;p&gt;Happy new year 2021! I hope you, the reader, had the opportunity to take the time to unwind at the end of the year and embrace the new year to come. Usually at this time people would establish some kind of new year resolution (though I don’t usually do it myself). But after coming from such a turbulent year, at the very least for the majority of people, you might not be up for creating a new year resolution. Or perhaps you may be in a situation where your life and your surroundings is in such dissonance that you can’t make heads or tails of your life, let alone a new resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were to be honest, the transition between the past year to the new year is simply a second difference. Within one second there isn’t much that necessarily change. Rather than a new year, shouldn’t it instead be called a continuing year? Well either way, the point is that things don’t just rapidly change in a split second. Considering the situation with COVID-19, though there are hopeful sentiments on vaccine rollout, there is a real chance that the next few months in the year would feel very similar to last year. Yet, things continuously change, especially in the macro levels of our life and surroundings. In the sea of changes (and undoubtedly uncertainty), it gets difficult to pinpoint any kind of target we can aim for. In this blog post I would like to talk about a framework to help you think about meaningful targets in your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-digression-to-probability&quot;&gt;A digression to probability&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When working with probabilities you may have come across these set of symbols: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X|Y)&lt;/code&gt; (or some variant of it). In more plain English it reads out as &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;the probability of X happening given that event Y happened&lt;/code&gt;. For example, we can ask what is the probability that the cake I am baking is going to turn out well (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;X&lt;/code&gt;) given that I have followed the recipe to a tee (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt;), compared to simply asking what is the probability that the cake is going to turn out well (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X)&lt;/code&gt; only).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathemathically, the calculation for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X|Y)&lt;/code&gt; are vastly different and while there are more variables involved in the latter it can actually be easier to answer the latter than the former. Why is that so? Under the conditional probability you would be assuming that some event &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; has happened, constraining a part of the myriad possibilities of events that can occur to a single possibility. Meanwhile when you try to answer &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X)&lt;/code&gt; you have to take into account those other possibilities &lt;strong&gt;AND&lt;/strong&gt; also the possibilities of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But how does this relate to me you ask?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s replace &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;X&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;something&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; with you. From &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X|Y)&lt;/code&gt; we get &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?(something|you)&lt;/code&gt;, which now says &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;does this something matter given you&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conditional-situation-unconditional-you&quot;&gt;Conditional situation, unconditional you&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behavioural economist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Thaler&quot;&gt;Richard Thaler&lt;/a&gt; has said in his works that &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;People are not dumb. The world is hard&lt;/code&gt;. I think we do tend to agree that yes the world can be hard and that we don’t want to be called dumb. More so than us being dumb, it certainly does feel like the world can be tremendously difficult to cope with, example: &lt;em&gt;COVID-19&lt;/em&gt;. In a world where change is constant, it can get dizzyingly confusing and erratic to make sense of anything, let alone goals and targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my recent &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life&quot;&gt;post about budgeting&lt;/a&gt; I talked a bit identifying goals that are important for you. Part of the steps required to identify the important goals in your life would be to ask yourself whether those goals matter. Of course, the question of what matters to you does not stop at goals either. But the world’s hard, we’ve agreed on that, and there are so many competing viewpoints and opinions out there. And I haven’t even mentioned social media, you know that place where you can easily fall in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/ca/articles/201711/the-comparison-trap&quot;&gt;trap of comparisons&lt;/a&gt; against people you don’t even know across the whole world. Against all these variables, how do you come to decide what matters to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back to the transformed symbols I mentioned before, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?(something|you)&lt;/code&gt;. Reading it in plain English we have “does this thing matter, given you”. Just like how calculating conditional probability let us assume certain variables, let’s start by constraining from the one variable that stays relatively well known - you. Yes you. Wouldn’t it be easier to think about the things that matter when we only consider it from our personal perspective, history, experience, knowledge, plans, past, situation etc. I’m not saying that it would be easy (look at all those parts about you I just quickly mentioned!), but it does seem easier to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the world may move and change and be dizzyingly bizarre, the you that lives life second by second is likely to be majorly similar from each moment to moment, just like how the previous year transitions to the new year in a single second. Unconditionally you will remain similar to from before, and that non-conditionality I think will greatly help you to consider what truly matters for you. So my suggestion is to start thinking in the form of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?(something|you)&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?(something)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I call this the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;what matters, given you&lt;/code&gt; framework of thinking&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;focusing-on-the-simplicity&quot;&gt;Focusing on the simplicity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a reason why I used conditional probability as my analogy. I want to emphasize on the words &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;given you&lt;/code&gt;, which is intentionally used as a replacement for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;for you&lt;/code&gt;. The world’s complex, difficult, dynamic, rich and filled with other beings (human or otherwise). Obviously, the things that truly matter in the world and life are not just things that are related to you. In fact, some of those things that matter may be in complete contrast to what you may consider as important. But that’s why I framed the framework as I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought of the framework as a way to &lt;strong&gt;simplify the process of understanding what truly matters in life&lt;/strong&gt;. I propose that we can start thinking about the things that matter in our life by identifying the thing that we are most likely to know best and least varied, ourselves. In truth, there will and should be further variables taken into account, but those are for the next steps. The things that matter will not just be decided by you, but it would definitely involve you. &lt;strong&gt;It is not ourselves that is the focus, but we can use ourselves as a starting point&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I have been thinking a lot about my own goals in life, which led me to ask several times the things that matter in my life. I realize, even more so than any previous time of my life, that such an endeavour is incredibly difficult. It also doesn’t help that society and our culture imposes certain expectations, overt or otherwise, on us. But in an effort to regain some sense of control over my thoughts and opinions, I have started to try tackling these large and grand questions in more simple building blocks. The framework of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;what matters, given you&lt;/code&gt; is one of them that I have recently identified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for having read this blog post, I hope it has served useful for you. Happy new year.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="framework" /><category term="new year" /><category term="probability" /><summary type="html">Happy new year 2021! I hope you, the reader, had the opportunity to take the time to unwind at the end of the year and embrace the new year to come. Usually at this time people would establish some kind of new year resolution (though I don’t usually do it myself). But after coming from such a turbulent year, at the very least for the majority of people, you might not be up for creating a new year resolution. Or perhaps you may be in a situation where your life and your surroundings is in such dissonance that you can’t make heads or tails of your life, let alone a new resolution.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Budgeting in Life</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Budgeting in Life" /><published>2020-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life">&lt;p&gt;This year I’ve taken up more interest in personal finance, and starting to really think about longer term goals (5 to 10 years ahead for example) and thinking about the costs those goals would entail. As I look more into discovering my goals and how money interplays with it I’ve taken up budgeting much more seriously, and to some people’s surprise deriving joy out of it. I honestly think the few things that I’ve come to realize and went through is of such importance to me now that I truly believe it would hold importance for a great number of people too. So in this blog post I would like to talk about budgeting, and my thinking behind it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-budget&quot;&gt;What is a budget?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to search for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?client=firefox-b-d&amp;amp;q=what+is+a+budget&quot;&gt;“what is a budget?” on Google&lt;/a&gt; you would get a number of definitions covering a range of ideas but they largely ring the same ideas: financial planning, income and expense estimation, planning to spend your money etc. My personal take is that &lt;strong&gt;budgeting is specifically the art and process of allocating resources towards a goal&lt;/strong&gt;. In general the resources you can allocate through a budget can be anything, from something as concret as material resources to more abstract concepts such as time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how I did not add in an element of time to my description of a budget and this is deliberate. While budgeting is often cited as a way to manage money (and in general resources) in the future, in actual fact the act of managing future money requires management of money in the now. Additionally, the now is intricately linked to events and actions in the past. The baseline process can be visualized as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the goal in the future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan the required resources for the goal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the gaps, if any, between required and present situation. Start to act or plan to act based identified gaps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If actions can’t be taken, reflect on why and how it became to be so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Re-adjust future goal or consider to allocate further resources to achieve the goal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a cyclical and continuous process of estimation, towards the future, and reflection, of the past implemented in the present. As the needs and circumstances are identified it becomes more manageable to start implementing and taking the appropriate actions to realize the desired goal. Sometimes of course you may need to re-adjust the goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-purpose-of-allocation&quot;&gt;The purpose of allocation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The allocation of resources is simply one smaller part of budgeting, while the goal of budgeting is an even larger aspect. Without the goal, the allocation of resources would be meaningless. However, rather than focus on &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; the goal is, I would like to focus on &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; the goal is established. I think it is extremely important to start from your values when creating goals. Aligning your goals to your values, the things that you care deep down in your heart and mind, I think is extremely important. Not all goals should be of equal value to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, most people’s goal I would reckon is to grow up the career ladder which might not necessarily align with one’s values. Even though going up the career ladder may bring you greater income, something I’m sure many people will be happy to have, it may mean it comes with higher amounts of responsibility which leads to less family time. If family time is something of value to you, I would definitely say it would be prudent to reassess your goal. Is it something that you really want? It is a tremendous shame to see someone reach the goal that they have set, only to realize that the goal that they made for themselves were never the right destination to head towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not all goals should be of equal importance to you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting yourself with the question: “what is of value to me?” I believe will help you start with the right direction. Like a compass that helps ascertain the direction one is facing, your values will do the same for your goals. Once the direction is established, the range of destinations to get to will be clearer, and a clearer destination helps you to draw out the path to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-freedom-of-a-budget&quot;&gt;The freedom of a budget&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my friend dislikes budgeting, particularly with regards to budgeting as a personal financial practice. Their reason is that budgeting feels stifling, they dislikes the fact that when you financially budget you put restraints on what and how much you can spend. I think this line of thinking is not uncommon. But I would like to persuade whoever thinks so. Remember that in how I define budgeting I specifically use the word &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;allocation&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;goal&lt;/code&gt;. The allocation of resources towards the accomplishment of a goal is not a restriction, on the contrary it is a deliberate conscious &lt;strong&gt;permission&lt;/strong&gt; made by you so that you can put certain resources towards the goal. When you think of it this way, budgeting becomes the anti-thesis of a tool of restriction and instead it is a tool of &lt;strong&gt;freedom&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give a simple example. One of my goals is simply that I would like to be entertained a.k.a I don’t want to be bored. I identified that the kinds of entertainment that I like requires paying a certain price. I ask myself - “well me, how much do I want to be entertained?” of which I answer with “I think $50 of this kind of entertainment should keep me reasonably entertained and I know that I am able to”. So I set up a financial budget of $50 per month for entertainment. Now, every month I am free to use that allocated $50 budget for my entertainment purposes however I want. When I do so, I don’t need to feel guilty or bad or worried or panic or anything that you might associate spending money frivolously with - because I have allowed myself to spend that much. If I do feel guilty, for whatever reason, that should be a signal that the budget that I have set was not appropriate for my values, which in turn is not appropriate for my goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that by allocating only $50 in my example above a restriction is in place, set by myself, that I shouldn’t use more than $50 in a single month. Still, this restriction is one that I was freely able to make after considering my goals and values along with my current situation. The explicit process of identifying my goals and values and my current situation frees me up to make a conscious and informed decision that aligns both with the present situation and the future. Moreover, now you have freed up the rest of your resources for other goals that you want to strive for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;taking-budgeting-forward&quot;&gt;Taking budgeting forward&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year has been quite an overhaul on my approach towards budgeting. Before this year though I have target goals, I never enacted a budget as a way to help realize those goals in actuality. Moreover, I did not consider whether how I use my resources, predominantly time and money, aligns with not only my goals but also more importantly my values. Now that I have taken budgeting more seriously and consider how its implications I don’t see myself letting it go. If you read this far, I truly thank you for your time and allowing yourself to read this blog post. I hope it was a good use of your time resource and helped you achieve your goals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="finance" /><category term="planning" /><category term="goals and values" /><summary type="html">This year I’ve taken up more interest in personal finance, and starting to really think about longer term goals (5 to 10 years ahead for example) and thinking about the costs those goals would entail. As I look more into discovering my goals and how money interplays with it I’ve taken up budgeting much more seriously, and to some people’s surprise deriving joy out of it. I honestly think the few things that I’ve come to realize and went through is of such importance to me now that I truly believe it would hold importance for a great number of people too. So in this blog post I would like to talk about budgeting, and my thinking behind it</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Job Search In A Pandemic, Part 1</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/02/job-search-in-pandemic-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Job Search In A Pandemic, Part 1" /><published>2020-12-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/02/job-search-in-pandemic-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/02/job-search-in-pandemic-1">&lt;p&gt;Recently I have just transitioned to a new job position (2 months ago from the date of this post) and the experience of the search served to be a valuable feedback for me. Now job search is not something I look forward to and doing it in a pandemic does not make me more enthusiastic. But due to personal reasons my decision to move to a new job was already set in stone pandemic or otherwise. I am sure I am not the only one that have been doing job searches during these hard times, so I feel my experience may bring some value to those that want to or still are job searching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;background-and-timeline&quot;&gt;Background and timeline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For background I was applying software/data engineering jobs in Toronto, Canada when I was still in Vancouver, Canada. I finished my Masters program on early April and I was targeting for a job position by end of August, which is when I planned to move to Toronto. During my job search I was working as a software engineer for a company that knows about my moving plans. Due to situation I was mostly mass applying to all kinds of software engineering jobs, though my specialty and expertise lies in backend engineering. Here is my job search timeline:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started applying for jobs mid April to early May and then stopped because of a combination of a lack of motivation, jobs that match my preferences and feeling that it was a bit too far from August.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restarted looking for jobs early June, this continued up to the third week of August. Applied almost daily, 1 to 3 applications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By early july only a handful (around 5) of recruiters/companies have contacted me back. Phone call interviews did not go well. Decided to introspect what kind of jobs I really want and the value I can bring forth as an engineer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In late July got a phone call interview for a node.js developer position. Flunked that one, used it as an opportunity to learn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got a phone interview for my current company in early August, and managed to get past. Interview with management a week after, used the time to read up on company further and studied several materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Passed interview with management and recruiter was able to put me for the technical interview with the team on the next day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical interview went well, but with some hiccups. Ended with an offer that I took&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this blog post will be structured following the timeline I laid out above as each one has a different story to tell. Since it’s quite long I will break the blog post to two parts. Link for the second part will be added on later&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;timeline-1&quot;&gt;Timeline #1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In mid April I was just finishing up my masters studies. Not wanting to waste time I immediately started to look for job openings. I decided to change some of the formatting of my resume to what I think is cleaner and better aligned to my goal of finding a software engineering job. I primarily used Indeed and LinkedIn for my job search and my searches were honed in to a full time job for software/data engineering positions. I’ve never really worked on a conctractual basis so I wasn’t sure if I would like that, and with the pandemic going on I wanted to find something that would be long lasting for a sense of security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t much that happened during this period. I immediately noticed that many job positions were looking for more of a full-stack engineer and I really wanted to focus on backend. But since I do have a bit of frontend understanding (nothing modern or advanced) I soon decided to just apply to those that demanded full-stack capabilities, and even some that are purely frontend. Surely it is better to try and apply rather than not at all (right?). Of course, simply increasing the breadth of my applications did not mean it generated any positive results. Most of the applications I made were not receiving any replies, and if they were replied it was a rejection. Some of the reasons I came up for myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The employers weren’t interested in my application (this is likely the case for various reasons)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was quite open in stating that I was looking for a job starting at the soonest on August/September and perhaps it didn’t fit with the employers timeframe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some wild theory that companies weren’t actually looking to hire but just scouting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I never really know the reason, it did leave me feeling a bit dejected. Nearing May, I got a phone call from the employer that I worked for during my co-op  wondering if I can come to help them on their projects. I took the offer and became busy with work and left job search on the side thinking that it may be better to try and apply another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;timeline-2&quot;&gt;Timeline #2&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May most of my time was taken up by work and just spending my off-time relaxing by picking up some Switch games that I have neglected. When June arrived I noticed that I haven’t been looking for jobs ever since I stopped. There is only 3 months left until I move to Toronto and that felt too close comfort. It’s actually a bit funny thinking back on how a month’s difference makes my perception of time availability turn 180 degrees, from “I have time” to “I don’t have time”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to improve from my previous attempts at applications I decided to look back to my resume and cover letter once more. Some of the things that I did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I noticed some inconsistencies in formatting and some grammatical improvements to be made in my resume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I put more emphasis on the job experiences that I wanted to highlight and be proud of by reordering them and using active words&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I created several copies of my resume, only differing in the job title that I wanted to present myself as depending on the application&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I decided to create a standard cover letter resume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would think that one of the things that I would have done was to have a connection review my resume in the list above, but as you there is no mention of it. Why? The reason is simple, I was too afraid to ask it to be critiqued by another set of eyes. Honestly, I should have sought someone to critique it for me, but I was simply too scared at the thought of being shot down, getting told that what I have won’t impress anyone and overall deflating my confidence and spirit. Deep down I know I have some issues with imposter syndrome, and honestly sometimes I do believe that I am incapable. Some time in the future I would probably write another blog post about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;timeline-3&quot;&gt;Timeline #3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job search did not go well. The number of applications that resulted into responses can be counted on one hand, while in total I probably applied to at least 50 applications (1 - 3 applications per day, at least 5 days per week). The ratio of “success”, success here simply getting a reply, is less than 1-to-10, yikes. Furthermore, I was sure not able to impress recruiters in my phone interviews. At some moments I did think that maybe it was all because of COVID19 and the job search climate. But I decided that even if that was the case, &lt;strong&gt;it was something that I can’t control&lt;/strong&gt;. No matter how much I groan, my groaning would not lead to the outcome I desire, getting a job. So I further expanded my effort to improve my application process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I challenged myself to answer the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What kind of job I really want? Does industry matter?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What responsibilities would I best be able to serve in? What technologies that I know that can benefit the company I apply to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answering the two questions above I decided to stop applying to frontend-heavy jobs. I would still apply to a full stack positions, but mostly those that are more backend oriented. While this is doubling down on a specific engineering area, it is really where I want to be and where I feel I can contribute best as an employee. With that in mind I reviewed my resume and cover letter once more to change how I present myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most extensive work experience were with messaging/event-driven and data streaming oriented systems which coincidentally I enjoyed and was partly the reason to why I took a masters program. Therefore I made those experiences my main highlight in both my resume and cover letter. There isn’t many applications that directly mention such systems, but I wanted to put myself forward not as an all-rounder programmer that has no specialty. I wanted to be seen as someone that has a specialty but also possessing a broad range of skills. The next major experience that I highlight is designing and building REST APIs, which at least gets mentioned a lot in job postings. Lastly, I made sure to put myself as a developer that cares for quality in my cover letter by putting some emphasis on TDD and other engineering principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the highlight of this timeline must be this: &lt;strong&gt;I started blogging and putting time for personal projects&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is actually no coincidence that I started blogging more from beginning of July. My lack of progress in job search led me to find other avenues I can make progress in. Blogging was one of those avenues I wanted to invest myself more in, and also a relatively easy way to gain a sense of progress. For the same reason, I also started to do more programming in my own free time. While it isn’t the progress that I need, I felt it was tremendously helpful to gain a sense of momentum in life and also combating my imposter syndrome. I needed to not just feel, but know and see that I am capable of doing something I can take pride and ownership in. Had I not decided to start blog more or code on the side, I absolutely believe that it would have been much harder for me to push myself forward and continue job search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;to-be-continued&quot;&gt;To be continued&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post has gotten quite long already and I don’t want to bore you to death with my life story. So feel free to close off the tab now, I will post the next part in the future. If you managed to read up to here, honestly thank you for reading the diary entries of a man on the internet. See you in the next part.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="reflection" /><category term="jobs" /><category term="software engineering" /><summary type="html">Recently I have just transitioned to a new job position (2 months ago from the date of this post) and the experience of the search served to be a valuable feedback for me. Now job search is not something I look forward to and doing it in a pandemic does not make me more enthusiastic. But due to personal reasons my decision to move to a new job was already set in stone pandemic or otherwise. I am sure I am not the only one that have been doing job searches during these hard times, so I feel my experience may bring some value to those that want to or still are job searching.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RIL - Financial Investing in the Market</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/09/03/learning-financial-investment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RIL - Financial Investing in the Market" /><published>2020-09-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/09/03/learning-financial-investment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/09/03/learning-financial-investment">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/56b1a53/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5760x3840+0+0/resize/840x560!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F82%2F78%2Fbaeb7fd7452ca0b59b92175c0d92%2Faptopix-financial-markets-wall-street-11829.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Poor man in a stock market exchange seems to be in pain, while I am writing a blog about my own journey with less pain&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past few months I have been dipping my feet to some financial investment vehicles. I primarily invest in broad based market indices, with certain product tilts that I’ve chosen to be fit for myself. The point of this post is not to suggestany particular investment products or vehicles, but instead to share what I’ve personally learned as an individual as I continue to invest and re-think my own financial position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-i-invest&quot;&gt;Why I Invest&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going further to what I have learnt, giving a backstory would be beneficial to see where I am coming from. Currently my main reason for investing is for retirement. Now I’m pretty far away from any thoughts of wanting to retire or close to the expected retirement age which is 65 in Canada, 39 years away from the time of this writing. So you might ask if retirement is really something that I should be considering about, so here’s my pitch to why I think its an appropriate time for me to start considering it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/t1/tbl1/en/tv.action?pid=1310013401&quot;&gt;Statistics Canada&lt;/a&gt;, the life expectancy for a male of my age is around 78. Considering that I’m living in a pretty well-off country with social and health support I’ll assume that I can almost be assured to live to the age of 60. If I do manage to get to age 60, my life expectancy would be around 80 years old (and in general my life expectancy would increase as I continue to age). Now assume that I might want to have an early retirement at age 60, which is not uncommon to do, with the expectation that I will not have any income stream during my retirement. Additionally, say I want to have a spending power of 20k every year, for the next 20 years, then that means that I need to have 400k set aside. If I manage to save 1k for every month up to the year of my retirement, I would manage to save 408k, just barely meeting the 400k threshold. But this situation oversimplifies things as I haven’t calculated emergency spending, sickness, large payments such as buying assets, mortgage, pension income, income increase (or decrease) and many more. Suffice to say however, this quick calculation shows that relying on income and saving habits alone may mean that I may very well be short of my retirement income goal, and may mean less than desirable retirement days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lessons-i-learnt&quot;&gt;Lessons I Learnt&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve explained and hopefully convinced you why starting to plan for retirement as early as now is reasonable, I want to go over the lessons that I’ve learned. There are three categories: goal setting and planning, rationality and expectation, humility&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goal-setting-and-planning&quot;&gt;Goal Setting And Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I approached investing as another source of income and a general way for me to get money. It is not wrong that I can get income, or at least appreciation of my capital, through investing, but over time I realized that having this generic hope of getting more money didn’t help me. It didn’t help me because I didn’t have anything in particular that I was trying to achieve, and while getting more income and money is good, I didn’t necessarily feel driven by it because I felt that I can get by with what I have without investing. It is only after I laid out what I want (the goal), and start to look at how I can achieve it (the planning), that I felt financial investing started to be more interesting and something I want to take seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goal setting and planning is not constrained to investments and financial activities of course, but financial health and planning can certainly help normalize the habit because it is often related to a familiar and quantifiable form which is money. Setting goals make, and sub-goals, makes even a long-term goal such as retirement more mentally acessible and approachable, particularly when paired with clear quantifiable metrics. It has also helped me in envisioning the time horizon of my activities (in this case my investment activities), which helps me to assess the decisions that I make and whether they are in line with what is demanded of my goal. If I know I need to save 1k every month to reach my minimum desired retirement days, then saving 500 for a month is a clear overstep of what is needed to achieve my goals. At the same time, knowing that I have a long time horizon for my goal means that I am learning to expect and include in my planning unexpected events, which helps me to further prepare in the face of such events and to develop flexible plans around such potentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rationality-and-expectation&quot;&gt;Rationality and Expectation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the resources I found and have been using frequently for my financial literacy and assessment is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/RATIONALREMINDER&quot;&gt;The Rational Reminder Podcast&lt;/a&gt;. The channel goes over a lot of decision making and thinking processes that aim to be as rational as possible (with acknowledgement that we are emotional and social beings). This way of thinking has really shaped my understanding of financial well-being as being founded upon sound and rational decisions &lt;em&gt;WITH&lt;/em&gt; appropriate expectations. What do I mean here by appropriate expectations? Well one simple example is packaged in the common saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;past performance is not guarantee of future performance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s simply a statement that the past is not a perfect indicator of the future, which in hindsight is something that is easily agreeable. The problem is that a lot of the times our decision are heavily biased towards our past experiences, sidelining the evidences in front of us of the present situation. When investing it can be easy to fall in the trap of doubling down on a well performing asset in the past, thinking that its good performance will continue unabated. Or perhaps we would think we will be able to &lt;em&gt;pull out&lt;/em&gt; from our choice when things look sour, something extremely difficult to do correctly for the plain reason that we do not have a perfect oracle into the future, and our insight can be influenced by non-evidence based reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related to goal setting and planning, I’m continuously learning to find reasonable expectations for my investments according to my goal. Since my goal is for the long-term I am setting up my investment positions to reflect that. Keeping this in mind has helped me to deal with the volatility shocks of the market. I cannot expect that my investment will continuously be increasing in value with such a long timespan, knowing that the market &lt;em&gt;IS&lt;/em&gt; volatile and &lt;em&gt;MUST&lt;/em&gt; be so in order to be profitable. It would be irrational of me to think otherwise, and likewise thus irrational of me to react as if it is unexpected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, acknowledgement that there are elements out of my control in the performance of my investments is helping me to isolate the reasons for the results of my decisions. Often we think good results is an indicator of good decisions, which is not necessarily true, especially in an environment where there is little that you can do to affect the results such as the market. Therefore it has been a learning point for me to assess the quality of my decisions according to what is accessible, knowledge and affect-wise, to me. This certainly helps in moderating both my expectations and having a more appropriate reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;humility&quot;&gt;Humility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finance is definitely not my forte. When dealing with the market there are additional elements of social expectations, economics, politics, and many more, none of which are my forte. Trying to understand basic terminologies and concepts took me hours and some late night sleeps. I enjoyed them for sure, but it’s not easy, plus I’m definitely still far from being financially literate, at least to the degree that I want. Yet I still decide to invest into the market, because I (optimistically perhaps) believe that the information that I have found and learned has come from well-meaning and knowledgeable experts and that as a whole the market will perform adequately to grow its value. Combined with lessons learnt in adopting more rational expectations, I acknowledge that I am riding on the shoulders of giants. It is a humbling feeling knowing that there is so much more for me to know, and that I shouldn’t expect results are necessarily driven by my abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;finishing-words&quot;&gt;Finishing Words&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every lesson I’ve shared here has been eye-opening and I take them fully to heart. Though I spent the least in talking about it, the lesson of humility is likely the most important for me. I expect the lessons I’ve taken so far will be applicable in all aspects of my life and I am certainly looking forward to learn, and share, further lessons in my financial journey.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="finance" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">Poor man in a stock market exchange seems to be in pain, while I am writing a blog about my own journey with less pain</summary></entry></feed>