<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-12T21:09:07-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">btruhand - scattering of thoughts</title><subtitle>Btruhand's blogging outlet, ranging from technical writeups to social opions</subtitle><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Agile is Experimentation</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/07/12/agile-as-experimentation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agile is Experimentation" /><published>2021-07-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-07-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/07/12/agile-as-experimentation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/07/12/agile-as-experimentation">&lt;p&gt;Recently I had a conversation with two gents about software development and the word “Agile” propped up. As software engineers, or even business management these days, the word agile is everywhere. In job postings, in company slogans, in company talks, on our computer screens, and in our purported work values. But I know from personal feelings, observations and anecdotes there is some distaste to “agile” and that it feels more than anything like hype, buzzword, and even worse at times feels like a marketing tool to attract talent which sadly does not deliver. Then there is the frustration of very few seemingly have a good grasp of what “agile” is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as per my usual inquiring-and-chatty-self I asked the two gents, “So, what does agile mean to you?”. And I purposefully directed the question to them through the vocabulary “you” because I want to understand their own personal mental model of Agile. I do not care about Scrum, Kanban or whatever new Agile framework out there is, I wanted to get to the fundamental of Agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first said that for him Agile is all about doing breaking up the work and taking them up. He stated that the importance is not in the pointing mechanism itself, but more in actually being able to take up and do the work. The other said that Agile for him is all about the small iterative steps that is aimed for continuous refinement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these kind of mental models of Agile is quite common. Generally they are surmised by these adjectives or nouns: ‘iterative’, ‘small’, ‘continuous improvement’. But I would like to further refine this understanding of iteration for in my honest optionion it doesn’t quite make the mark of what Agile really is. So let’s do that in this post, let’s try to develop a better mental model of Agile&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here is my take: The main abstraction provided by Agile is experimentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;experimentation-first-the-rest-is-by-product&quot;&gt;Experimentation first, the rest is by-product&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As software engineers we love to abstract things away, to turn details into common patterns that can be encoded as a set of computer interactions (algorithms basically) to solve a problem, or class of problems. As a software engineer I posit that the main abstraction that Agile brings is experimentation in order to solve the problem of business development and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I say experimentation, I really mean experimentation as in the scientific method sense:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/82/The_Scientific_Method.svg/1024px-The_Scientific_Method.svg.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A picture of the scientific method, which is an on-going process. Source - Wikipedia&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I posit that Agile is really all about experimentation brought to business practice, then there are four elements that businesses adopting Agile must absolutely meet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A hypothesis to test&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mechanisms to perform tests for or against the hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The gathering of, and capability to assess data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A commitment and understanding to learn and adapt continuously based on feedback of previous experiments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When viewing and applying Agile as experimentation through the scientific method towards business, iteration and continuous improvement is a given. It simply becomes a by-product. Small requires an additional perspective which I will touch later on, but I assure you that it remains a by-product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;on-hypotheses-and-testing&quot;&gt;On hypotheses and testing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I would like to touch on hypothesization and testing because as a software engineer this is where a lot of software engineer’s time is spent struggling on. It shouldn’t and definitely isn’t the only phase in the Agile cycle where software engineers are involved in, but I find a lot of software engineers along with their business counterparties stumble in these areas often. The stumbles that occur here impede the whole Agile flow, and impacts its adoption within a team and potentially organization at large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poorly-made-hypotheses&quot;&gt;Poorly made hypotheses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of the hypothesis is often estranged from the software engineers’ work and by that I mean something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Business asks for a feature &amp;gt; Business comes up with requirements &amp;gt; Business forks over requirements to engineers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two problems with this kind of “hypothesization”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It isn’t really framed as a hypothesis. A hypothesis is about creating an assumption that is meant to be further investigated. Hence a hypothesis must always be made with the presupposition and even expectation that it may be false or incorrect. So a rewording may say that “Business thinks that a feature would be useful to be developed” instead. &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/eozFlgu6ByY&quot;&gt;Dave Farley in his video&lt;/a&gt; covers this idea of expecting false assumptions further and better than I do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The software engineers are often the people who procure the experimentation “ingredients” (code and machineries) and make the testing of the hypothesis possible. When the those that are creating the test experiments are not involved in the development of the hypothesis, there is significant risk that what would be setup does not reflect what the hypothesis is claiming. In other words - what software engineers develop may stray away tremendously from what the business actually needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;failure-to-perform-tests-for-the-hypothesis&quot;&gt;Failure to perform tests for the hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming that the software engineers have managed to scrounged up some code for the hypothesis, Agile as experimentation would say the next step is to test that the hypothesis is correct. You can also say you can (and probably should) test that the implementation of the hypothesis is correct. But too many organizations forego this step, likely because they do not think of Agile as experimentation. The result of this in my experience usually leads to (in order of severity and face-palm worthiness, with some embellishment):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never testing it because the software never got released in fear of what can go wrong (and also not knowing what can go right)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Letting the majority of the users be the one and only tester of the hypothesis - it’s not a bug, it’s a feature (or it’s not a feature, it’s a bug)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business performs tests on their side only at the very end when every hypothesis are realized as code. Then they spectacularly notice that nothing works as hypothesized&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software engineers never testing out their code and solution before running experiments. Usually exacerbating the length of feedback loops and by the time they are aware of issues highlighted in experiment results they already forgot what they did&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Silo’d QA teams that have no idea what is happening and have poor awareness of the hypothesis that needs to be tested&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of testing, and the inability to perform testing whether because of technological unreadiness or organizational politics impedes the collection of data. Without this data, Agile breaks down because the next experiment cycle will be disconnected from the previous. And even if the next experiment cycle does not have anything to do with the previous one, without testing the experiment cycle is incomplete. Yet many teams and businesses readily jump in to the next experiment without really finishing the previous one at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be noted that the procurement of data and testing of the hypothesis in Agile may come from various tests and groups of testers. This idea of diverse testers should be intuitive in both its concept and also importance. In fact, the differing kinds of testers at times also help keep the experiment iteration small. For example, software engineers as testers is likely (or hopefully) testing a small piece of the hypothesis in a fairly quick manner, keeping the experiment and feedback fast and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;failures-in-adopting-agile&quot;&gt;Failures in adopting Agile&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve postulated Agile as primarily an experimentation it becomes we can look at the potential concrete reasons why Agile adoption fails. And here is where the pscyhology aspect of working with or within Agile becomes more prominent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mischaracterization-of-agile&quot;&gt;Mischaracterization of Agile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that is quite likely to have happened is that the organization has mischaracterized Agile as a set of procedures and formal methodologies. This is exactly not what Agile was meant to be based on the Agile manifesto. The focus is likely to have been aimed at adopting Scrum or Kanban methodologies while missing the essence of Agile; an abstraction for scientific experimentation for the business problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-off-from-being-wrong&quot;&gt;Closing off from being wrong&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you watched Dave Farley’s video that I linked above you should understand where I am coming from with this. Experimentation necessitates that there is an uncertainty that wants to be further investigated. By nature this must mean that incorrect hypothesis and even seemingly unfruitful effort will be made as business attempt to solve problems through products, services and processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of being wrong is psychologically difficult to reconciliate with. There is also a social dimension to it which hits some people harder than others, for legitimate and illegitimate reason. But even disregarding that, our brain and ego often limits our ability to accept mistakes, by others or ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inability-to-change&quot;&gt;Inability to change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific method is a continuous loop. Each loop may feed in new data points and observations for the next loop. Iteration is enabled by the successive feed of data from one step to another. But some experiments will inevitably challenge our assumptions and hence our cycle. More likely though, challenges will come from external sources Agile processes. It is unlikely that your Agile journey will be a sequence of smooth loops; they say the only constant is change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disregarding turbulent external change, Agile itself promotes change, and so it must be something that teams and organizations can work and be comfortable with. But inherently change is difficult to do. There is technical aspect of change which is difficult in itself which covers aspects of software design, architecture, CI/CD and many more. Then there is the fragility of our human cognition in accepting change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need for change may be brought by previously held incorrect hypothesis or experimentations. And we’ve said that accepting being wrong in itself is already hard. Even if it isn’t necessitated by previous missteps we may be prone to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Status_quo_bias&quot;&gt;status quo bias&lt;/a&gt;. Or perhaps we have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.behavioraleconomics.com/resources/mini-encyclopedia-of-be/sunk-cost-fallacy/&quot;&gt;sunk cost fallacy&lt;/a&gt; towards our previous assumptions. Erroneously, some organizations may situate themselves to be unable to respond to the need for change because of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End-of-history_illusion&quot;&gt;end-of-history illusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;uncontrolled-change&quot;&gt;Uncontrolled change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some organizations do change, to the point of being overwhelmed by change. Change is difficult, and more so when change happens frequently and in an unstructured fashion. The COVID-19 pandemic has thought us that we need to change our long-held practices. But the deluge, abrupt and perhaps unprecedented scale of change that needs to be adapted for the modern era made many of us grind to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of our difficulty when change is uncontrolled:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small businesses anguish at ever changing regulations and response turbulence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Health officials saying they are doing science by looking and listening to the evidence that is constantly changing based on new data points. To many it seems these officials are flip-flopping and changing their stance or suggestions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scrum, Kanban and other Agile methodologies particularly shine here by bringing in a framework that acts as a guidance. In particular the emphasis on the dissection of experiments into smaller pieces helps to make change feel and be manageable. But these methodologies work best when the change being brought are iterative towards some form of north star, a loose trajectory guidance. When the north star itself is what keeps changing, many will find it difficult to handle what often becomes uncontrolled change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;industrial-friction&quot;&gt;Industrial friction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming that individuals within the organization themselves can apply Agile as a way of experimentation, there are still industrial challenges to the adoption of Agile. Such challenges may come internally or externally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internally, the problems mentioned above can equally be replicated and exacerbated on the organizational level. So there are the pscyhological dimensions on the individual and corporate that needs to be addressed in the adoption of Agile. Many organizations are still not comfortable yet in performing experiments; in hypothesizing, testing, analyzing data and rinse and repeat. They view business problems as work that needs to be steamrolled in one go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Externally, some organizations are situated within an industry that makes experimentation difficult. These industries often have low tolerance for mistakes. Arguably all industries are intolerant for mistakes, but some just feel more daunting than others, whether that is true or not is another topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite internal or external friction, it is possible to adopt Agile methodologies in gradients. While indeed Agile can be adopted within the context of “move fast and break things”, it can also be adapted in more nuanced and smaller scale. I take inspiration from SpaceX that continuously runs launch experiments against their hypothetical products. The level of funding needed to run these experiments, which may end with million-dollars fireworks, is ludicrously high. Yet, SpaceX shows that it is possible that Agile is possible even in high-stake. So instead of fully backing off from Agile, we can try to see at which parts of our organizations do Agile make sense and in what form. At the very least I think all software engineering teams can adopt Agile at least by adopting CI/CD pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: Dave Farley has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/v8f6q4ruvds&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; more on SpaceX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-comments&quot;&gt;Final comments&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear Agile, I always think of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://agilemanifesto.org/&quot;&gt;Agile Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;. We know that at the heart of it Agile is not Scrum, and it is not Kanban. I posit it as the abstraction of the scientific experimentation to solve business problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing Agile as experimentation puts a lot of emphasis on &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Working software&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Responding to change&lt;/code&gt; of the Manifesto. In particular, the Agile experiments are there to serve as a way to create software that works (for customers, not just for computers) according to battle-tested hypotheses. The experimental loop fundamentally necessitates organizations to expect change from the Agile cycles, and also from external forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this helps you in truly bringing Agile chnages to your organization.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="software development" /><category term="management" /><category term="organizational techniques" /><summary type="html">Recently I had a conversation with two gents about software development and the word “Agile” propped up. As software engineers, or even business management these days, the word agile is everywhere. In job postings, in company slogans, in company talks, on our computer screens, and in our purported work values. But I know from personal feelings, observations and anecdotes there is some distaste to “agile” and that it feels more than anything like hype, buzzword, and even worse at times feels like a marketing tool to attract talent which sadly does not deliver. Then there is the frustration of very few seemingly have a good grasp of what “agile” is.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">EUPHORIA - An acronym for financial well-being</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/05/02/euphoria-acronym" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EUPHORIA - An acronym for financial well-being" /><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/05/02/euphoria-acronym</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/05/02/euphoria-acronym">&lt;p&gt;It has been a while since my latest blog post and this time I’m writing out of whimsical inspiration. I was browsing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/PersonalFinanceCanada/&quot;&gt;PersonalFinanceCanada sub-Reddit&lt;/a&gt; and saw a question about being mindful of lifestyle creep. If you don’t know what lifestyle creep is, it basically means ever increasingly extravagant lifestyle, usually marked with fancier material posessions, dinners or experiences. It usually coincides with increases in salary, relocation or a momentous life event (such as a financial windfall).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually (though not everyone necessarily sees this way), lifestyle creep has a negative connotation, particularly because it usually hampers someone’s ability to save for their future. Suffice to say that the poster of the thread was of that mindset. So I came up with the acronym &lt;strong&gt;EUPHORIA&lt;/strong&gt;, hoping that it can be of help to the poster. And I hope an expansion of the acronym in this blog post will also help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;e---envision-where-you-want-to-be&quot;&gt;E - Envision where you want to be&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.halhershfield.com/&quot;&gt;Hal Hershfield&lt;/a&gt;, a UCLA researcher in the domain of behavioural decision making has conducted studies into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.halhershfield.com/research-index&quot;&gt;effectiveness of envisioning yourself into the future&lt;/a&gt;. He contends that interestingly, often we treat ourselves in the future as completely different people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While at first it may be surprising, intuitively you can kind of see why that may be the case. It is unsurprising to us now that though the world is ever more connected through the Internet, the lack of physical proximity may still cause a toll in our connection and relationship with others. Similarly ourselves in the future are temporally distant to ourselves. But at the very least space is arguably a visible and felt concept while time is more nebulous and seemingly unfelt, and you certainly never feel like slamming against time as you do against a wall. Compound this with the idea of trying to project yourself into the future several years ahead and you would likely have a hard time accurately depicting what you will be like into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know about you, but I certainly have moments of surprises when I think back what I was like 5 years ago compared to how I am now. I find it surprising not because of how extraordinarily different I am now than what I hope to be, but simply because I didn’t even imagine a world where I am like I am now. In his research Hal and his colleagues identified that given effective cues to both visually and imaginatively one’s future self, those that were studied were able to make better savings decisions. They contend that the exercise helped create a connection between the present and future selves which helped participants to &lt;strong&gt;discount future rewards less&lt;/strong&gt;. In other words they were better able to appreciate the value of delayed gratification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;u---understand-yourself&quot;&gt;U - Understand yourself&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If self envisioning can help you to more seriously aim for desired future targets to achieve, then the next question would be to ask what kind of targets you would like to pursue. While you can try to envision what, how and where you want to be in the future, it is still notoriously difficult to understand the &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; of the goals you are making. In a &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/post/2021/01/05/what-matters-given-you&quot;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; I talked a bit on the topic of exploring what matters for yourself. In the post I advocate for the notion of focusing on your situation to find out what is important for you. The blog post was inspired by the larger notion of self-understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The hardest but most important financial skill is getting the goalpost to stop moving - Morgan Housel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it so hard? Morgan argues that in order to keep the goalpost from moving requires a sense of having enough. But our sense of needs and wants live in a continuum scale, and probability will tell you that identifying the chances of a single point in the scale to materialize is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Probability_distribution#Continuous_probability_distribution&quot;&gt;a flat zero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a perfect understanding of what is enough for us need not be the case. We simply need to be able to narrow it down enough to a small band of area in the needs and wants spectrum such that we can confidently say that anywhere within this small band we are content and can continue to be so. To be able narrow the ban BUT also stay confident in our judgement of what brings us contentment, joy, happiness, fulfillment etc. the ability to understand ourself is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example: for myself I am keeping a “decision log” that tracks my investment decisions. It helps me record and assess my actions such that I don’t just understand myself by how I feel, but also by what I actually did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;p---prioritize-what-is-important-not-what-is-nice&quot;&gt;P - Prioritize what is important, not what is nice&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if you are able to both envision yourself, and continuously improve your understanding of yourself, you will now come to the impasse of how to proceed with life such that you can reach that envisioned content self. Between now and the future we all notice that there is no magical time leap machine we can take such that we can jump through the hoops of process and life. So we must take things step by step, which requires us to &lt;em&gt;create prioritizations in life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally the act of prioritization is akin to the act of making decisions. For this I will direct you to this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZU2VOXH2PI4&amp;amp;t=2s&quot;&gt;Rational Reminder podcast episode #120 with Annie Duke&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I want to say though is that it is okay if you find your prioritizations to shift and change over time. Independently, envisioning and understanding yourself is already difficult, even more so when you start thinking of things and steps you would like to prioritize in order to achieve your goals and targets. The point is to be able to commit to the things that you have identified to be important, and if you realize eventually that they are not as important as you think they were, your vision for the future and the understanding you have for yourself will act as your lighthouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of us have heard of tales of regret from those whose lives have run out short. The least we want to be is be that someone that poured our resources for that extra dash of glittering junk in life, while missing the real beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;h---hold-off-from-making-hasty-decision&quot;&gt;H - Hold off from making hasty decision&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have heard of the tale of the GameStop mania in early 2021. Basically the story goes that GameStop’s stock experienced a massive increase in price, over a whopping 2000% growth from January 1st, 2021 of the year to its highest point on January 27th, 2021. Many people took a substantial amount of profit from this and those are the headlines you would like to see (or maybe not if you are feeling sour about it), but how many people &lt;em&gt;LOST&lt;/em&gt; money?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know the global number, but here I’ll take a sample (and for sure a biased one to make a point). Based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wealthsimple.com/en-ca/magazine/gme-data&quot;&gt;Wealthsimple’s report&lt;/a&gt; 67% of people that invested in the GameStop stock (GME) lost money. The holding period is an average of 4.5 days, not very long. So what does this say? Well, in general the average investor likely saw the craze, for whatever reason decided to jump in to the craze, and then seemingly as fast as they went in they got out of it. It’s good that many didn’t lose more than 1000, but financially it would’ve been better that they didn’t lose any. Ah but perhaps they were allured at the &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; prospect&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile one of the earliest believers in the GME stock, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith_Gill&quot;&gt;Keith Gill&lt;/a&gt;, made millions out of this episode (and have not fully cashed out at the time of this writing), but he was holding the stock for a much longer period than 4.5 days. He held the stock since September 2019, whilst during that time the GME stock kept going lower AND he was making YouTube content talking about his position, making his thoughts and opinions public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against all odds AND viewing eyes, Keith held on and continued to have conviction. Yes his conviction may have turned out to be a bad result, but you cannot deny his conviction. At least in contrast to some of his peers with a holding period of 4.5 days, his decision definitely seems less hasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it is not necessarily the time horizon that I want to focus on, but the reasoning and believe you have over your decisions that I want to highlight. Remember, your future self and your self-understanding continues to be your lighthouse. Here’s another way to get my message across:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgflip.com/580uty.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Courtesy of imgflip&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;o---organize-your-finances-and-be-on-top-of-it&quot;&gt;O - Organize your finances and be on top of it&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What you do not measure, you do not know&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably a pretty common saying you may have heard somewhere in your professional career or even the Internet. Leaving a side the origins of the statement and how accurate it is, it is undeniable that observability, data and understanding over that data is becoming more important in the digital age. Data is the new gold they say. So why not bring to your personal finance life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am an &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life&quot;&gt;advocator for budgeting&lt;/a&gt;. I am not a budgeting expert, but I try to budget and set myself expenditure targets. It helps me understand where my money is going, where I want it to go, and any discrepancy between reality and desire that may happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a more universal topic, mayhaps you have heard tales of people who get swamped in their purchasing debt and are having trouble keeping a rein on it or improving the situation. And if you are Canadian you probably have heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L0JI-rWPG3Y&quot;&gt;hearsay speak about how high personal debt is in Canada&lt;/a&gt;(and continue to grow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are possibly some structural issues that people may be facing, it can also be useful to bring in specialized financial organization tools. Coupled with a vision for your future self, an understanding of oneself, commitment to prioritization and identification of what is important and holding off from making hasty decisions, these organization tools can be immensely powerful in paving the way for financial wellness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some tools that you can try to look into:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wealthica.com/&quot;&gt;Wealthica&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mint.intuit.com/&quot;&gt;Mint.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zero-basedbudget.com/&quot;&gt;Zero based budgeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youneedabudget.com/&quot;&gt;YNAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good old Excel spreadsheets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;r---run-from-comparison&quot;&gt;R - Run from comparison&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another commonly heard phrase:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Comparison is the thief of joy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was small, from time to time I get compared by my parents to some other kid they knew. Luckily it wasn’t often for me, but when it did happen it always felt unnerving and discomforting. Even for the pettiest of things (at least in my head), such as who dresses nicer (definitely not me), it would still be a bit of a sting. A sting to my pride, confidence and yes, joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not dislike all kinds of comparisons. In fact, it is useful to be able to compare one thing over another, a lot of our decisions are a matter of extracting conclusions from comparisons. But there are certainly good AND bad comparisons. Remember how apples aren’t necessarily comparable to oranges? The same case applies often when we are compared against one another. A person’s situation may seem similar but contain vastly differing details. A comparison that does not really apply equal criteria and assumptions likewise is not a good comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when it comes to finances, it is also equally important to NOT make comparisons against others yourself. Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/global/2017/may/11/outclassed-neighbors-income-happiness&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; that mentions that social and wealth comparisons are detrimental for your psyche, and there are other research delving into the topic. It is the case irrespective of who is initiating the comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think in recent years we have started to learn the lesson from our exposure to social media, and we can apply the same wisdom there with our financial lives. Some people may be able to tolerate it, some may even revel in it. But it is probably best for most if not all of us, to run from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;i---involve-your-partner-in-the-discussion&quot;&gt;I - Involve your partner in the discussion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that marriage is costly? Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weddingwire.ca/wedding-ideas/how-much-does-the-average-wedding-cost-in-canada--c1677&quot;&gt;an article from WeddingWire&lt;/a&gt; that says the average Canadian wedding costs 29,450 CAD (maybe it has gone down during the pandemic though). But I contend that divorce is costlier. You get the mental and physical stress, arguments, fear, trauma, child care disputes, legal costs and also on top of it the financial costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not going to be a fair example for daily people like you and me but consider Jeff and Mackenzie Bezos’ divorce. Depending on how you see it, Mackenzie (Jeff) got (lost) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weddingwire.ca/wedding-ideas/how-much-does-the-average-wedding-cost-in-canada--c1677&quot;&gt;38 billion USD in Amazon stock&lt;/a&gt;. Financially a big win for Mackenzie, but at the very least a dent into Jeff’s financial situation. As I’ve noted this is not a fair nor representative example of the average person, but it strikes an example of how costly financially a divorce can be. As your marriage (or even just dating) there are some assets that have been grown together between the you and your partner, a big one would be housing usually, which would somehow need to be divided amongst the both of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insauga.com/many-canadian-couples-open-about-their-finances-survey&quot;&gt;an article&lt;/a&gt; that may be closer to home for young Canadian couples. It seems that financial communication has improved for these couples, yet still there are a significant percentage feeling like they are struggling to meet their financial goals. Communication is on aspect, but when I say “involve your partner” I mean so much more. It is about bringing your partner along with your journey of self-envisioning, self-understanding, self prioritization etc. Transforming the self into a process and activity of togetherness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me try to inspire you with my own experience. Compared to me my partner isn’t at all interested in investments. I don’t try to force her into it but I explain to her about the things I do, and likewise she explains to me her thought process. While not much, but I managed to help her started with investing bit by bit, with what we think is suitable for her at this time. Everytime I think something good can be done for her investments I consult her, and I let her have the final say. Sometimes I want to do things faster, but she doesn’t. Sometimes I share investment material and discuss financial topics or scenarios with her, as much as she is willing to take. In doing all this I’ve made it clear to her that I want her to be financially ready and successful, regardless if I am there in her life or not. While we may be different in many ways, this is a common goal and journey that we are both working towards for each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a---automate-where-possible&quot;&gt;A - Automate where possible&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a software engineer, automation naturally plays a big role in my life. I love to be able to automate the rote work I need to do day to day. Not only is it faster, if done well it can help bring a much needed simplicity to my activities. And the same case applies to finances, if not even more so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money has been a very emotionally related and charged topic in our culture. It has led to one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/financial-consumer-agency/services/financial-wellness-work/stress-impacts.html&quot;&gt;greatest stressors in people’s lives&lt;/a&gt;. Let alone making investments, people sometimes don’t know what to do to keep things afloat! Automation can’t help to start to fill all the holes caused by financial stress, but I believe it can greatly help people achieve consistency in implementing their goals and targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scotiabank.com/ca/en/personal/programs-services/bank-the-rest-personal-savings-program.html&quot;&gt;Scotiabank’s Bank The Rest Program&lt;/a&gt;, automatic paycheck deposit to savings account, pre-authorized contributions for investments, robo-advisors, spending tracking apps and tax software management, are just some examples of ways you can automate your financial life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will automation bring you the most optimal financial result? Theoretically, not always, especially since some of these automation technologies have a cost. However it definitely does help alleviate the taxing mental energy you would have otherwise required to invest in. And as human beings we are neither fully rational or have infinite capacity and resources to always consistently reach the optimal result. Worse, we are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investmentnews.com/fundamentals-of-behavioral-finance-overconfidence-bias-197276&quot;&gt;prone to be overconfident in our own ability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why not let technology help you achieve speed, greater peace of mind and consistency? Those non-financial gains may very well outweigh whatever financial optimization you were trying to do, especially when you take into account what you should prioritize&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;Final words&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acronym &lt;strong&gt;EUPHORIA&lt;/strong&gt; was created in the mindset and context of financial well-being. But I think it has room to be amended for other contexts. Additionally it doesn’t go through the gritty details and leaves out other important considerations. Some points may need to be adapted for your specific case (most easily visible in “&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;” if you don’t have a partner). But in general I believe it is a good and applicable recipe for financial (or other) well-being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been reading this far in, thank you for your time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="finance" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">It has been a while since my latest blog post and this time I’m writing out of whimsical inspiration. I was browsing the PersonalFinanceCanada sub-Reddit and saw a question about being mindful of lifestyle creep. If you don’t know what lifestyle creep is, it basically means ever increasingly extravagant lifestyle, usually marked with fancier material posessions, dinners or experiences. It usually coincides with increases in salary, relocation or a momentous life event (such as a financial windfall).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Matters, Given You</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/01/05/what-matters-given-you" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Matters, Given You" /><published>2021-01-05T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/01/05/what-matters-given-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2021/01/05/what-matters-given-you">&lt;p&gt;Happy new year 2021! I hope you, the reader, had the opportunity to take the time to unwind at the end of the year and embrace the new year to come. Usually at this time people would establish some kind of new year resolution (though I don’t usually do it myself). But after coming from such a turbulent year, at the very least for the majority of people, you might not be up for creating a new year resolution. Or perhaps you may be in a situation where your life and your surroundings is in such dissonance that you can’t make heads or tails of your life, let alone a new resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were to be honest, the transition between the past year to the new year is simply a second difference. Within one second there isn’t much that necessarily change. Rather than a new year, shouldn’t it instead be called a continuing year? Well either way, the point is that things don’t just rapidly change in a split second. Considering the situation with COVID-19, though there are hopeful sentiments on vaccine rollout, there is a real chance that the next few months in the year would feel very similar to last year. Yet, things continuously change, especially in the macro levels of our life and surroundings. In the sea of changes (and undoubtedly uncertainty), it gets difficult to pinpoint any kind of target we can aim for. In this blog post I would like to talk about a framework to help you think about meaningful targets in your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-digression-to-probability&quot;&gt;A digression to probability&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When working with probabilities you may have come across these set of symbols: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X|Y)&lt;/code&gt; (or some variant of it). In more plain English it reads out as &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;the probability of X happening given that event Y happened&lt;/code&gt;. For example, we can ask what is the probability that the cake I am baking is going to turn out well (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;X&lt;/code&gt;) given that I have followed the recipe to a tee (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt;), compared to simply asking what is the probability that the cake is going to turn out well (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X)&lt;/code&gt; only).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathemathically, the calculation for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X|Y)&lt;/code&gt; are vastly different and while there are more variables involved in the latter it can actually be easier to answer the latter than the former. Why is that so? Under the conditional probability you would be assuming that some event &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; has happened, constraining a part of the myriad possibilities of events that can occur to a single possibility. Meanwhile when you try to answer &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X)&lt;/code&gt; you have to take into account those other possibilities &lt;strong&gt;AND&lt;/strong&gt; also the possibilities of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But how does this relate to me you ask?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s replace &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;X&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;something&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; with you. From &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P(X|Y)&lt;/code&gt; we get &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?(something|you)&lt;/code&gt;, which now says &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;does this something matter given you&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conditional-situation-unconditional-you&quot;&gt;Conditional situation, unconditional you&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behavioural economist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Thaler&quot;&gt;Richard Thaler&lt;/a&gt; has said in his works that &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;People are not dumb. The world is hard&lt;/code&gt;. I think we do tend to agree that yes the world can be hard and that we don’t want to be called dumb. More so than us being dumb, it certainly does feel like the world can be tremendously difficult to cope with, example: &lt;em&gt;COVID-19&lt;/em&gt;. In a world where change is constant, it can get dizzyingly confusing and erratic to make sense of anything, let alone goals and targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my recent &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life&quot;&gt;post about budgeting&lt;/a&gt; I talked a bit identifying goals that are important for you. Part of the steps required to identify the important goals in your life would be to ask yourself whether those goals matter. Of course, the question of what matters to you does not stop at goals either. But the world’s hard, we’ve agreed on that, and there are so many competing viewpoints and opinions out there. And I haven’t even mentioned social media, you know that place where you can easily fall in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/ca/articles/201711/the-comparison-trap&quot;&gt;trap of comparisons&lt;/a&gt; against people you don’t even know across the whole world. Against all these variables, how do you come to decide what matters to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back to the transformed symbols I mentioned before, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?(something|you)&lt;/code&gt;. Reading it in plain English we have “does this thing matter, given you”. Just like how calculating conditional probability let us assume certain variables, let’s start by constraining from the one variable that stays relatively well known - you. Yes you. Wouldn’t it be easier to think about the things that matter when we only consider it from our personal perspective, history, experience, knowledge, plans, past, situation etc. I’m not saying that it would be easy (look at all those parts about you I just quickly mentioned!), but it does seem easier to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the world may move and change and be dizzyingly bizarre, the you that lives life second by second is likely to be majorly similar from each moment to moment, just like how the previous year transitions to the new year in a single second. Unconditionally you will remain similar to from before, and that non-conditionality I think will greatly help you to consider what truly matters for you. So my suggestion is to start thinking in the form of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?(something|you)&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;matters?(something)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I call this the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;what matters, given you&lt;/code&gt; framework of thinking&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;focusing-on-the-simplicity&quot;&gt;Focusing on the simplicity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a reason why I used conditional probability as my analogy. I want to emphasize on the words &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;given you&lt;/code&gt;, which is intentionally used as a replacement for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;for you&lt;/code&gt;. The world’s complex, difficult, dynamic, rich and filled with other beings (human or otherwise). Obviously, the things that truly matter in the world and life are not just things that are related to you. In fact, some of those things that matter may be in complete contrast to what you may consider as important. But that’s why I framed the framework as I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought of the framework as a way to &lt;strong&gt;simplify the process of understanding what truly matters in life&lt;/strong&gt;. I propose that we can start thinking about the things that matter in our life by identifying the thing that we are most likely to know best and least varied, ourselves. In truth, there will and should be further variables taken into account, but those are for the next steps. The things that matter will not just be decided by you, but it would definitely involve you. &lt;strong&gt;It is not ourselves that is the focus, but we can use ourselves as a starting point&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I have been thinking a lot about my own goals in life, which led me to ask several times the things that matter in my life. I realize, even more so than any previous time of my life, that such an endeavour is incredibly difficult. It also doesn’t help that society and our culture imposes certain expectations, overt or otherwise, on us. But in an effort to regain some sense of control over my thoughts and opinions, I have started to try tackling these large and grand questions in more simple building blocks. The framework of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;what matters, given you&lt;/code&gt; is one of them that I have recently identified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for having read this blog post, I hope it has served useful for you. Happy new year.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="framework" /><category term="new year" /><category term="probability" /><summary type="html">Happy new year 2021! I hope you, the reader, had the opportunity to take the time to unwind at the end of the year and embrace the new year to come. Usually at this time people would establish some kind of new year resolution (though I don’t usually do it myself). But after coming from such a turbulent year, at the very least for the majority of people, you might not be up for creating a new year resolution. Or perhaps you may be in a situation where your life and your surroundings is in such dissonance that you can’t make heads or tails of your life, let alone a new resolution.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Budgeting in Life</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Budgeting in Life" /><published>2020-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/20/budgeting-in-life">&lt;p&gt;This year I’ve taken up more interest in personal finance, and starting to really think about longer term goals (5 to 10 years ahead for example) and thinking about the costs those goals would entail. As I look more into discovering my goals and how money interplays with it I’ve taken up budgeting much more seriously, and to some people’s surprise deriving joy out of it. I honestly think the few things that I’ve come to realize and went through is of such importance to me now that I truly believe it would hold importance for a great number of people too. So in this blog post I would like to talk about budgeting, and my thinking behind it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-budget&quot;&gt;What is a budget?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to search for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?client=firefox-b-d&amp;amp;q=what+is+a+budget&quot;&gt;“what is a budget?” on Google&lt;/a&gt; you would get a number of definitions covering a range of ideas but they largely ring the same ideas: financial planning, income and expense estimation, planning to spend your money etc. My personal take is that &lt;strong&gt;budgeting is specifically the art and process of allocating resources towards a goal&lt;/strong&gt;. In general the resources you can allocate through a budget can be anything, from something as concret as material resources to more abstract concepts such as time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how I did not add in an element of time to my description of a budget and this is deliberate. While budgeting is often cited as a way to manage money (and in general resources) in the future, in actual fact the act of managing future money requires management of money in the now. Additionally, the now is intricately linked to events and actions in the past. The baseline process can be visualized as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the goal in the future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan the required resources for the goal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the gaps, if any, between required and present situation. Start to act or plan to act based identified gaps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If actions can’t be taken, reflect on why and how it became to be so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Re-adjust future goal or consider to allocate further resources to achieve the goal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a cyclical and continuous process of estimation, towards the future, and reflection, of the past implemented in the present. As the needs and circumstances are identified it becomes more manageable to start implementing and taking the appropriate actions to realize the desired goal. Sometimes of course you may need to re-adjust the goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-purpose-of-allocation&quot;&gt;The purpose of allocation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The allocation of resources is simply one smaller part of budgeting, while the goal of budgeting is an even larger aspect. Without the goal, the allocation of resources would be meaningless. However, rather than focus on &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; the goal is, I would like to focus on &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; the goal is established. I think it is extremely important to start from your values when creating goals. Aligning your goals to your values, the things that you care deep down in your heart and mind, I think is extremely important. Not all goals should be of equal value to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, most people’s goal I would reckon is to grow up the career ladder which might not necessarily align with one’s values. Even though going up the career ladder may bring you greater income, something I’m sure many people will be happy to have, it may mean it comes with higher amounts of responsibility which leads to less family time. If family time is something of value to you, I would definitely say it would be prudent to reassess your goal. Is it something that you really want? It is a tremendous shame to see someone reach the goal that they have set, only to realize that the goal that they made for themselves were never the right destination to head towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not all goals should be of equal importance to you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting yourself with the question: “what is of value to me?” I believe will help you start with the right direction. Like a compass that helps ascertain the direction one is facing, your values will do the same for your goals. Once the direction is established, the range of destinations to get to will be clearer, and a clearer destination helps you to draw out the path to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-freedom-of-a-budget&quot;&gt;The freedom of a budget&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my friend dislikes budgeting, particularly with regards to budgeting as a personal financial practice. Their reason is that budgeting feels stifling, they dislikes the fact that when you financially budget you put restraints on what and how much you can spend. I think this line of thinking is not uncommon. But I would like to persuade whoever thinks so. Remember that in how I define budgeting I specifically use the word &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;allocation&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;goal&lt;/code&gt;. The allocation of resources towards the accomplishment of a goal is not a restriction, on the contrary it is a deliberate conscious &lt;strong&gt;permission&lt;/strong&gt; made by you so that you can put certain resources towards the goal. When you think of it this way, budgeting becomes the anti-thesis of a tool of restriction and instead it is a tool of &lt;strong&gt;freedom&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give a simple example. One of my goals is simply that I would like to be entertained a.k.a I don’t want to be bored. I identified that the kinds of entertainment that I like requires paying a certain price. I ask myself - “well me, how much do I want to be entertained?” of which I answer with “I think $50 of this kind of entertainment should keep me reasonably entertained and I know that I am able to”. So I set up a financial budget of $50 per month for entertainment. Now, every month I am free to use that allocated $50 budget for my entertainment purposes however I want. When I do so, I don’t need to feel guilty or bad or worried or panic or anything that you might associate spending money frivolously with - because I have allowed myself to spend that much. If I do feel guilty, for whatever reason, that should be a signal that the budget that I have set was not appropriate for my values, which in turn is not appropriate for my goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that by allocating only $50 in my example above a restriction is in place, set by myself, that I shouldn’t use more than $50 in a single month. Still, this restriction is one that I was freely able to make after considering my goals and values along with my current situation. The explicit process of identifying my goals and values and my current situation frees me up to make a conscious and informed decision that aligns both with the present situation and the future. Moreover, now you have freed up the rest of your resources for other goals that you want to strive for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;taking-budgeting-forward&quot;&gt;Taking budgeting forward&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year has been quite an overhaul on my approach towards budgeting. Before this year though I have target goals, I never enacted a budget as a way to help realize those goals in actuality. Moreover, I did not consider whether how I use my resources, predominantly time and money, aligns with not only my goals but also more importantly my values. Now that I have taken budgeting more seriously and consider how its implications I don’t see myself letting it go. If you read this far, I truly thank you for your time and allowing yourself to read this blog post. I hope it was a good use of your time resource and helped you achieve your goals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="finance" /><category term="planning" /><category term="goals and values" /><summary type="html">This year I’ve taken up more interest in personal finance, and starting to really think about longer term goals (5 to 10 years ahead for example) and thinking about the costs those goals would entail. As I look more into discovering my goals and how money interplays with it I’ve taken up budgeting much more seriously, and to some people’s surprise deriving joy out of it. I honestly think the few things that I’ve come to realize and went through is of such importance to me now that I truly believe it would hold importance for a great number of people too. So in this blog post I would like to talk about budgeting, and my thinking behind it</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Job Search In A Pandemic, Part 1</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/02/job-search-in-pandemic-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Job Search In A Pandemic, Part 1" /><published>2020-12-02T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/02/job-search-in-pandemic-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/12/02/job-search-in-pandemic-1">&lt;p&gt;Recently I have just transitioned to a new job position (2 months ago from the date of this post) and the experience of the search served to be a valuable feedback for me. Now job search is not something I look forward to and doing it in a pandemic does not make me more enthusiastic. But due to personal reasons my decision to move to a new job was already set in stone pandemic or otherwise. I am sure I am not the only one that have been doing job searches during these hard times, so I feel my experience may bring some value to those that want to or still are job searching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;background-and-timeline&quot;&gt;Background and timeline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For background I was applying software/data engineering jobs in Toronto, Canada when I was still in Vancouver, Canada. I finished my Masters program on early April and I was targeting for a job position by end of August, which is when I planned to move to Toronto. During my job search I was working as a software engineer for a company that knows about my moving plans. Due to situation I was mostly mass applying to all kinds of software engineering jobs, though my specialty and expertise lies in backend engineering. Here is my job search timeline:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started applying for jobs mid April to early May and then stopped because of a combination of a lack of motivation, jobs that match my preferences and feeling that it was a bit too far from August.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restarted looking for jobs early June, this continued up to the third week of August. Applied almost daily, 1 to 3 applications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By early july only a handful (around 5) of recruiters/companies have contacted me back. Phone call interviews did not go well. Decided to introspect what kind of jobs I really want and the value I can bring forth as an engineer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In late July got a phone call interview for a node.js developer position. Flunked that one, used it as an opportunity to learn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got a phone interview for my current company in early August, and managed to get past. Interview with management a week after, used the time to read up on company further and studied several materials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Passed interview with management and recruiter was able to put me for the technical interview with the team on the next day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical interview went well, but with some hiccups. Ended with an offer that I took&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this blog post will be structured following the timeline I laid out above as each one has a different story to tell. Since it’s quite long I will break the blog post to two parts. Link for the second part will be added on later&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;timeline-1&quot;&gt;Timeline #1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In mid April I was just finishing up my masters studies. Not wanting to waste time I immediately started to look for job openings. I decided to change some of the formatting of my resume to what I think is cleaner and better aligned to my goal of finding a software engineering job. I primarily used Indeed and LinkedIn for my job search and my searches were honed in to a full time job for software/data engineering positions. I’ve never really worked on a conctractual basis so I wasn’t sure if I would like that, and with the pandemic going on I wanted to find something that would be long lasting for a sense of security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t much that happened during this period. I immediately noticed that many job positions were looking for more of a full-stack engineer and I really wanted to focus on backend. But since I do have a bit of frontend understanding (nothing modern or advanced) I soon decided to just apply to those that demanded full-stack capabilities, and even some that are purely frontend. Surely it is better to try and apply rather than not at all (right?). Of course, simply increasing the breadth of my applications did not mean it generated any positive results. Most of the applications I made were not receiving any replies, and if they were replied it was a rejection. Some of the reasons I came up for myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The employers weren’t interested in my application (this is likely the case for various reasons)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was quite open in stating that I was looking for a job starting at the soonest on August/September and perhaps it didn’t fit with the employers timeframe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some wild theory that companies weren’t actually looking to hire but just scouting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I never really know the reason, it did leave me feeling a bit dejected. Nearing May, I got a phone call from the employer that I worked for during my co-op  wondering if I can come to help them on their projects. I took the offer and became busy with work and left job search on the side thinking that it may be better to try and apply another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;timeline-2&quot;&gt;Timeline #2&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May most of my time was taken up by work and just spending my off-time relaxing by picking up some Switch games that I have neglected. When June arrived I noticed that I haven’t been looking for jobs ever since I stopped. There is only 3 months left until I move to Toronto and that felt too close comfort. It’s actually a bit funny thinking back on how a month’s difference makes my perception of time availability turn 180 degrees, from “I have time” to “I don’t have time”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to improve from my previous attempts at applications I decided to look back to my resume and cover letter once more. Some of the things that I did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I noticed some inconsistencies in formatting and some grammatical improvements to be made in my resume&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I put more emphasis on the job experiences that I wanted to highlight and be proud of by reordering them and using active words&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I created several copies of my resume, only differing in the job title that I wanted to present myself as depending on the application&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I decided to create a standard cover letter resume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would think that one of the things that I would have done was to have a connection review my resume in the list above, but as you there is no mention of it. Why? The reason is simple, I was too afraid to ask it to be critiqued by another set of eyes. Honestly, I should have sought someone to critique it for me, but I was simply too scared at the thought of being shot down, getting told that what I have won’t impress anyone and overall deflating my confidence and spirit. Deep down I know I have some issues with imposter syndrome, and honestly sometimes I do believe that I am incapable. Some time in the future I would probably write another blog post about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;timeline-3&quot;&gt;Timeline #3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job search did not go well. The number of applications that resulted into responses can be counted on one hand, while in total I probably applied to at least 50 applications (1 - 3 applications per day, at least 5 days per week). The ratio of “success”, success here simply getting a reply, is less than 1-to-10, yikes. Furthermore, I was sure not able to impress recruiters in my phone interviews. At some moments I did think that maybe it was all because of COVID19 and the job search climate. But I decided that even if that was the case, &lt;strong&gt;it was something that I can’t control&lt;/strong&gt;. No matter how much I groan, my groaning would not lead to the outcome I desire, getting a job. So I further expanded my effort to improve my application process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I challenged myself to answer the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What kind of job I really want? Does industry matter?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What responsibilities would I best be able to serve in? What technologies that I know that can benefit the company I apply to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answering the two questions above I decided to stop applying to frontend-heavy jobs. I would still apply to a full stack positions, but mostly those that are more backend oriented. While this is doubling down on a specific engineering area, it is really where I want to be and where I feel I can contribute best as an employee. With that in mind I reviewed my resume and cover letter once more to change how I present myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most extensive work experience were with messaging/event-driven and data streaming oriented systems which coincidentally I enjoyed and was partly the reason to why I took a masters program. Therefore I made those experiences my main highlight in both my resume and cover letter. There isn’t many applications that directly mention such systems, but I wanted to put myself forward not as an all-rounder programmer that has no specialty. I wanted to be seen as someone that has a specialty but also possessing a broad range of skills. The next major experience that I highlight is designing and building REST APIs, which at least gets mentioned a lot in job postings. Lastly, I made sure to put myself as a developer that cares for quality in my cover letter by putting some emphasis on TDD and other engineering principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the highlight of this timeline must be this: &lt;strong&gt;I started blogging and putting time for personal projects&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is actually no coincidence that I started blogging more from beginning of July. My lack of progress in job search led me to find other avenues I can make progress in. Blogging was one of those avenues I wanted to invest myself more in, and also a relatively easy way to gain a sense of progress. For the same reason, I also started to do more programming in my own free time. While it isn’t the progress that I need, I felt it was tremendously helpful to gain a sense of momentum in life and also combating my imposter syndrome. I needed to not just feel, but know and see that I am capable of doing something I can take pride and ownership in. Had I not decided to start blog more or code on the side, I absolutely believe that it would have been much harder for me to push myself forward and continue job search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;to-be-continued&quot;&gt;To be continued&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post has gotten quite long already and I don’t want to bore you to death with my life story. So feel free to close off the tab now, I will post the next part in the future. If you managed to read up to here, honestly thank you for reading the diary entries of a man on the internet. See you in the next part.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="reflection" /><category term="jobs" /><category term="software engineering" /><summary type="html">Recently I have just transitioned to a new job position (2 months ago from the date of this post) and the experience of the search served to be a valuable feedback for me. Now job search is not something I look forward to and doing it in a pandemic does not make me more enthusiastic. But due to personal reasons my decision to move to a new job was already set in stone pandemic or otherwise. I am sure I am not the only one that have been doing job searches during these hard times, so I feel my experience may bring some value to those that want to or still are job searching.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RIL - Financial Investing in the Market</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/09/03/learning-financial-investment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RIL - Financial Investing in the Market" /><published>2020-09-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/09/03/learning-financial-investment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/09/03/learning-financial-investment">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/56b1a53/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5760x3840+0+0/resize/840x560!/quality/90/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F82%2F78%2Fbaeb7fd7452ca0b59b92175c0d92%2Faptopix-financial-markets-wall-street-11829.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Poor man in a stock market exchange seems to be in pain, while I am writing a blog about my own journey with less pain&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past few months I have been dipping my feet to some financial investment vehicles. I primarily invest in broad based market indices, with certain product tilts that I’ve chosen to be fit for myself. The point of this post is not to suggestany particular investment products or vehicles, but instead to share what I’ve personally learned as an individual as I continue to invest and re-think my own financial position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-i-invest&quot;&gt;Why I Invest&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going further to what I have learnt, giving a backstory would be beneficial to see where I am coming from. Currently my main reason for investing is for retirement. Now I’m pretty far away from any thoughts of wanting to retire or close to the expected retirement age which is 65 in Canada, 39 years away from the time of this writing. So you might ask if retirement is really something that I should be considering about, so here’s my pitch to why I think its an appropriate time for me to start considering it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/t1/tbl1/en/tv.action?pid=1310013401&quot;&gt;Statistics Canada&lt;/a&gt;, the life expectancy for a male of my age is around 78. Considering that I’m living in a pretty well-off country with social and health support I’ll assume that I can almost be assured to live to the age of 60. If I do manage to get to age 60, my life expectancy would be around 80 years old (and in general my life expectancy would increase as I continue to age). Now assume that I might want to have an early retirement at age 60, which is not uncommon to do, with the expectation that I will not have any income stream during my retirement. Additionally, say I want to have a spending power of 20k every year, for the next 20 years, then that means that I need to have 400k set aside. If I manage to save 1k for every month up to the year of my retirement, I would manage to save 408k, just barely meeting the 400k threshold. But this situation oversimplifies things as I haven’t calculated emergency spending, sickness, large payments such as buying assets, mortgage, pension income, income increase (or decrease) and many more. Suffice to say however, this quick calculation shows that relying on income and saving habits alone may mean that I may very well be short of my retirement income goal, and may mean less than desirable retirement days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lessons-i-learnt&quot;&gt;Lessons I Learnt&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve explained and hopefully convinced you why starting to plan for retirement as early as now is reasonable, I want to go over the lessons that I’ve learned. There are three categories: goal setting and planning, rationality and expectation, humility&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goal-setting-and-planning&quot;&gt;Goal Setting And Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I approached investing as another source of income and a general way for me to get money. It is not wrong that I can get income, or at least appreciation of my capital, through investing, but over time I realized that having this generic hope of getting more money didn’t help me. It didn’t help me because I didn’t have anything in particular that I was trying to achieve, and while getting more income and money is good, I didn’t necessarily feel driven by it because I felt that I can get by with what I have without investing. It is only after I laid out what I want (the goal), and start to look at how I can achieve it (the planning), that I felt financial investing started to be more interesting and something I want to take seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goal setting and planning is not constrained to investments and financial activities of course, but financial health and planning can certainly help normalize the habit because it is often related to a familiar and quantifiable form which is money. Setting goals make, and sub-goals, makes even a long-term goal such as retirement more mentally acessible and approachable, particularly when paired with clear quantifiable metrics. It has also helped me in envisioning the time horizon of my activities (in this case my investment activities), which helps me to assess the decisions that I make and whether they are in line with what is demanded of my goal. If I know I need to save 1k every month to reach my minimum desired retirement days, then saving 500 for a month is a clear overstep of what is needed to achieve my goals. At the same time, knowing that I have a long time horizon for my goal means that I am learning to expect and include in my planning unexpected events, which helps me to further prepare in the face of such events and to develop flexible plans around such potentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rationality-and-expectation&quot;&gt;Rationality and Expectation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the resources I found and have been using frequently for my financial literacy and assessment is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/RATIONALREMINDER&quot;&gt;The Rational Reminder Podcast&lt;/a&gt;. The channel goes over a lot of decision making and thinking processes that aim to be as rational as possible (with acknowledgement that we are emotional and social beings). This way of thinking has really shaped my understanding of financial well-being as being founded upon sound and rational decisions &lt;em&gt;WITH&lt;/em&gt; appropriate expectations. What do I mean here by appropriate expectations? Well one simple example is packaged in the common saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;past performance is not guarantee of future performance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s simply a statement that the past is not a perfect indicator of the future, which in hindsight is something that is easily agreeable. The problem is that a lot of the times our decision are heavily biased towards our past experiences, sidelining the evidences in front of us of the present situation. When investing it can be easy to fall in the trap of doubling down on a well performing asset in the past, thinking that its good performance will continue unabated. Or perhaps we would think we will be able to &lt;em&gt;pull out&lt;/em&gt; from our choice when things look sour, something extremely difficult to do correctly for the plain reason that we do not have a perfect oracle into the future, and our insight can be influenced by non-evidence based reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related to goal setting and planning, I’m continuously learning to find reasonable expectations for my investments according to my goal. Since my goal is for the long-term I am setting up my investment positions to reflect that. Keeping this in mind has helped me to deal with the volatility shocks of the market. I cannot expect that my investment will continuously be increasing in value with such a long timespan, knowing that the market &lt;em&gt;IS&lt;/em&gt; volatile and &lt;em&gt;MUST&lt;/em&gt; be so in order to be profitable. It would be irrational of me to think otherwise, and likewise thus irrational of me to react as if it is unexpected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, acknowledgement that there are elements out of my control in the performance of my investments is helping me to isolate the reasons for the results of my decisions. Often we think good results is an indicator of good decisions, which is not necessarily true, especially in an environment where there is little that you can do to affect the results such as the market. Therefore it has been a learning point for me to assess the quality of my decisions according to what is accessible, knowledge and affect-wise, to me. This certainly helps in moderating both my expectations and having a more appropriate reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;humility&quot;&gt;Humility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finance is definitely not my forte. When dealing with the market there are additional elements of social expectations, economics, politics, and many more, none of which are my forte. Trying to understand basic terminologies and concepts took me hours and some late night sleeps. I enjoyed them for sure, but it’s not easy, plus I’m definitely still far from being financially literate, at least to the degree that I want. Yet I still decide to invest into the market, because I (optimistically perhaps) believe that the information that I have found and learned has come from well-meaning and knowledgeable experts and that as a whole the market will perform adequately to grow its value. Combined with lessons learnt in adopting more rational expectations, I acknowledge that I am riding on the shoulders of giants. It is a humbling feeling knowing that there is so much more for me to know, and that I shouldn’t expect results are necessarily driven by my abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;finishing-words&quot;&gt;Finishing Words&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every lesson I’ve shared here has been eye-opening and I take them fully to heart. Though I spent the least in talking about it, the lesson of humility is likely the most important for me. I expect the lessons I’ve taken so far will be applicable in all aspects of my life and I am certainly looking forward to learn, and share, further lessons in my financial journey.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="life" /><category term="finance" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">Poor man in a stock market exchange seems to be in pain, while I am writing a blog about my own journey with less pain</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RIL - Request Body Buffering With Spring’s RestTemplate</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/17/spring-resttemplate-request-body-buffering" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RIL - Request Body Buffering With Spring’s RestTemplate" /><published>2020-08-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/17/spring-resttemplate-request-body-buffering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/17/spring-resttemplate-request-body-buffering">&lt;h1 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using the Java Spring framework for my work for a while now. I started learning the Spring framework while building a REST API application which had to connect to other remote services through their own REST API interface. While the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spring.io/spring/docs/current/spring-framework-reference/web.html#webmvc-client&quot;&gt;Spring RestTemplate&lt;/a&gt; is currently only in maintenance mode and expected to be deprecated completely in the future, it was the first thing that I found for making HTTP requests in the Spring framework. So I just started using it out of practicality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we often want to make log HTTP requests our servers make. One way is to put log statements everywhere we needed to make HTTP calls. One of the alternatives with Spring RestTemplate is to configure a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baeldung.com/spring-resttemplate-logging#logging-body-with-a-resttemplate-interceptor&quot;&gt;logging interceptor&lt;/a&gt;. This way we can configure a global (or several) RestTemplates that have configured logging capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;LoggingInterceptor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;implements&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClientHttpRequestInterceptor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	 
	    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Logger&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;LoggerFactory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getLogger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;LoggingInterceptor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	 
	    &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@Override&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClientHttpResponse&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;intercept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;HttpRequest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;byte&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reqBody&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClientHttpRequestExecution&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	      &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;throws&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;IOException&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;debug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Request body: {}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reqBody&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;StandardCharsets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;UTF_8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClientHttpResponse&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;response&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;execute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reqBody&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;InputStreamReader&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;isr&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;InputStreamReader&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;response&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getBody&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;StandardCharsets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;UTF_8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;BufferedReader&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;isr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	          &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;lines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
	          &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;collect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Collectors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;joining&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;\n&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;debug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Response body: {}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;response&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking from the Baeldung post above, we can see that the signature for the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;intercept&lt;/code&gt; method contains a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;reqBody&lt;/code&gt; parameter of type &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;byte[]&lt;/code&gt;. This means that in order to log the outgoing request body, Spring has to serialize whatever we are sending to a byte array structure in-memory. Depending on the request body that you are sending this can cause memory issues, and perhaps even out of memory errors. Additionally it probably has performance impact to your application, even if a little. So it’s something that may need some considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in my current project I have to relay uploaded files made by clients to another service through its API call. These files will potentially be in gigabyte size range. Still using RestTemplate I realize immediately that the application will run out of memory if I logged using the interceptor above. So I decided to create two kinds of RestTemplate, one that can is configured to log requests automatically and another that doesn’t. Additionally I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spring.io/spring-framework/docs/current/javadoc-api/org/springframework/http/client/HttpComponentsClientHttpRequestFactory.html#setBufferRequestBody-boolean-&quot;&gt;HttpComponentsClientHttpRequestFactory.setBufferRequestBody(false)&lt;/a&gt; to ensure that the application will not buffer the uploaded file that needs to be relayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I was functionally testing the application I kept running to out of memory errors when uploading a 1.5 GB file and no matter what I did I could not fix it. After investigating further it turns out that I didn’t know the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spring.io/spring-boot/docs/current/reference/html/production-ready-features.html&quot;&gt;SpringBoot Actuator&lt;/a&gt; is available in the classpath. One of the things that the Actuator package provides is metric collection of outgoing HTTP clients made by RestTemplates, which is automatically provided if we build our &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/code&gt; through the auto-configured &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplateBuilder&lt;/code&gt; provided by SpringBoot. That is if we created our RestTemplate like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@Bean&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;restTemplate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;RestTemplateBuilder&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;builder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;builder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;build&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then the metric collection capability is automatically configured. And of course the metric collection is done by adding an interceptor, to be precise the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/spring-projects/spring-boot/blob/master/spring-boot-project/spring-boot-actuator/src/main/java/org/springframework/boot/actuate/metrics/web/client/MetricsClientHttpRequestInterceptor.java&quot;&gt;MetricsRestTemplateCustomizer&lt;/a&gt; is used. This interceptor is added to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplateBuilder&lt;/code&gt; I used above to build the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/code&gt;, and therefore all of my requests made with the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/code&gt; that wasn’t configured for logging was actually buffering the request body! No wonder I kept hitting OOM errors…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-fix&quot;&gt;The fix&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well the fix is actually quite simple, I just built the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/code&gt; without the configured &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplateBuilder&lt;/code&gt; provided and everything is fine! Well… in the end I decided to move the application to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spring.io/spring/docs/current/javadoc-api/org/springframework/web/reactive/function/client/WebClient.html&quot;&gt;WebClient&lt;/a&gt; instead. Not only it is the suggested API to use now, thus am building for a future proof application, I would still be able to log requests without having to be forced to buffer the request body. Though if I want to log the request body programmatically, I would still be required to buffer the request body, but that’s a separate issue for the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="technology" /><category term="java" /><category term="spring" /><category term="springboot" /><summary type="html">Background</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Challenging Technology’s Social Free Lunch</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/08/software-free-lunch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Challenging Technology’s Social Free Lunch" /><published>2020-08-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/08/software-free-lunch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/08/software-free-lunch">&lt;p&gt;No, this blog post is not about how many software companies (and I think more and more in general) provide food budgets or cater free lunch or dinner to their workers. The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;free lunch&lt;/code&gt; I mean here is an assumed and taken for granted property that technology has. Particularly a belief in technology as inevitably driving positive social progress and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The belief that technology deterministically drives social progress (and implicitly social good or bad) has a name: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_determinism&quot;&gt;technological determinism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think this view is held explicitly, but I do think at the corporate level there is definitely a sense that progress in technology is almost always contributing imore positively to the social good than negatively. At the very least we get that sense when we see the headlines regarding technology startups (often computer software/hardware related companies) are seen as the next greatest thing. Also how this optimism is priced in to their business valuation, and how they are marketed by the founders themselves when they pitch their companies. Some examples would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/videos/business/2020/02/10/clearview-ai-facial-recognition-orig.cnn-business&quot;&gt;Clearview AI founder asserting that his company is there for better law enforcement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://css.umich.edu/publication/beyond-meats-beyond-burger-life-cycle-assessment-detailed-comparison-between-plant-based&quot;&gt;Beyond Meat sponsoring a study to their product’s environment impact&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-am-i-thinking-about-this-now&quot;&gt;Why am I thinking about this now?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I decided to go to university to study computer science my brother asked me, “why do you want to study computer science?” Back then I did not have any background in computer science, software or programming but I was quite decent in mathematics and I only know roughly that I computer science is related to math. I’ve also been a heavy user of computer throughout my life, so studying in computer science was a bit of a whimsical choice on my part. So I could only answer with “well I think it would be great to help people through software and computers” to which my brother responded with “But why do it through software and computer?” and there was no immediate reason that pops up in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an avid computer user, computers have been tremendously useful and beneficial throughout my life. Never have I really thought of the negative implications of computers and software (aside from my mum yelling at me for using the computer too much). As I become a software engineer I felt my optimism towards technology (software specifically) is further magnified. But we’ve seen how more recent stories, government bodies, social groups, and even the technologists themselves have become more critical towards technology’s social effect. They have started to not buy in to the social free lunch of technologies as much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/codeland&quot;&gt;DEV’s CodeLand 2020&lt;/a&gt;, there was a talk titled &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;The Cost of Data&lt;/code&gt; by Vaidehi Joshi (you can CTRL+F to find it). Vaidehi gave a talk about how running your code on servers will lead to the use of electricity, which is often still generated by non-renewable energy sources. She went further and talked about the clean energy initiatives by top public cloud providers namely Amazon, Google and Microsoft. When the host and Vaidehi interacted after the talk, the host said: “The world of data and the world of climate change seems so far apart”. As software engineers I feel the same way, though I am intimately related to the creation of software and technology, its impact and its relations to the world around me can often elude me. While I focus in creating a software for a particular purpose, and often for what I believe as a good cause and purpose, I do not necessarily know and understand the full scope of the impact of the technology that I have created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mismatch between between an intimacy with creation and intimacy with effect is really the reason why I made this blog post. For this blog post I just want to create a more explicit awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;acknowledging-that-lunch-has-to-be-paid&quot;&gt;Acknowledging that lunch has to be paid&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skepticism towards technology is now more felt by me than ever before. Social progress and good is not so immediate and free anymore and efforts should be taken in order for the lunch to be properly given out. As technologists that create the technology I do think that I and many others are at the unique position to consider the kind of lunch that we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time I acknowledge that it is hard to do. Not just in mental capacity and knowledge, but also in execution. Many of us work for a company or a boss that has set upon us goals and visions that may constrain what we can do. We may not feel that we are at the right place to make these high-level decisions of social impact, which may very well affect the business. Perhaps we feel like speaking out our concerns will jeopardize our job and career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the end of the day someone will need to pay for the lunch. Someone has to put effort into creating a meaningful and desired social effect. I think it would be ludicrous for our stakeholders to bear the implicit costs of the products that we make. Imagine a grocery store that asks you to pay an explicit fee for the potential health complications you may contract from the ingredients they sell! Ludicrous I’d say. While I don’t think that technologists such as me has all the answers, and definitely not going to be the only one to be involved in the process, I do think we need to be more aware of it due to our unique position. Which I hope will translate to a more active participation in the construction of the desired social affects of the technologies that we build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, there’s really no free lunch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="technology" /><category term="society" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">No, this blog post is not about how many software companies (and I think more and more in general) provide food budgets or cater free lunch or dinner to their workers. The free lunch I mean here is an assumed and taken for granted property that technology has. Particularly a belief in technology as inevitably driving positive social progress and change.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The blog has a new logo!</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/26/a-new-logo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The blog has a new logo!" /><published>2020-07-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/26/a-new-logo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/26/a-new-logo">&lt;p&gt;I commissioned a good designer friend of mine for a logo for this site (including a favicon), and I want to outline why the logo looks like the way it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my blog title says, this blog is a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scattering of thoughts&lt;/code&gt;. What does that mean? It means that this blog covers a range of topics and is really a representation of
the scattered thoughts and ideas in my mind. At the same time I made this blog as a way to self-improve and grow, whether it be in writing, blog creation,
self-advertising (though I’m not intending to heavily promote the blog as of the time of this writing) or technical matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence I thought up of a Rubik’s cube that is disentangled and ripped apart by a growing seed. The idea is that the Rubik’s cube is a structured confinement of
my thoughts in a logical form with many, but finite possibilities. By disentangling the Rubik’s cube from its structured form I hope to show the attempt to
“break free” from my current self, expanding my tightly held logics, thoughts, structures and experiences. At the same time it also serves the dual purpose of
the scattering of my thoughts in action. The seed is the seed of growth that enables this destructuring, and its blossom is a symbol of my growth. The animation too,
while entertaining, serves a purpose. Through a cycle of being structured and destructured, I acknowledge that as I grow there will be moments where I will settle
with the new me, and whenever those moments come, I would want to grow again. Hence, repeating the cycle ad infinitum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m truly happy for the work that my friend managed to do. Sadly, there is no attribution link I can direct to for her right now, but I hope to add it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="blog improvement" /><summary type="html">I commissioned a good designer friend of mine for a logo for this site (including a favicon), and I want to outline why the logo looks like the way it is.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Being An Early Mentor</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/13/being-an-early-mentor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being An Early Mentor" /><published>2020-07-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/13/being-an-early-mentor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/13/being-an-early-mentor">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/images/mentorship_post_20200713.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Trust me that this picture of clouds isn't randomly put here&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my career so far as a software engineer I have had 3 opportunities to be a mentor for someone that is more junior than me. Sometimes this junior-senior
status is established not necessarily by the capabilities and skills but more by my length of stay in the company. This was especially true when I worked in
Japan that is known heavily to promote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japantimes.co.jp/opinion/2019/08/24/editorials/reviewing-seniority-based-pay/&quot;&gt;seniority ranking&lt;/a&gt; of some sorts,
implicitly or explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that I have only been professionally in the field for 4 years, with no previous background to software programming before my
undergraduate, is something I find a bit surprising even for myself. I feel blessed to have had the opportunity so early in my career and in this blog post I
go over my experiences and thoughts on my role as a mentor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-first-mentee&quot;&gt;The first mentee&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was asked to mentor a new colleague six months into my first professional full-time career as a software engineer. By standards of total working experience this
colleague was actually more senior than me, but I just so happen to have worked in the company sooner than him. This mentee was also quite adept in his tech
skills, so aside from a few pointers about the team dynamics, projects, system overview I can’t actually remember any specific piece of technical knowledge that I
felt I was able to impart. Actually I remembered several times where I was surprised with what he showed me, for example a specific setup that he had for the
terminal-based text editor Vim. I have no shame in saying that I actually learned some things from my mentee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My relationship with this mentee was more akin to colleague buddies. We were both close in age and was very techno-optimistic (I’m less techno-optimistic now) and
think that technological advancement is always the best. We thought that impediments to technological progress is always bad. We bonded over the frustration of not
being able to use and try out more modern techniques or tools, because management would say its too risky. We would shrug them off as an evil that we needed to live
with and begrudgingly dreaded whenever we had to work with parts of the system that was deemed ancient (even by the really senior members in our team).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, my relationship as a mentor had to end because I was scouted by another team. There is an inherent idea in my head that the success of a mentor is in how much
one can impart their knowledge to the mentee and in this view I would say I had done a poor job as a mentor. But I take solace in thinking that I was a great
and relatable colleague, hopefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-second-mentee&quot;&gt;The second mentee&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit more than a year into my software engineering career I was again given the opportunity to mentor an incoming colleague. This time, my mentee was actually
just freshly started work as a professional software engineer. She also came from a more research oriented background, unlike my first mentee that came from a more
engineering oriented background. It was clear from the get go that as a professional she was very green in terms of software engineering standards and the practical
skills. I didn’t have to teach her to code, but at times I had to assist her in trying to understand one technical choice over the other. I do not know whether I
was actually being an effective mentor, but often my mentee would come to ask me for assistance for her own project. When I had time to spare I would ask how she’s
doing and ask if she needs assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this time my attitude towards code quality was also becoming more bullish. Still coming off from the assumption that technical progress is important, as
important or if not exceeding at times to some business needs, I would at times be hellbent that some technical progress be included into a project. One such
example would be automated testing and basic CI/CD, which we were greatly lacking back then. To the credit of my persistence, and also some heavy silences during
team debates, gradually my team started to adopt some of the ideas that I kept throwing at them. It wasn’t perfect of course, and it wasn’t smooth or complete either,
but it got things going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my code-quality-hellbent-saga I remember some times when I tried to directly impart this knowledge to my mentee, but uneffectively. I would tell her
to revise her code several times, and then may in the end revert some suggestions back. Why you may ask? Well it was because I was also trying to learn the thing
that I was trying to impart to my mentee. I had the drive yes, but I was rough in the edges and was more like a bulldoze trying to make its way through instead
of being more like a worker ant and learning with and encouraging my mentee. I’m sure my team had their frustrations with me too and probably felt confused
at times by my behaviour too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-third-mentee&quot;&gt;The third mentee&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third mentee is more recent. In terms of technical skills this mentee is somewhere in between the first and second mentee, still inexperienced overall but not a
blank slate. This time I have personally grown with regards to my technical skills from my time with my first and second mentee. I’ve refined my thoughts and experience
a bit more and had more time to polish it. I still hold some strong opinions regarding particular positions related to the software craft, but I think I can say
that I am more flexible than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also try to be more accommodating and reasonable for my mentee this time, trying to explain things a bit more slowly and showcasing more examples. However, I do
find myself to sometimes be a bit impatient with my mentee. It might be because of the experience that I had accumulated so far which makes certain things seem
simple and easy for me. So when my mentee is not able to keep up with me I would sometimes say to myself “why can’t he get this quickly?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a recent reminder that I’m not always right (and certainly not great) was when I was helping my mentee for the code design of a feature he was working on. At first
my mentee suggested a very simple solution that would get the job done, but I said it would be too inflexible for future changes and prone to breaking. My mentee
agreed, and tried out my solution, made some unit tests and it seemed fine, until it wasn’t when a more comprehensive integration test was conducted. Turns out I made
incorrect assumptions in my solution, and my mentee’s simpler solution would not have run to the same issue as mine. To be honest it did feel bad that not only was I
wrong but also I led my mentee to an incorrect solution, but am glad that overall I managed to resolve everything together with my mentee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rounding-up-my-experience-so-far&quot;&gt;Rounding up my experience so far&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my mentorship experiences so far here are some things that I have taken away:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is important as a mentor to actually be able to impart the skills that you are mentoring in. Being close colleagues with my first mentee was good, but I could
have been a much more effective mentor and support for my mentee had I had the skills to backup my position&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A mentor is a teacher in knowledge, methods and also in conduct. If a mentee is to learn from a mentor, then a mentor should reflect the correct posture to learning
and be open to the need for growing themselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Related to learning, I learned and am reminded that humility is so important, because we won’t get everything right. We need to learn with humility and open to admit
our mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish things off, there is a proverbial quote I like to say that goes like this (though I’m not sure where of its origins):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Above the sky, there is another sky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will always be someone better than you, and so there is always room for you to improve and grow, even if you are a mentor and role model for someone&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="professional life" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">Trust me that this picture of clouds isn't randomly put here</summary></entry></feed>