<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-17T04:01:12-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">btruhand - scattering of thoughts</title><subtitle>Btruhand's blogging outlet, ranging from technical writeups to social opions</subtitle><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Request Body Buffering With Spring’s RestTemplate</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/17/software-free-lunch-copy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Request Body Buffering With Spring's RestTemplate" /><published>2020-08-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/17/software-free-lunch%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/17/software-free-lunch-copy">&lt;h1 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using the Java Spring framework for my work for a while now. I started learning the Spring framework while building a REST API application which had to connect to other remote services through their own REST API interface. While the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spring.io/spring/docs/current/spring-framework-reference/web.html#webmvc-client&quot;&gt;Spring RestTemplate&lt;/a&gt; is currently only in maintenance mode and expected to be deprecated completely in the future, it was the first thing that I found for making HTTP requests in the Spring framework. So I just started using it out of practicality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we often want to make log HTTP requests our servers make. One way is to put log statements everywhere we needed to make HTTP calls. One of the alternatives with Spring RestTemplate is to configure a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baeldung.com/spring-resttemplate-logging#logging-body-with-a-resttemplate-interceptor&quot;&gt;logging interceptor&lt;/a&gt;. This way we can configure a global (or several) RestTemplates that have configured logging capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;LoggingInterceptor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;implements&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClientHttpRequestInterceptor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	 
	    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Logger&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;LoggerFactory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getLogger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;LoggingInterceptor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	 
	    &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@Override&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClientHttpResponse&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;intercept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;HttpRequest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;byte&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reqBody&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClientHttpRequestExecution&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	      &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;throws&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;IOException&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;debug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Request body: {}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reqBody&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;StandardCharsets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;UTF_8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClientHttpResponse&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;response&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;execute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reqBody&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;InputStreamReader&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;isr&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;InputStreamReader&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;response&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getBody&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;StandardCharsets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;UTF_8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;BufferedReader&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;isr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	          &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;lines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
	          &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;collect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Collectors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;joining&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;\n&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;debug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Response body: {}&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;response&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking from the Baeldung post above, we can see that the signature for the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;intercept&lt;/code&gt; method contains a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;reqBody&lt;/code&gt; parameter of type &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;byte[]&lt;/code&gt;. This means that in order to log the outgoing request body, Spring has to serialize whatever we are sending to a byte array structure in-memory. Depending on the request body that you are sending this can cause memory issues, and perhaps even out of memory errors. Additionally it probably has performance impact to your application, even if a little. So it’s something that may need some considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in my current project I have to relay uploaded files made by clients to another service through its API call. These files will potentially be in gigabyte size range. Still using RestTemplate I realize immediately that the application will run out of memory if I logged using the interceptor above. So I decided to create two kinds of RestTemplate, one that can is configured to log requests automatically and another that doesn’t. Additionally I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spring.io/spring-framework/docs/current/javadoc-api/org/springframework/http/client/HttpComponentsClientHttpRequestFactory.html#setBufferRequestBody-boolean-&quot;&gt;HttpComponentsClientHttpRequestFactory.setBufferRequestBody(false)&lt;/a&gt; to ensure that the application will not buffer the uploaded file that needs to be relayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I was functionally testing the application I kept running to out of memory errors when uploading a 1.5 GB file and no matter what I did I could not fix it. After investigating further it turns out that I didn’t know the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spring.io/spring-boot/docs/current/reference/html/production-ready-features.html&quot;&gt;SpringBoot Actuator&lt;/a&gt; is available in the classpath. One of the things that the Actuator package provides is metric collection of outgoing HTTP clients made by RestTemplates, which is automatically provided if we build our &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/code&gt; through the auto-configured &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplateBuilder&lt;/code&gt; provided by SpringBoot. That is if we created our RestTemplate like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@Bean&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;restTemplate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;RestTemplateBuilder&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;builder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;builder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;build&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then the metric collection capability is automatically configured. And of course the metric collection is done by adding an interceptor, to be precise the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/spring-projects/spring-boot/blob/master/spring-boot-project/spring-boot-actuator/src/main/java/org/springframework/boot/actuate/metrics/web/client/MetricsClientHttpRequestInterceptor.java&quot;&gt;MetricsRestTemplateCustomizer&lt;/a&gt; is used. This interceptor is added to the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplateBuilder&lt;/code&gt; I used above to build the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/code&gt;, and therefore all of my requests made with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/code&gt; that wasn’t configured for logging was actually buffering the request body! No wonder I kept hitting OOM errors…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-fix&quot;&gt;The fix&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well the fix is actually quite simple, I just built the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplate&lt;/code&gt; without the configured &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RestTemplateBuilder&lt;/code&gt; provided and everything is fine! Well… in the end I decided to move the application to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spring.io/spring/docs/current/javadoc-api/org/springframework/web/reactive/function/client/WebClient.html&quot;&gt;WebClient&lt;/a&gt; instead. Not only it is the suggested API to use now, thus am building for a future proof application, I would still be able to log requests without having to be forced to buffer the request body. Though if I want to log the request body programmatically, I would still be required to buffer the request body, but that’s a separate issue for the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Background</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Challenging Technology’s Social Free Lunch</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/08/software-free-lunch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Challenging Technology's Social Free Lunch" /><published>2020-08-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/08/software-free-lunch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/08/08/software-free-lunch">&lt;p&gt;No, this blog post is not about how many software companies (and I think more and more in general) provide food budgets or cater free lunch or dinner to their workers. The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;free lunch&lt;/code&gt; I mean here is an assumed and taken for granted property that technology has. Particularly a belief in technology as inevitably driving positive social progress and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The belief that technology deterministically drives social progress (and implicitly social good or bad) has a name: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technological_determinism&quot;&gt;technological determinism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think this view is held explicitly, but I do think at the corporate level there is definitely a sense that progress in technology is almost always contributing imore positively to the social good than negatively. At the very least we get that sense when we see the headlines regarding technology startups (often computer software/hardware related companies) are seen as the next greatest thing. Also how this optimism is priced in to their business valuation, and how they are marketed by the founders themselves when they pitch their companies. Some examples would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/videos/business/2020/02/10/clearview-ai-facial-recognition-orig.cnn-business&quot;&gt;Clearview AI founder asserting that his company is there for better law enforcement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://css.umich.edu/publication/beyond-meats-beyond-burger-life-cycle-assessment-detailed-comparison-between-plant-based&quot;&gt;Beyond Meat sponsoring a study to their product’s environment impact&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-am-i-thinking-about-this-now&quot;&gt;Why am I thinking about this now?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I decided to go to university to study computer science my brother asked me, “why do you want to study computer science?” Back then I did not have any background in computer science, software or programming but I was quite decent in mathematics and I only know roughly that I computer science is related to math. I’ve also been a heavy user of computer throughout my life, so studying in computer science was a bit of a whimsical choice on my part. So I could only answer with “well I think it would be great to help people through software and computers” to which my brother responded with “But why do it through software and computer?” and there was no immediate reason that pops up in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an avid computer user, computers have been tremendously useful and beneficial throughout my life. Never have I really thought of the negative implications of computers and software (aside from my mum yelling at me for using the computer too much). As I become a software engineer I felt my optimism towards technology (software specifically) is further magnified. But we’ve seen how more recent stories, government bodies, social groups, and even the technologists themselves have become more critical towards technology’s social effect. They have started to not buy in to the social free lunch of technologies as much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/codeland&quot;&gt;DEV’s CodeLand 2020&lt;/a&gt;, there was a talk titled &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;The Cost of Data&lt;/code&gt; by Vaidehi Joshi (you can CTRL+F to find it). Vaidehi gave a talk about how running your code on servers will lead to the use of electricity, which is often still generated by non-renewable energy sources. She went further and talked about the clean energy initiatives by top public cloud providers namely Amazon, Google and Microsoft. When the host and Vaidehi interacted after the talk, the host said: “The world of data and the world of climate change seems so far apart”. As software engineers I feel the same way, though I am intimately related to the creation of software and technology, its impact and its relations to the world around me can often elude me. While I focus in creating a software for a particular purpose, and often for what I believe as a good cause and purpose, I do not necessarily know and understand the full scope of the impact of the technology that I have created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mismatch between between an intimacy with creation and intimacy with effect is really the reason why I made this blog post. For this blog post I just want to create a more explicit awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;acknowledging-that-lunch-has-to-be-paid&quot;&gt;Acknowledging that lunch has to be paid&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skepticism towards technology is now more felt by me than ever before. Social progress and good is not so immediate and free anymore and efforts should be taken in order for the lunch to be properly given out. As technologists that create the technology I do think that I and many others are at the unique position to consider the kind of lunch that we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time I acknowledge that it is hard to do. Not just in mental capacity and knowledge, but also in execution. Many of us work for a company or a boss that has set upon us goals and visions that may constrain what we can do. We may not feel that we are at the right place to make these high-level decisions of social impact, which may very well affect the business. Perhaps we feel like speaking out our concerns will jeopardize our job and career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at the end of the day someone will need to pay for the lunch. Someone has to put effort into creating a meaningful and desired social effect. I think it would be ludicrous for our stakeholders to bear the implicit costs of the products that we make. Imagine a grocery store that asks you to pay an explicit fee for the potential health complications you may contract from the ingredients they sell! Ludicrous I’d say. While I don’t think that technologists such as me has all the answers, and definitely not going to be the only one to be involved in the process, I do think we need to be more aware of it due to our unique position. Which I hope will translate to a more active participation in the construction of the desired social affects of the technologies that we build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, there’s really no free lunch.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">No, this blog post is not about how many software companies (and I think more and more in general) provide food budgets or cater free lunch or dinner to their workers. The free lunch I mean here is an assumed and taken for granted property that technology has. Particularly a belief in technology as inevitably driving positive social progress and change.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The blog has a new logo!</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/26/a-new-logo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The blog has a new logo!" /><published>2020-07-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/26/a-new-logo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/26/a-new-logo">&lt;p&gt;I commissioned a good designer friend of mine for a logo for this site (including a favicon), and I want to outline why the logo looks like the way it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my blog title says, this blog is a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scattering of thoughts&lt;/code&gt;. What does that mean? It means that this blog covers a range of topics and is really a representation of
the scattered thoughts and ideas in my mind. At the same time I made this blog as a way to self-improve and grow, whether it be in writing, blog creation,
self-advertising (though I’m not intending to heavily promote the blog as of the time of this writing) or technical matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence I thought up of a Rubik’s cube that is disentangled and ripped apart by a growing seed. The idea is that the Rubik’s cube is a structured confinement of
my thoughts in a logical form with many, but finite possibilities. By disentangling the Rubik’s cube from its structured form I hope to show the attempt to
“break free” from my current self, expanding my tightly held logics, thoughts, structures and experiences. At the same time it also serves the dual purpose of
the scattering of my thoughts in action. The seed is the seed of growth that enables this destructuring, and its blossom is a symbol of my growth. The animation too,
while entertaining, serves a purpose. Through a cycle of being structured and destructured, I acknowledge that as I grow there will be moments where I will settle
with the new me, and whenever those moments come, I would want to grow again. Hence, repeating the cycle ad infinitum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m truly happy for the work that my friend managed to do. Sadly, there is no attribution link I can direct to for her right now, but I hope to add it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I commissioned a good designer friend of mine for a logo for this site (including a favicon), and I want to outline why the logo looks like the way it is.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Being An Early Mentor</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/13/being-an-early-mentor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being An Early Mentor" /><published>2020-07-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/13/being-an-early-mentor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/13/being-an-early-mentor">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/images/mentorship_post_20200713.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Trust me that this picture of clouds isn't randomly put here&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my career so far as a software engineer I have had 3 opportunities to be a mentor for someone that is more junior than me. Sometimes this junior-senior
status is established not necessarily by the capabilities and skills but more by my length of stay in the company. This was especially true when I worked in
Japan that is known heavily to promote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japantimes.co.jp/opinion/2019/08/24/editorials/reviewing-seniority-based-pay/&quot;&gt;seniority ranking&lt;/a&gt; of some sorts,
implicitly or explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that I have only been professionally in the field for 4 years, with no previous background to software programming before my
undergraduate, is something I find a bit surprising even for myself. I feel blessed to have had the opportunity so early in my career and in this blog post I
go over my experiences and thoughts on my role as a mentor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-first-mentee&quot;&gt;The first mentee&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was asked to mentor a new colleague six months into my first professional full-time career as a software engineer. By standards of total working experience this
colleague was actually more senior than me, but I just so happen to have worked in the company sooner than him. This mentee was also quite adept in his tech
skills, so aside from a few pointers about the team dynamics, projects, system overview I can’t actually remember any specific piece of technical knowledge that I
felt I was able to impart. Actually I remembered several times where I was surprised with what he showed me, for example a specific setup that he had for the
terminal-based text editor Vim. I have no shame in saying that I actually learned some things from my mentee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My relationship with this mentee was more akin to colleague buddies. We were both close in age and was very techno-optimistic (I’m less techno-optimistic now) and
think that technological advancement is always the best. We thought that impediments to technological progress is always bad. We bonded over the frustration of not
being able to use and try out more modern techniques or tools, because management would say its too risky. We would shrug them off as an evil that we needed to live
with and begrudgingly dreaded whenever we had to work with parts of the system that was deemed ancient (even by the really senior members in our team).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, my relationship as a mentor had to end because I was scouted by another team. There is an inherent idea in my head that the success of a mentor is in how much
one can impart their knowledge to the mentee and in this view I would say I had done a poor job as a mentor. But I take solace in thinking that I was a great
and relatable colleague, hopefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-second-mentee&quot;&gt;The second mentee&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit more than a year into my software engineering career I was again given the opportunity to mentor an incoming colleague. This time, my mentee was actually
just freshly started work as a professional software engineer. She also came from a more research oriented background, unlike my first mentee that came from a more
engineering oriented background. It was clear from the get go that as a professional she was very green in terms of software engineering standards and the practical
skills. I didn’t have to teach her to code, but at times I had to assist her in trying to understand one technical choice over the other. I do not know whether I
was actually being an effective mentor, but often my mentee would come to ask me for assistance for her own project. When I had time to spare I would ask how she’s
doing and ask if she needs assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this time my attitude towards code quality was also becoming more bullish. Still coming off from the assumption that technical progress is important, as
important or if not exceeding at times to some business needs, I would at times be hellbent that some technical progress be included into a project. One such
example would be automated testing and basic CI/CD, which we were greatly lacking back then. To the credit of my persistence, and also some heavy silences during
team debates, gradually my team started to adopt some of the ideas that I kept throwing at them. It wasn’t perfect of course, and it wasn’t smooth or complete either,
but it got things going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my code-quality-hellbent-saga I remember some times when I tried to directly impart this knowledge to my mentee, but uneffectively. I would tell her
to revise her code several times, and then may in the end revert some suggestions back. Why you may ask? Well it was because I was also trying to learn the thing
that I was trying to impart to my mentee. I had the drive yes, but I was rough in the edges and was more like a bulldoze trying to make its way through instead
of being more like a worker ant and learning with and encouraging my mentee. I’m sure my team had their frustrations with me too and probably felt confused
at times by my behaviour too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-third-mentee&quot;&gt;The third mentee&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third mentee is more recent. In terms of technical skills this mentee is somewhere in between the first and second mentee, still inexperienced overall but not a
blank slate. This time I have personally grown with regards to my technical skills from my time with my first and second mentee. I’ve refined my thoughts and experience
a bit more and had more time to polish it. I still hold some strong opinions regarding particular positions related to the software craft, but I think I can say
that I am more flexible than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also try to be more accommodating and reasonable for my mentee this time, trying to explain things a bit more slowly and showcasing more examples. However, I do
find myself to sometimes be a bit impatient with my mentee. It might be because of the experience that I had accumulated so far which makes certain things seem
simple and easy for me. So when my mentee is not able to keep up with me I would sometimes say to myself “why can’t he get this quickly?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a recent reminder that I’m not always right (and certainly not great) was when I was helping my mentee for the code design of a feature he was working on. At first
my mentee suggested a very simple solution that would get the job done, but I said it would be too inflexible for future changes and prone to breaking. My mentee
agreed, and tried out my solution, made some unit tests and it seemed fine, until it wasn’t when a more comprehensive integration test was conducted. Turns out I made
incorrect assumptions in my solution, and my mentee’s simpler solution would not have run to the same issue as mine. To be honest it did feel bad that not only was I
wrong but also I led my mentee to an incorrect solution, but am glad that overall I managed to resolve everything together with my mentee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rounding-up-my-experience-so-far&quot;&gt;Rounding up my experience so far&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my mentorship experiences so far here are some things that I have taken away:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is important as a mentor to actually be able to impart the skills that you are mentoring in. Being close colleagues with my first mentee was good, but I could
have been a much more effective mentor and support for my mentee had I had the skills to backup my position&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A mentor is a teacher in knowledge, methods and also in conduct. If a mentee is to learn from a mentor, then a mentor should reflect the correct posture to learning
and be open to the need for growing themselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Related to learning, I learned and am reminded that humility is so important, because we won’t get everything right. We need to learn with humility and open to admit
our mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish things off, there is a proverbial quote I like to say that goes like this (though I’m not sure where of its origins):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Above the sky, there is another sky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will always be someone better than you, and so there is always room for you to improve and grow, even if you are a mentor and role model for someone&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Trust me that this picture of clouds isn't randomly put here</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Re-thinking Mocks</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/04/rethinking-mocks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Re-thinking Mocks" /><published>2020-07-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-07-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/04/rethinking-mocks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/07/04/rethinking-mocks">&lt;p&gt;These days I have mainly been using Java for my professional career (roughly I have been working with Java for a year). I also mainly have been using the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.spring.io/spring/docs/current/spring-framework-reference/&quot;&gt;Spring framework&lt;/a&gt; along with its additional libraries at work. One of the things that
I enjoy with Spring is the dependency injection capability that it provides, primarily through the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@Autowired&lt;/code&gt; annotation. This quick and easy way to do dependency
injection is also further compounded in testing benefits as Spring also provides easy and seemless way to obtain these dependencies at test time (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@Import&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@ContextConfiguration&lt;/code&gt; to name a few) makes testing much easier. I also make a good amount of use &lt;a href=&quot;https://site.mockito.org/&quot;&gt;Mockito&lt;/a&gt; which makes my development
life much easier through &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mocks&lt;/code&gt;, and this post is about &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mocks&lt;/code&gt; and my experience and thoughts on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-mocks&quot;&gt;What are mocks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question has been covered in a variety of other posts out there, one of which I found most useful to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/articles/mocksArentStubs.html&quot;&gt;Martin Fowler’s post&lt;/a&gt;. In the words of Martin Fowler himself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mocks use behavior verification, where we instead check to see if the order made the correct calls on the warehouse. We do this check by telling the mock what to expect during setup and asking the mock to verify itself during verification&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of mocking is behaviour verification, which is the ability to assert what has &lt;strong&gt;happened&lt;/strong&gt; during the execution of a test, and not just what the system
under test has produced. Martin Fowler made a clear distinction and emphasis on this part which you can read up on his post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;quick-example&quot;&gt;Quick example&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dependency&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;boolean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shouldDoFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dependency&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;boolean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shouldDoFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;dependency&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dependency&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;shouldDoFunc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shouldDoFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;shouldDoFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;dependency&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;doFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;doFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// do something&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// test code below&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;test_func_whenShouldNotDoFunc_notCallDoFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mock&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;verify&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;never&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;doFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above example is extremely contrived but it just barely shows the use case of mocks. The call to the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;verify&lt;/code&gt; function says that we are trying to verify
that when &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shouldDoFunc = false&lt;/code&gt;, we expect that &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ClassB.doFunc&lt;/code&gt; will not be called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative to using mocks above would be to supply an actual instance of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ClassB&lt;/code&gt; (not mocked) and check against the &lt;em&gt;results&lt;/em&gt; after calling &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ClassA.func&lt;/code&gt;.
Now in the above example no values are being returned from any of the function calls so no returned value can be expected, however often such functions causes
side-effects. Common side-effects include calling some API that causes some change, changing the environment settings, performing DB changes such as updates, changing
the state of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ClassB&lt;/code&gt; and many more. Such side-effects are testable and verifiable (if there are no side-effects performed by the function I question why the function
exists).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-positives-of-mocks&quot;&gt;The positives of mocks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my experience thus far using mocks is that it has been beneficial to create tests. Certain testing may require an expensive setup or verification procedure,
which makes tests run slow but also developed more slowly. An alternative to mocks may include creating fakes or stubs (a separate kind of testing entity), which may
also create additional development effort to make and also may require its own maintenance. Though a great deal of this benefit comes from the fact that many languages
have a well-tested and prevalent mocking library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mocks also makes creating truly &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unit&lt;/code&gt; tests easier, and by unit here I mean tests that only put a single class/object under test. Mocks enable me to put the focus
and attention of tests on the specific unit under test and not have to worry about the other interacting pieces. In the example above, the test is made deliberately
about &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ClassA.func&lt;/code&gt; behaviour when it is in a certain state. In more complex objects under test, this makes some desired fine-grained testing much more approachable
and manageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-negatives-of-mocks&quot;&gt;The negatives of mocks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest drawback using mocking is it requires whitebox testing, in order to verify using mocks we need to know what functions are being called, which essentially
bears down to knowing some level of detail about the implementation of the unit under test. Nowadays I think of this as &lt;em&gt;reflection for testing&lt;/em&gt;. Reflection is the
ability to inspect programming constructs at runtime of some code within the code itself. Often this involves passing in names of functions or fields in the form of
strings to specialized reflection APIs. Since access is made via strings, IDEs won’t help you during refactoring which makes mistakes during changes in the codebase
harder to detect. Thankfully a testing is one of the tools we have to safeguard ourselves against our programming mistakes, until the tests start to fail us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using reflection capabilities requires the programmer to have clear knowledge about what is and isn’t present and bake that knowledge statically into the code and
it is the same case when we use mocks. Now libraries like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Mockito&lt;/code&gt; does enable the use of refactoring through IDE unlike reflection, but mocking doesn’t easily
allow us to change the tests when the dependency calls in the code under test changes. This creates a mismatch between expectation and reality. For example, if in
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ClassA&lt;/code&gt; above we change the call of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;doFunc&lt;/code&gt; to another function &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;doFunc2&lt;/code&gt;, the test would still pass but for very much the wrong reason! The reality is that
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;doFunc&lt;/code&gt; is no longer a dependency call being made, but the test still expects it as a call to be made and it just so happens the test was verifying that no calls
were to be made. The following test would fail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;test_func_whenShouldDoFunc_callDoFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mock&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ClassA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;verify&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;classB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;once&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;doFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but now the test fails for the wrong reason! The test will fail because the test is expecting the wrong thing, not because the unit under test is behaving
incorrectly. This is test maintenance drag. Martin Fowler calls this the coupling of implementation and testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;an-alternative-for-mocking&quot;&gt;An alternative for mocking&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the compelling alternatives to mocking is by supplying functions as parameters to the unit under test instead of whole object dependencies. The ability to pass
functions as parameters is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First-class_function&quot;&gt;First-class function&lt;/a&gt;. Consider this example in pseudo-Javascript&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-javascript highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;funcToTest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;dependentFunction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;some&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;dependentFunction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;test_funcToTest_whenConditionNotMet_doNotCallDependentFunction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// do something to cause condition to not be met&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;counter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;funcToTest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;counter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;counter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;throw&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;TestFailed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passed in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dependentFunction&lt;/code&gt; is simply a function passed as a parameter that is called when some condition is met inside &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;funcToTest&lt;/code&gt;. Notice how in the test we
are also verifying the behaviour of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;funcToTest&lt;/code&gt; under some condition, similar to the example with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ClassA&lt;/code&gt;. In both the test using mocks and first-class function we
see that behaviour is being verified, and this should come as no surprise. We can think of objects as instances of namespaces/groupings for functions (with the ability
to maintain and collect some form of internal state) and so when we pass an object as a dependency it can be seen as passing in a collection of functions. The
difference is that when we use mocks we have to explicitly mention the dependent function we are interested in, while with first-class functions the dependent function
is stipulated in formal syntax (scratching off the fact that it’s possible to call functions without their parameters in Javascript). With mocks tests can fail/pass
for reasons of a mismatch between expectation and reality, with first-class functions that possibility is greatly diminished and if it happens is likely the
programmer’s mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in reality I have not used first-class functions as an alternative to mocks at all. Much the reason is because it is much easier to work with objects and
mocks in Java. Though Java does have lambda functions and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/lang/FunctionalInterface.html&quot;&gt;@FunctionalInterface&lt;/a&gt;
it is not that fluid to create classes and methods that take in first-class functions all the time. But this is surely a technique that I would explore and be more
conscious of in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">These days I have mainly been using Java for my professional career (roughly I have been working with Java for a year). I also mainly have been using the Spring framework along with its additional libraries at work. One of the things that I enjoy with Spring is the dependency injection capability that it provides, primarily through the @Autowired annotation. This quick and easy way to do dependency injection is also further compounded in testing benefits as Spring also provides easy and seemless way to obtain these dependencies at test time (@Import and @ContextConfiguration to name a few) makes testing much easier. I also make a good amount of use Mockito which makes my development life much easier through mocks, and this post is about mocks and my experience and thoughts on them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflecting on racism and recent events</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/06/07/reflecting-on-racism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflecting on racism and recent events" /><published>2020-06-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/06/07/reflecting-on-racism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/06/07/reflecting-on-racism">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-this-post-about&quot;&gt;What is this post about?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the tragic death of George Floyd and the still ongoing protests as of this writing, I have been thinking and
reflecting on the issue of racism. While the issue and protest have been triggered within the North American cultural
context, the angle of my reflection is not restricted to the NA context. Partly because racism isn’t contained within
a particular culture, and also my own lack of understanding of the NA context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-now&quot;&gt;Why now?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m the type to take my time  trying to understand and grasp the subtleties of issues. Making this post is not an assertion
that I have gotten all the details pinned down, on the contrary it is my attempt to just start from somewhere, in my own way.
Some would say that I should have just immediately take some form of action and not be so caught up with how right or wrong
what I do is. I won’t argue with that sentiment&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, just that it’s not how I usually operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the tragedy that befell upon George Floyd, I likely won’t be making a post with this particular theme. Had recent
events not been so widespread, I also think I probably won’t have made a post specifically on this topic either. So the
creation of this post is also a result of being compelled to act due to my ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;have-i-been-subjected-to-racism&quot;&gt;Have I been subjected to racism?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. At least I do not feel that any of the treatments that I have received had been motivated by racism, intentional or not.
Perhaps the closest event to racism would be when I was with my friend speaking our mother tongue language. Apparently at
that time he overheard two people making near us to be making murmuring sounds which he said seemed to be
making an impersonation of our speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;am-i-racist&quot;&gt;Am I racist?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not think of myself as racist, but I doubt any person asked this would respond with an affirmative yes. But I realize
that when talking amongst my close friends that I do make racial remarks of our own group jokingly. I also know that I have
my own explicit racial presumptions. As someone with a bit of tanned color skin I did have my own phase of negatively viewing
my skin color. It was brief, but it was a moment of associating human worth with skin color and an ingredient for developing
racism through the lens of skin color. No one has said that I’m a racist, but that doesn’t mean that I have not been one,
acted as one, or exude the sense that I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;am-i-an-anti-racist&quot;&gt;Am I an anti-racist?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest the word &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;anti-racist&lt;/code&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is a first for me from reading and hearing the various resources over these past few weeks.
With regards to moral values I would say yes I am against anyone to be a target of racism. But I would not say that I have
spoken up against racism, especially not compared to the recent calling to denounce racism and being anti-racist. When
my friend pointed out to me the two people who he thought to be mimicking our speech I told him to let it be and to not
let it bother him too much. I wasn’t sure myself whether the two people were really making a mockery of our speech or not,
but at least reflecting back I should have stood up for my friend more, at least when I was consulting him and his feelings
of discomfort&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-stance-on-racism&quot;&gt;My stance on racism&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then God said, “Let us make mankind in our image …” - Genesis 1:26&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether by divine or natural commonality I believe that there is no difference in the intrinsic value between people of different
races, skin color, social standing and culture. Intrinsically, everyone is equally valuable and should be respected as such.
But in having this stance I sometimes forget the peculiarities surrounding one’s experience, the good and also their hardships.
As we live our lives and subject to our personal AND collective experience, we would pick up unique perceptions and also treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not having felt to have been a subject of racism makes me prone to the thought of dismissing certain identity roles in one’s
experience, including their race. Though, having given further thought to my own experiences and experiences, I would not
retract my foundational belief of the intrinsic worth of people. This is a point of growth that I would hope to continue further
as I continue life and interact with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;thoughts-on-violence-in-recent-protests&quot;&gt;Thoughts on violence in recent protests&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not one that would like to resort to violence. I can imagine myself being violent, I can imagine myself returning payback
violently to others, but I can’t imagine myself actually doing it. When I saw the violent death of George Floyd, I became
teary-eyed, and when I took the time to replay it over and over in video and in mind, I wept. But my tears are certainly different
from the tears of the black community who have experienced such physical abuse directly. My tears flowed because it was heart-wrenching
and clashed against my moral conscience, but the tears of those who are right in that situation is &lt;em&gt;AT LEAST&lt;/em&gt; the same as mine,
and more. So acknowledging that, while my ideals remain to be advocating non-violent response, I can understand the impulse and need
to unleash violence by some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it is difficult for me to come to terms morally to the use of violence. In fact, at times I have difficulties to come to
terms with being angry as one school drama teacher questioned my ability to be angry; “can you actually be angry for once?”
Compounded with the possibility and reality&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, that those who have enacted violence are not necessarily doing so with care for
others, whether they be the police or protesters, it becomes harder for me to square with the violence. While violence
has justified itself throughout history to play a central role in the development of humanity for better or worse, I just don’t
know if this is the time for violence for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;to-black-readers&quot;&gt;To black readers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know how you perceive my writing. Is it with disdain? Disagreement? Disgust? Sadness? Regardless of what you think of me,
I want you to know that you matter, and that your life certainly matter. No one can say otherwise, and I hope you will always
bring that sense of worth with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;to-all-readers&quot;&gt;To all readers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes in dealing with others’ experience, our mind starts churning. We start to rationalize others’ experience try in the name
of objectivity and critical thinking to break down experience into minute facts, of which is formed through our own understanding.
In doing so, when our understanding and experience is mismatch with the reality experienced by the other, we start to question
the legitimacy of their claims. As I underwent reflection for this post, countless times I have done this myself, putting myself
at the seat and lens of rationality. The progress of science have put a moral (or at least goodness) pedestal for objectivity,
the analytical mind, the scientist within us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But rewinding my senses to the time when I watched the video of George Floyd’s death it wasn’t objectivity that first shock me,
it was the sadness and the desire to scream &lt;strong&gt;STOP!&lt;/strong&gt; towards the police officers despite seeing it though a monitor. The first
thing that connected and captured us within the tragedy was not our mind, but our hearts and emotion. Yes, being analytical has its time,
but we are not animals of pure rationality either, having both thoughts and feelings. As such I hope we can all learn and continue to channel
our hearts and feelings for the compassion of others, as many of us would fail to understand the lived experience, but can still share
our emotions with one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;footnotes-and-resources&quot;&gt;Footnotes and resources&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1BRlF2_zhNe86SGgHa6-VlBO-QgirITwCTugSfKie5Fs/preview?pru=AAABcqYzb90*BLtlNH3BbTokzzKkcpKSiQ&quot;&gt;A list of resources&lt;/a&gt; if you are interested in understanding racism, particularly in NA context. Treat it as something ongoing in your life if you decide to use the resources&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://aeon.co/essays/anger-is-a-valuable-emotion-driving-private-and-public-good&quot;&gt;anger and how they can connect us together&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VlsKDIn6ecs&quot;&gt;Angee Floyd thriving as a black woman far away from her home&lt;/a&gt;, a showcase of the capabilities of black people. I feel like I won’t ever be able to do what she did&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_q4D8wpYaR0&quot;&gt;Multiple black people feeling safe outside of America&lt;/a&gt;. As someone who has lived in Japan I can attest to the feeling of safety in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;One such man who said to just do something was Tyrone Edwards in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H0gdHA-W5hA&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/564299/how-to-be-an-antiracist-by-ibram-x-kendi/&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; made by Ibram X. Kendi talks specifically about being an &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;anti-racist&lt;/code&gt;. I haven’t gotten to the book myself &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8e1ld1uGpXA&quot;&gt;A woman lecturing on what seems to be “protesters”&lt;/a&gt; on their destructive tendencies on the properties that a community relies on. Meanwhile these “protesters” can only give vain cheers and empty nods &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">What is this post about?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The best course at SFU was a Sociology course</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/05/24/the-best-sfu-course-sociology" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The best course at SFU was a Sociology course" /><published>2020-05-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/05/24/the-best-sfu-course-sociology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/05/24/the-best-sfu-course-sociology">&lt;p&gt;For my final term at SFU for the Big Data specialization masters program I was at a decision junction between several courses I can take. I was certain of taking an
NLP (natural language processing) course and only need to take one more elective course besides that. The choice was between &lt;a href=&quot;https://coursys.sfu.ca/2020sp-cmpt-727-g1/pages/&quot;&gt;CMPT 727 - Statistical Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfu.ca/outlines.html?2020/spring/cmns/815/g100&quot;&gt;CMNS 815 - Social Construction of Communication Technologies&lt;/a&gt;. CMPT 727 would clearly complement the whole degree itself and would even go hand in hand with NLP, while CMNS 815 may be argued as more loosely tied to the degree and my overall career path. But I have made a similar decision before in my undergraduate years, between taking statistics or philosophy as my minor. I chose the uncommon philosophy as my choice, and in the same fate spirit as I did before I choise CMNS 815 as my last elective course to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My decision to take philosophy as my undergraduate minor were due to both my interest and benefits. With machine learning and data science on the rise, many would
probably I missed out on the opportunity as statistical capabilities would help me transition with more ease to such roles. Personally I disagree, firstly because
statistics is not something I’m particularly fond of learning (it is one of the more difficult areas of mathematics for me to get a handle on), and secondly
I felt that zoning in on a technical field would make me too technically inclined. I prefer to be more balanced and rounded in both discipline and worldview.
These same reasons apply when I chose CMNS 815 over CMPT 727. I knew that I am neither greatly interested in statistics or machine learning (I prefer building and
designing software) and that CMNS 815 would help me see technology in a broder social context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-learned&quot;&gt;What I learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMNS 815 in a nutshell was examining how technologies not just impact, but play a role in the shaping of society, cultures and worldviews. The technologies discussed
were not constraint to the technologies we are so wary of these days such as social media, surveillance cameras, computers but also to clocks, institutions, language
and many more things that in this day and age we would not immediately associate with the word “technology”. Perhaps it is better to replace “technology” with the term
“tools of life” to capture the broad sense of technology covered. But the course isn’t about isolating particular social phenomena or impact to a particular technology,
but it attempted to use particular case studies of technology to bring about understanding and appreciation of how technology &lt;em&gt;MAY&lt;/em&gt; impact society. Example of topics
include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;distributed agency, realizing objects (technologies) can express a form of choice and greatly affect our own sense of agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the subtle yet powerful classifications made by technologies and their designers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the encoding of humanity in something that is not human, such as data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;importance and power of language and metaphors in how we think of the world including technologies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ethics and how technologists grapple with ethical needs and perceived moral stances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shaping behaviour through technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and many more…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-i-value-it-so-much&quot;&gt;Why I value it so much&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from my own interests the professor Sun Ha Hong who teched the course was clearly keen, knowledgeable and empathetic. Combined with my own personal interests,
it made the class much more enjoyable. The small class size (7 people in total) was also beneficial as thre were a lot of opportunities, designed or ad-hoc, to engage
with students and exchange pointers. Above all however is the diversity of topics, while also maintaining an approachable depth so as to not just be a skim of topics.
As a professional working in software, there are seldom any encouragement or endorsed professional opportunity to expand insights beyond the usual technical realm.
Having guidance in the vast discourse of social topics helps me expand my understanding and appreciation in a manageable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a software engineer I wanted to be better at wrestling and engaging with the social consequences of my own work and the profession itself. I came to CMNS 815 with
that hope, and I felt it did better prepare me for future challenges. Certainly, the spotlights given by media these days pressured me to thinking that I should be
able to balance the ethical and social good with monetary results. But I am also of the conviction that positively navigating the social dilemmas of our creation
should be a nurtured and expected ability of software engineers. This course helped me forward to realize that conviction in my own professional life. Sure, the
chances of being asked about the social issues of technology in an interview will likely not crop up. Open discussion of them might not even happen reasonably often,
and my colleagues may show little interest. However, I see this knowledge and experience as my little edge over others, and I can proudly say that I am not afraid to
reflect on the muddy social issues of the software I had built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a culmination of what I had learnt I wrote a paper on cryptocurrency and trust (maybe I will cover it in some future time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-recommendation-to-you&quot;&gt;My recommendation to you&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are an SFU student and you can afford to take this course, take this course. If you happen to find a similar course somewhere else take it. I’m obviously biased,
and well aware that such my fellow software engineers (or perhaps technologists in general) are not really inclined to take such courses. I understand, between
learning something that can have immediate clear gains to your professional and personal life (learning some new language) vs a course like CMNS 815, many would choose
the former. Yet I can’t help to recommend this course least because of the knowledge and experience I had gained, and more so due to how I throughly enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">For my final term at SFU for the Big Data specialization masters program I was at a decision junction between several courses I can take. I was certain of taking an NLP (natural language processing) course and only need to take one more elective course besides that. The choice was between CMPT 727 - Statistical Machine Learning and CMNS 815 - Social Construction of Communication Technologies. CMPT 727 would clearly complement the whole degree itself and would even go hand in hand with NLP, while CMNS 815 may be argued as more loosely tied to the degree and my overall career path. But I have made a similar decision before in my undergraduate years, between taking statistics or philosophy as my minor. I chose the uncommon philosophy as my choice, and in the same fate spirit as I did before I choise CMNS 815 as my last elective course to take.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reboot</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/05/19/reboot" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reboot" /><published>2020-05-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/05/19/reboot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2020/05/19/reboot">&lt;p&gt;The first time I tried blogging was back in 2017. Like now, back then I had the same thought of “hey why not start blogging, it will be good for experience and maybe
it will be helpful for people”. But then I stopped, and here I am again trying to make blog posts. One time I had an interview for a job and the interviewee asked me
what do in my personal time to which I said I &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; to blog, which the interviewee of course asked “why did you stop?” It was a hard question to answer on the spot,
because I knew that the truthful answer does not put me in a good spotlight. The reasons why I stopped blogging was…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lazy&quot;&gt;Lazy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lazy. I felt the need to keep making posts and coming up with things to talk about (as if I was getting any readership, I didn’t even promote or manage my blog’s
SEO). That feeling of needing to make posts in a consistent basis, if not for the views at least for self-improvement, was honestly not fun to do. And it created
this feeling of pressure to do it, like a dreaded homework that you keep procastinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scared&quot;&gt;Scared&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was scared. Even though I knew I wasn’t necessarily getting any readership (I didn’t set up analytics but most probably did not), I was scared at putting my thoughts
in the public domain. I was scared if the presentation was good enough, are the words I chose appropriate, is my post controversial, is it relatable etc. etc. I have
a knack for overthinking and finding different possibilities, and surely I did and it kind of overwhelmed me funnily enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-different-now&quot;&gt;What’s different now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only recently entertained the idea of blogging again. It’s not to kill time during the COVID-19 pandemic but because I still do have desires to express my thoughts
in some concrete manner, which blogging helps with. It’s also a way for me to have my own little personal “product” that I can work on bit by bit. So there is both
personal and professional reasons to why I am restarting blogging. To help overcome the reasons why I stopped blogging, here are several things I want to stick to as
much as possible:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not hoping to gain viewership. I want to make this blog grow for now for myself and I don’t want to be caught up on “advertising”, which also includes feeling forced
to make posts in a consistent timeframe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focusing on creating honest but quality written work. I want to emphasize on the honesty part first, and then worry about presentation and stringent professionalism
second&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enjoy it more! Honestly, I need to enjoy my own creative work more and enjoy the process of it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be sticking my best to these guidelines&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">The first time I tried blogging was back in 2017. Like now, back then I had the same thought of “hey why not start blogging, it will be good for experience and maybe it will be helpful for people”. But then I stopped, and here I am again trying to make blog posts. One time I had an interview for a job and the interviewee asked me what do in my personal time to which I said I used to blog, which the interviewee of course asked “why did you stop?” It was a hard question to answer on the spot, because I knew that the truthful answer does not put me in a good spotlight. The reasons why I stopped blogging was…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Values and AI</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2017/06/16/values-and-AI" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Values and AI" /><published>2017-06-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-06-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2017/06/16/values-and-AI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2017/06/16/values-and-AI">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://si.wsj.net/public/resources/images/BI-AA979_AI_GR_20150506144558.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Thinking, thinking, thinking, always thinking&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago I read the following article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/a-blueprint-for-coexistence-with-artificial-intelligence/&quot;&gt;AI and jobs&lt;/a&gt;
. The author, Mr. Kai-Fu Lee goes back a bit telling his tale, a near death experience, continued with regret and then resolving it into a vision for the current
and upcoming age of AI. In the article he argued that in order for us to co-exist (take not he didn’t say &lt;em&gt;to win&lt;/em&gt;) with AI is for us to create avenues in life    , particularly jobs that takes advantage and relies on our humanity. The specific quality which he propose to be a solution to the job-market-wrecking-AI problem
is &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt;. Mr. Lee did mention other qualities which we often think are intrinsically tied to what makes us humans, but the main thing is love. 
Mr. Lee’s article then made me thinking about values and AI, and I’ve thought of several things. So let’s continue and read them below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-value-of-data&quot;&gt;The value of data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have heard by now the wise words “Knowledge is power” (to which I agree). And you may have heard “Data is the new oil”, that is data is the basis of our
current age, just like oil was in the 18th century. But of course humanity has amassed knowledge and data for so many years, past decades and centuries, though they
do say most of our amassed data has been created in the past few years. You get the idea though, we’ve been gathering data for many years now and now with the
advancement of technology the data we have stacked up and gathered that have been left to dust previously are being picked up and consumed. We feed our computers,
servers, models with data and create products and services out of them. Where previously data was just lying there seemingly dead without much use (aside for a
select group of entities, like Google which really have the resources and expertise), now our world is inundated with data and so called &lt;i&gt;data-driven decision&lt;/i&gt;.
Through technology we have managed to extract and find value in data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extending-the-value-of-data-with-ai&quot;&gt;Extending the value of data with AI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s AI, which like Mr. Lee said, really is another piece of technology that consumes and tries to get value out of our data. But it not only extracts
value out of data, AI also extrapolates value out of our data. It creates models, decisions, predictions, generalizations out of our data and use them on
complex subjects it may have never seen and which we like to solve or get better at. AI enables things like self-driving cars, better more relevant ads, AlphaGo
possible. To add to that, with current advances in technology and research AI has really taken off not just in complexity but also speed and availability. AI
has taken the value of data a step further by enabling the ability to create services and products that really wouldn’t have been able to take off without it
(think self-driving cars). Though at the same time it has made several of our jobs redundant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extending-the-value-of-ai&quot;&gt;Extending the value of AI?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that AI has given us so much value, where do we go from here on? How do we keep ourselves relevant in a world where technology and AI has been able to eke out
value out of data, the resource that is believed to be most crucial in our age, better (arguably) and faster (definitely) than we ourselves can? Mr. Lee’s proposed
solution is more akin to complementing that rather than extending on it. Rather than trying to come up with a way in which we can possibly do better than AI, or
add something to AI’s results which it cannot do itself, to him it is better to to work alongside AI and let us be complemented and also to complement it with our
inherent humanistic qualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem-is&quot;&gt;The problem is…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea itself is fine in my opinion, but the execution may not be so simple. I’m pretty sure there are many more people who are far more qualified than me
to talk about AI and how to solve the possibility of us being runover by AI. But despite the many influential and capable people out there it seems the fear and
worry has not gone away and no actual implemented solution is on the way. At best it’s because the problem is inherently hard to formulate and to solve in a way
that can satisfy the vast majority of our world. At worst… it’s because we really don’t know think there are significant value we can gain from our inherent
humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay I doubt it’s as bad as I purport, but I do think the thought has some merit. At the very least I do think we don’t give enough objective and appreciation
to our humanistic qualities. For example, I’m sure most if not all of us would agree that a great and caring parent goes a long way in the upbringing of a child and
their future. A child that is brought up well and with great care probably has less risks to incur mental health problems which may be related to their environment.
So those kids in the future can be healthier, and less cost is needed to maintain his or her mental health. A great parent also seems likely to enable their child
to attain greater heights, and thus higher social contribution in the future. These are all valuable things for us and our society and have direct or indirect
consequence to our economy, but I’m not aware of any widespread economic measurement that takes into account quality of parenthood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many other humanistic qualities which I am sure we do value in our life, but are not given it’s due appreciation and value in an objective manner.
Whether that objective quantification or assessment is in terms of monetary value, or recognition, or something else, I do think we are lacking in that aspect.
This is a problem that is not inherent in AI but in us, in how we see, value and think of life, of ourselves. If we are to complement the value of our AI with
value inherent in us, then we must be able to value our human capabilities and existence in ourselves and in others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrapping-up&quot;&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Mr. Lee’s blueprint, though barebones, is something agreeable. Rather than battling our way through data and AI’s inherent ability to qucikly and accurately
derive value out of data we should strive to look into ourselves ways in which we can bring about value through our own nature. As AI achieves feats which
we have previously only associated with humans we would need to branch out to other areas, whether to compete or to co-exist with AI. But branching out would also
entail our desire and ability to find value in those areas, a problem which I think we, as humans and society, need to solve by ourselves and re-align
our values.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><category term="[&quot;old-post&quot;, &quot;AI&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Thinking, thinking, thinking, always thinking</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Balance in life</title><link href="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2017/04/04/balance-in-life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Balance in life" /><published>2017-04-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-04-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2017/04/04/balance-in-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://btruhand.github.io/blog/post/2017/04/04/balance-in-life">&lt;p&gt;Around 1 year and a month ago I started working in Japan. Perhaps many of you have heard on the harsh conditions of long working hours in Japan and incidents of
suicide by death and other such depressing stories. Being faced with such a possibility I put myself in a staunch position to maintain a clear distinction between personal
and work life and not to let one or the other, particularly the work aspect, negatively impact on the other. And of course this is what many of us refer to as work-life
balance, maintaining an equilibrium between work and personal life. But there’s more to this than simply about work-life balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After establishing my stance on my work-life balance, I started to think about all kinds of balance in life, having realized how important it is in general in our lives.
As an example, during people’s daily work, we  have a stack of to-do list everyday and sometimes I would need to find the balance between, in
terms of time spent, working on task A compared to all other tasks. As another example, when we buy products many of us would weight in between the price vs value of
a service or good. Yet in another example we talk about maintaining a balanced diet for our health. It would seem that balance is quite prevalent in our life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick skim of balance led me to the believe that balance is important and prevalent in our life, which leads me to the question: how well are we at creating, identifying
and maintaining balance? I’m asking this not so much on the perspective of human’s innate ability but more so on our surroundings. A lot of our time is spent in improving ourselves
or just doing a small set of core activities, and there are advices to continue doing so. Just as an example, there’s quite a lot of advices to maintain focus in order to get into
an Ivy League school, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.prepscholar.com/how-to-get-into-harvard-and-the-ivy-league-by-a-harvard-alum&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/How-can-I-get-into-an-Ivy-League-college/answer/Arvin-Chang?srid=7d08&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
On the other hand many of us grew up in an environment in school that exposed us to all kinds of activities by having us take a diverse set of subjects in 12 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet again at work and at other times we are asked to focus and present the main points, while in the process of focusing on the main points we are asked to consider alternatives,
balancing our view points. We’re told to find and focus on the things and people that matter, at the same time we’re told by articles to travel and explore and find something new to do,
to be adventurous. People want us to be nice, but at the same time we shouldn’t make ourselves exposed to danger. In showing these examples I think there is one thing that we can consider:
we have a love with balance and at the same time we have a love in focus. And between our love for focus and our love for balance, we have the meta question of how do we balance between the two?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might not have a universal answer to the question, but I do believe that a possible answer is that that each of us not only have a common sense of balance but also a personal
sense. My sense of work-life balance is most likely not the same as Elon Musk, who just made another venture into a brain-computer company and still managing 3 other companies. Your sense
of good to safety balance is probably not the same as mine as people have different levels of good they are comfortable in displaying. What I think is balanced may not necessarily be
what you think is balanced. A lot of it really comes down to identifying and being aware of personal value and adjusting as needed. It’s more of a part of the art of living than it is
the science of living. That’s my take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certainly a lot of talk about focus, and a lot of talk about balance, and sometimes one will prevail over another out of necessity but there are also times we would need to
balance between the two. In between the myriad of advices for such situations I just think there is little talk in reconciling the two. Having being so conscious on balancing my own life
made me realize the relevance of it and how it is so intrinsic to our lives, because if you go over some of the examples I gave a lot of balancing we do is for the sake of maximizing
or minimizing results, something we humans put a lot of attention into.  The sense of balance you have now may not be the best it can be, but I think if only we can identify them we put
ourselves in a better position to create a balanced life by simply being aware of it. Cheers to a personally balanced life.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>btruhand</name><email>btruhand@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Around 1 year and a month ago I started working in Japan. Perhaps many of you have heard on the harsh conditions of long working hours in Japan and incidents of suicide by death and other such depressing stories. Being faced with such a possibility I put myself in a staunch position to maintain a clear distinction between personal and work life and not to let one or the other, particularly the work aspect, negatively impact on the other. And of course this is what many of us refer to as work-life balance, maintaining an equilibrium between work and personal life. But there’s more to this than simply about work-life balance.</summary></entry></feed>